<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>

    <string name="geological_time_scale">Geological time scale</string>

    <string name="environment">Environment</string>
    <string name="general_information">Description</string>
    <string name="life_forms">Life</string>

    <string name="map_author_1">&#169; Masato Hattori</string>
    <string name="map_author_2">&#169; C. R. Scotese</string>

    <string name="mya">%s mya</string>

    <string name="hadean">Hadean</string>
    <string name="archean">Archean</string>
    <string name="proterozoic">Proterozoic</string>
    <string name="cambrian">Cambrian</string>
    <string name="ordovician">Ordovician</string>
    <string name="silurian">Silurian</string>
    <string name="devonian">Devonian</string>
    <string name="carboniferous">Carboniferous</string>
    <string name="permian">Permian</string>
    <string name="triassic">Triassic</string>
    <string name="jurassic">Jurassic</string>
    <string name="cretaceous">Cretaceous</string>
    <string name="paleogene">Paleogene</string>
    <string name="neogene">Neogene</string>
    <string name="quaternary">Quaternary</string>
    <string name="future">Future</string>

    <string name="hadean_short_description">Early Earth formation, first water.</string>
    <string name="archean_short_description">Single-celled life traces, first oxygen. Photosynthesis.</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_short_description">Multi-celled life traces, atmospheric oxygen. Global glaciations.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_short_description">Modern complex life appearance.</string>
    <string name="ordovician_short_description">Modern life diversification trends continue.</string>
    <string name="silurian_short_description">First terrestrial plants.</string>
    <string name="devonian_short_description">First terrestrial tetrapods.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_short_description">Times of the large forests and insects. Pangaea formation.</string>
    <string name="permian_short_description">Arid Earth period. Largest mass extinction in the Earth history.</string>
    <string name="triassic_short_description">First mammals and dinosaurs.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_short_description">Dinosaur dominance. Division of the Pangaea.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_short_description">Flowering plants appearance. Dinosaur extinction.</string>
    <string name="paleogene_short_description">Mammal dominance. Eocene thermal maximum.</string>
    <string name="neogene_short_description">Modern fauna formation. First hominids.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_short_description">Time of the Ice Ages. Current times.</string>
    <string name="future_short_description">Who knows.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="hadean_physics">Mean temperature: 70&#8211;2100 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 0%</string>
    <string name="hadean_description">Hadean Eon – the earliest period of Earth\'s history, spanning from the planet\'s formation approximately 4.56 billion years ago until the emergence of stable tectonic plates around 4.0 billion years ago.\nThe landscape of the Early Hadean was extremely hostile, resembling a hellish environment. The surface was dominated by widespread volcanic activity, molten rock, and frequent bombardment by meteorites and comets.\nThe first 100 million years were far too inhospitable for any form of life, with surface temperatures reaching around 230 degrees Celsius—and in the earliest stages, even exceeding 2000 degrees Celsius. Atmospheric pressure was estimated to be about 27 times higher than today. While Earth possessed a primitive atmosphere, it was repeatedly stripped away by intense collisions with other celestial bodies.\nAround 4.4 billion years ago, the planet began to cool, as evidenced by zircon crystals, which suggest the presence of liquid water during this period. The end of the Hadean Eon is marked by the stabilization of Earth\'s crust, the formation of early oceans, and the beginnings of continental crust.</string>
    <string name="hadean_additional_title"></string>
    <string name="hadean_additional"></string>
    <string name="hadean_life_forms">There is no definitive proof that life could have existed in such a harsh environment. However, 4.1-billion-year-old graphite deposits found in Western Australia contain carbon isotopes that suggest possible biological origins, indicating that conditions for life may have been sustainable earlier than previously thought. Some scientists hypothesize that life may have emerged multiple times during the Hadean Eon, only to be repeatedly annihilated by catastrophic asteroid impacts and extreme volcanic activity. Additionally, carbon-rich meteorites, which delivered organic molecules to early Earth, support the idea that the building blocks of life may have originated in space.</string>

    <string name="archean_physics">Mean temperature: 45&#8211;70 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 0%</string>
    <string name="archean_description">The Archean Eon – the second eon in Earth\'s history – spans from approximately 4.0 billion years ago, when the first tectonic plates began to form, to around 2.5 billion years ago, just before the Great Oxidation Event.\nAt the beginning of this eon, Earth\'s temperature was 2–3 times higher than today. This was primarily due to a high concentration of greenhouse gases (dozens of times higher than today) and residual heat from planetary accretion and core formation.\nDuring this period, the Sun\'s luminosity was about 70–75% of its present level, leading to a \"faint young Sun paradox\", which was mitigated by the greenhouse effect. By the end of the Archean, Earth\'s tectonic activity had evolved into a more modern-like system, and vast oceans of liquid water covered much of the planet, providing the conditions for the emergence of early microbial life.</string>
    <string name="archean_additional_title">Late heavy bombardment</string>
    <string name="archean_additional">Around 4.0 billion years ago, the planets of our solar system, including Earth, experienced intense bombardment by large cosmic bodies for approximately 200 million years. This period, known as the Late Heavy Bombardment (LHB), is evidenced by lunar samples collected by Apollo astronauts, which contain high-impact melt formations.\nExtrapolating lunar cratering rates to Earth at this time suggests that the planet would have experienced:\n1. Approximately 22,000 craters with diameters greater than 20 km.\n2. Around 40 craters with diameters exceeding 1,000 km.\n3. Several craters with diameters close to 5,000 km.\nThe prevailing hypothesis for this bombardment is that the giant planets—such as Jupiter, Saturn, and Neptune—underwent orbital migration. This gravitational disturbance scattered objects from the asteroid and/or Kuiper belts into eccentric orbits, increasing the impact rate on the inner planets. This event may have delayed the emergence of life during the Early Archean by creating a hostile surface environment through frequent, high-energy impacts.</string>
    <string name="archean_life_forms">Unlike in the Hadean, the presence of life during the Archean is well established, though the exact timing of its emergence remains debated.\nThe earliest solid evidence of life comes from 3.48-billion-year-old stromatolites found in Australia and 3.77–4.28-billion-year-old microfossils discovered in Canadian rocks. Additionally, 3.85-billion-year-old isotopic signatures in Greenland suggest biological activity, though their interpretation is contested.\nBanded iron formations (BIFs) also date back to this period. While some argue that their formation required oxygen from early photosynthetic microbes, others suggest alternative abiotic processes could have played a role.\nPossible early prokaryotes have been identified in Canadian rocks at least 3.77 billion years old, and lipid biomarker analysis suggests that the first eukaryotes may have emerged by the late Archean, around 2.7 billion years ago.</string>

    <string name="proterozoic_physics">Mean temperature: 5&#8211;45 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 0&#8211;12%</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_description">The Proterozoic Eon – the third major eon in Earth\'s history, spanning from approximately 2.5 billion to 541 million years ago, just before the widespread emergence of complex life. Key events of this eon include the transition to an oxygen-rich atmosphere during the Great Oxidation Event, multiple global glaciations (such as those associated with the Snowball Earth hypothesis during the Huronian, Sturtian, and Marinoan glaciations), and the evolution of early multicellular eukaryotic organisms, including soft-bodied life forms like those of the Ediacaran biota.\nThis is a hypothetical reconstruction of a Snowball Earth scenario during the Huronian and Cryogenian glaciations.</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_additional_title">Great Oxidation Event</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_additional">The Great Oxidation Event was the biologically induced rise of oxygen in Earth\'s atmosphere, occurring around 2.4 to 2.1 billion years ago. The widely accepted hypothesis states that the primary driver of this event was the evolution of oxygenic photosynthesis in cyanobacteria.\nBefore this event, any free oxygen produced was rapidly consumed by chemical reactions with dissolved iron or organic matter. However, once these oxygen sinks became saturated, excess oxygen began accumulating in the atmosphere.\nFree oxygen is toxic to obligate anaerobic organisms, leading to a major extinction event. Additionally, atmospheric oxygen reacted with methane, a potent greenhouse gas, significantly lowering its concentration. This process likely triggered the Huronian glaciation, which lasted approximately 300 million years (from ~2.4 to ~2.1 billion years ago).\nThese profound changes in Earth\'s atmospheric and chemical cycles created new evolutionary pressures and opportunities. Life adapted first to tolerate and then to harness atmospheric oxygen, leading to the development of aerobic respiration. This metabolic breakthrough vastly increased the available energy supply, enabling the evolution of more complex, multicellular organisms.</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_life_forms">The Proterozoic Eon marks a crucial transition in the evolution of life, from simple unicellular organisms to more complex forms. During the Great Oxidation Event, many anaerobic organisms declined due to oxygen toxicity, while oxygen-tolerant and aerobic life forms, including early eukaryotic protists and bacteria, proliferated. By the mid-Proterozoic, stromatolites—microbial reef-like structures built by cyanobacteria—reached their peak diversity. During this time, the ancestors of fungi diverged from the ancestors of animals, marking an important evolutionary split within eukaryotes. By the Ediacaran Period (635–541 million years ago), the first complex, soft-bodied multicellular organisms had appeared, including members of the enigmatic Ediacaran biota, which represent some of the earliest known macroscopic life forms.</string>

    <string name="cambrian_physics">Mean temperature: 21 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 12.5%</string>
    <string name="cambrian_description">The Cambrian Period was the first geological period of the Paleozoic Era and marked a profound transformation in life on Earth. Before the Cambrian, most living organisms were microscopic and relatively simple. However, the Cambrian saw an unprecedented diversification of life in an event known as the Cambrian Explosion. During this time, many major animal phyla first appeared in the fossil record, and complex ecosystems emerged.\nThe great glaciers of the late Proterozoic Eon had long melted, leading to high sea levels that flooded vast areas of continents with warm, shallow seas—an ideal environment for marine life. The Earth was generally cool during the Early Cambrian, likely due to the supercontinent Gondwana covering the South Pole, which disrupted polar ocean currents. However, global temperatures were still around 7°C higher than today. While polar ice caps and glaciations may have existed, the climate gradually warmed toward the end of the period. Glaciers retreated, sea levels rose dramatically, and this warming trend continued into the Ordovician Period.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_additional_title">The Cambrian Explosion</string>
    <string name="cambrian_additional">The Cambrian Explosion was a relatively brief evolutionary event, during which approximately 63% of all biological classes and most of the major modern animal phyla first appeared. This period saw the emergence of complex ecosystems, with the development of burrowing behaviors and the widespread diversification of skeletonized animals, which were previously absent or rare.\nPossible causes of this evolutionary event:\n1. Increased atmospheric oxygen levels, which supported larger and more complex organisms.\n2. The formation of an ozone layer, reducing the harmful effects of ultraviolet (UV) radiation and enabling life to thrive in shallower waters.\n3. The Snowball Earth events during the late Proterozoic, which led to mass extinctions and opened up ecological niches for new life forms.\n4. Higher calcium concentrations in Cambrian seawater, allowing marine organisms to develop skeletons, shells, and other hard body structures.\n5. Developmental changes, including the evolution of Hox genes, which played a key role in organizing body plans and enabling more complex organisms to form.\n6. Changes in the food web, leading to coevolution and predator-prey “arms races” that drove anatomical and behavioral innovations.\nThe Cambrian was also a time of evolutionary experimentation, resulting in many bizarre and unique body plans, some of which have no modern descendants.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_life_forms">Most animal life during the Cambrian was aquatic. Arthropods were by far the most dominant animals in the ocean, with trilobites being particularly abundant. This period also saw the emergence of many new mineralized organisms, as well as the first widespread burrowing animals, which played a key role in reshaping seafloor ecosystems. However, unlike in modern times, most animals lived on or near the sea floor, with very few swimming or pelagic species.</string>

    <string name="ordovician_physics">Mean temperature: 16 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 13.5%</string>
    <string name="ordovician_description">The Ordovician is the second of six periods of the Paleozoic Era. During this period, ancient oceans separated the largely barren continents of Laurentia, Baltica, Siberia, and the supercontinent Gondwana. The Ordovician saw a great diversification of marine life, including the rise of early corals, cephalopods, and the first jawless fish. However, the period ended with one of the most severe ice ages in Earth’s history, leading to the second-largest mass extinction, which wiped out around 85% of marine species. Ice sheets covered much of the southern region of Gondwana, dramatically altering global sea levels and climate.</string>
    <string name="ordovician_additional_title">Ordovician Radiation</string>
    <string name="ordovician_additional">The Ordovician period is notable for the Great Ordovician Biodiversification Event (GOBE), a time of rapid biological diversification that replaced the distinctive Cambrian fauna with a Paleozoic fauna rich in suspension feeders and pelagic animals. This event followed the Cambrian-Ordovician extinction, which was likely caused by a sudden glaciation and a depletion of available oxygen in the oceans.\nThe primary driver of the Ordovician radiation was a major shift in paleogeography. Due to high sea levels, continents became highly fragmented into distinct marine provinces, fostering regional biodiversity. Intense orogeny (mountain-building events), along with increased erosion, contributed to high ecosystem productivity by delivering abundant nutrients into the oceans.\nWhile the Cambrian Explosion was crucial in establishing most modern animal phyla, the GOBE can be seen as the event that diversified these phyla into modern classes and lower-level taxa, significantly shaping marine ecosystems that would persist for millions of years.</string>
    <string name="ordovician_life_forms">Life during the Ordovician continued to flourish, with an explosion of marine biodiversity, including the rise of the first coral reefs, trilobites, brachiopods, mollusks, and the first true vertebrates—jawless fish. However, the period ended with a catastrophic mass extinction at the boundary with the Silurian. This extinction was primarily driven by severe global cooling, glaciation, and associated sea-level changes. Despite this, the fauna that emerged and thrived during the Ordovician laid the foundation for marine ecosystems throughout the remainder of the Paleozoic Era.</string>

    <string name="silurian_physics">Mean temperature: 17 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 14%</string>
    <string name="silurian_description">The Silurian is a relatively short geological period, lasting approximately 24 to 28 million years. During this time, Laurentia collided with Baltica, closing the northern branch of the Iapetus Ocean and forming the "Old Red Sandstone" continent. Coral reefs thrived, becoming more widespread and diverse, and the first vascular land plants began to colonize the previously barren continents, marking a significant evolutionary step in the history of life on land.</string>
    <string name="silurian_additional_title">Terrestrial plant diversification</string>
    <string name="silurian_additional">The evolutionary appearance of vascular plants dramatically altered Earth\'s environment, paving the way for animal life on land and fundamentally changing Earth\'s atmosphere. Interestingly, plant evolution progressed much faster than animal evolution: during the Late Silurian, plants were structurally simple and small, but by the end of the Devonian (approximately 46 million years later), almost all present-day plant lineages (except flowering plants) had emerged.\nOne possible explanation is that adapting to terrestrial life posed a greater challenge for plants than for animals. At the level of the individual organism, all plants (except parasitic ones) must perform four essential functions to grow and survive:\n1. Intercept sunlight.\n2. Exchange atmospheric gases with the environment.\n3. Acquire, transport, and conserve water.\n4. Cope with external mechanical forces.\nThese tasks are interdependent and often conflict with one another. For example: a) Increasing surface area to capture more sunlight and facilitate gas exchange can reduce water conservation. b) Positioning leaves horizontally to maximize light interception increases mechanical stress.\nAquatic environments are relatively uniform and stable, while terrestrial environments are affected by wind, temperature changes, unpredictable precipitation, and varying sunlight. Adapting to diverse terrestrial conditions required innovative solutions for each of the basic functions, leading to significant diversification in plant body forms.\nAdditionally, greater exposure to ultraviolet light above the wate\'s surface likely caused more mutations, accelerating evolutionary changes. However, the theory of plant fitness—how well plants adapted to the challenges of terrestrial life—best explains the rapid evolution of land plants.</string>
    <string name="silurian_life_forms">Multicellular life began to appear on land in the form of small, bryophyte-like and early vascular plants that grew near lakes, streams, and coastlines. The Silurian period also marked the first appearance of arthropods on land, including primitive millipedes and arachnids. However, terrestrial life would not significantly diversify or impact the landscape until the Devonian period.\nA major evolutionary milestone during the Silurian was the diversification of bony fishes (Osteichthyes), which began to dominate marine ecosystems. This diversification laid the foundation for the evolution of many modern fish lineages.</string>

    <string name="devonian_physics">Mean temperature: 20 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 15%</string>
    <string name="devonian_description">The Devonian is the fourth of the six periods of the Paleozoic era. It was a relatively warm period, though occasionally disrupted by glaciations. The climate was generally arid, particularly near the equator. During this time, the Early Paleozoic oceans were gradually closing, leading to the formation of a “pre-Pangea” supercontinent. This continental configuration allowed fish to migrate from the southern hemisphere continents to North America and Europe. For the first time, extensive forests appeared in the equatorial regions of what is now Arctic Canada. The period concluded with the Late Devonian extinction, which resulted in the loss of about 50% of all genera, significantly impacting marine life, including many fish and reef-building organisms.</string>
    <string name="devonian_additional_title">The Late Devonian extinction</string>
    <string name="devonian_additional" formatted="false">The Late Devonian extinction was one of the five major extinction events in Earth\'s history. Rather than being a single event, it consisted of a series of two major crises known as the Kellwasser and Hangenberg events. It is estimated that around 75% of all animal species disappeared during this time. The extinction primarily affected marine life, severely impacting groups such as brachiopods, trilobites, and reef-building organisms, which almost completely collapsed. Major fish groups like Placodermi, Heterostraci, and Anaspida were completely wiped out. The extinction event destroyed approximately 97% of all vertebrate species, with only smaller forms surviving. In the aftermath, no sharks larger than a meter and almost no fishes or tetrapods larger than 10 centimeters remained, and it would take around 10 million years before they began to increase in size again. However, despite its catastrophic impact, the Late Devonian extinction crucially paved the way for the evolution of modern vertebrate fauna, including actinopterygians (ray-finned fishes), chondrichthyans (cartilaginous fishes), and tetrapods.\nThe crash in biodiversity during the Late Devonian was more drastic than the famous mass extinction event at the end of the Cretaceous.\nThe causes of this extinction event remain uncertain. Some proposed explanations include:\n1. An asteroid impact.\n2. Evolutionary changes in plants, particularly the development of root systems, which led to massive water eutrophication and subsequent anoxia.\n3. A reduction in atmospheric carbon dioxide, causing global cooling.\n4. Increased magmatism and volcanic activity.</string>
    <string name="devonian_life_forms">Free-sporing vascular plants began to spread across dry land during the Devonian period, covering the continents with extensive forests. By the Middle Devonian, several groups of plants had evolved leaves and true roots, marking significant advancements in plant evolution. Groups such as lycophytes, equisetophytes, and pteridophytes diversified, forming the first complex terrestrial ecosystems.\nFish achieved remarkable diversity during this time, earning the Devonian the nickname “Age of Fish”. Placoderms, armored prehistoric fish, were the most dominant group. The ancestors of tetrapods, particularly lobe-finned fish, began to adapt to walking on land, as their robust pectoral and pelvic fins gradually evolved into legs. These transitional species paved the way for the later evolution of amphibians.\nThe first ammonites (a group of molluscs) appeared, marking an important diversification of marine life. Trilobites and large coral reef systems remained common, with one notable now-dry barrier reef, located in what is now the Kimberley Basin of Northwest Australia, once extending approximately a thousand kilometers.</string>

    <string name="carboniferous_physics">Mean temperature: 14 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 32.5%</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_description">The name "Carboniferous" means “coal-bearing,” referring to the extensive coal deposits formed during this period. In the Early Carboniferous, the Paleozoic oceans between Euramerica and Gondwana began to close, giving rise to mountain ranges such as the Appalachians and the Variscans. A large ice cap developed over the South Pole, while lush, tropical coal swamps near the Equator supported the evolution of four-legged vertebrates (tetrapods) and the first winged insects.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_additional_title">Carboniferous collapse and coal</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_additional">The Carboniferous Rainforest Collapse was a significant ecological event that occurred around 305 million years ago. It disrupted the vast coal forests that once covered the equatorial region, fragmenting them into isolated patches. This fragmentation led to dwarfism and the eventual extinction of many plant and animal species.\nThe collapse resulted in the extinction of dominant lycopsid trees and a shift toward ecosystems dominated by more opportunistic plants like tree ferns. Before the event, animal species were distributed widely across the forests, but afterward, each isolated “island” of rainforest developed its own unique mix of species—this process is known as endemism.\nOxygen levels reached a record high of approximately 32.5% during the Carboniferous, allowing enormous arthropods like Meganeura (a giant dragonfly-like insect) and Arthropleura (a giant millipede-like arthropod) to thrive. However, following the rainforest collapse, oxygen levels declined, leading to the extinction of many of these giants. The increasingly arid climate also caused a mass decline in amphibian diversity, opening ecological space for reptiles to diversify—organisms better suited to dry environments.\nSeveral hypotheses have been proposed to explain the collapse, with the most widely accepted being climate aridification and increased volcanic activity.\nThis event also played a role in the formation of large coal deposits. During the Carboniferous, extensive swamp forests prevented the full decomposition of dead plant material. At the time, few animals or microbes had evolved enzymes to break down tough substances like phenolic lignin and waxy suberin. Fungi capable of decomposing these materials appeared only toward the end of the period, which is one reason why massive coal formation is largely limited to the Carboniferous.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_life_forms">The Carboniferous is renowned for its vast tropical rainforests dominated by towering plants like Lepidodendron, Sigillaria, and Calamites—some of the largest and most extensive forests in Earth’s history. Giant arthropods and insects thrived during this time, aided by high atmospheric oxygen levels and the absence of effective predators. Terrestrial vertebrates became increasingly abundant: amphibians diversified greatly, and following the Carboniferous Rainforest Collapse, reptiles began to flourish due to their better adaptation to drier environments.</string>

    <string name="permian_physics">Mean temperature: 16 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 23%</string>
    <string name="permian_description" formatted="false">The Permian was the final period of the Paleozoic Era, it ended with the most extensive mass extinction in Earth’s history, wiping out approximately 90% of marine species and 70% of terrestrial species. During this time, most of the world\'s landmasses were joined into two large continents—Pangaea and Siberia—surrounded by a vast global ocean called Panthalassa. Western Pangaea was dominated by arid deserts, while reptiles, including early ancestors of mammals, diversified and spread widely across the supercontinent.</string>
    <string name="permian_additional_title">Great Dying</string>
    <string name="permian_additional" formatted="false">The Permian and the entire Paleozoic Era ended 252 million years ago with the most severe mass extinction in Earth\'s history. The Permian-Triassic extinction event, also known as the Great Dying, wiped out about 95% of all marine species and 70% of all terrestrial species.\nMarine environments were hit particularly hard. Entire groups such as acanthodians (spiny sharks), sea scorpions, trilobites (already in decline), fusulinids, and Tabulata and Rugosa corals became completely extinct. Shelled marine animals were severely affected—96% of brachiopod species, 97% of ammonites, 59% of bivalves, and 98% of gastropods perished.\nTerrestrial ecosystems also suffered enormously. Most large tetrapods disappeared, and around 80% of insect species were lost. Paleozoic wet forests, once dominated by ancient plants like Sigillaria, Lepidodendron, and Gigantopteris, were devastated due to widespread aridification and intense wildfires.\nSeveral interlinked causes contributed to this catastrophe:\n1. Massive volcanic eruptions in the region now known as the Siberian Traps released enormous quantities of carbon dioxide, methane, and hydrogen sulfide. These gases drastically altered atmospheric chemistry. Methane reacted with atmospheric oxygen, reducing oxygen levels from 30% to around 13%. The ozone layer was damaged, exposing the surface to harmful ultraviolet radiation. This led to a rapid increase in global temperatures—by as much as 8°C.\n2. Oceans became dangerously deoxygenated. Warmer temperatures reduced oxygen absorption, and toxic gases led to acidification. Acidic water dissolved the calcium carbonate shells of mollusks and corals, leading to their mass extinction. The proliferation of cyanobacteria and microbial mats further consumed what little oxygen remained, turning the seas into anoxic, acidic, nearly lifeless zones.\n3. A temporary weakening of Earth\'s magnetic field may have allowed increased solar radiation to reach the surface, creating extreme seasonal swings with scorching summers followed by bitterly cold winters.\nThe devastation was so profound that ecosystems took over 30 million years to recover their former diversity—not until the Middle Triassic. The extinction selectively eliminated dominant Paleozoic life forms, erasing 79% of their families, while only 27% of the lineages that would come to thrive in the Mesozoic were affected.</string>
    <string name="permian_life_forms">The Permian began with Carboniferous-era plant life still thriving. In the Middle Permian, a major shift in vegetation occurred: swamp-loving lycopod trees such as Lepidodendron and Sigillaria were gradually replaced by more advanced seed ferns like Glossopteris, along with early conifers, ginkgoes, and cycads.\nInsects during this time were dominated by primitive relatives of cockroaches and early dragonflies. Early Permian terrestrial ecosystems were populated by pelycosaurs (sail-backed synapsids like Dimetrodon) and large amphibians. By the Middle Permian, these groups declined and were succeeded by primitive therapsids—mammal-like reptiles. In the Late Permian, more advanced therapsids such as gorgonopsians emerged, becoming top predators.\nToward the very end of the Permian, the first archosaurs appeared—a group that would later evolve into dinosaurs, pterosaurs, and crocodiles. Also emerging in this period were the earliest cynodonts, small therapsids that would eventually give rise to mammals in the Triassic.</string>

    <string name="triassic_physics">Mean temperature: 17 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 16%</string>
    <string name="triassic_description">The Triassic began in the aftermath of the Permian-Triassic extinction event, the most severe extinction in Earth\'s history, which left the biosphere severely impoverished. Life began to recover significantly only by the middle of the Triassic period. \nDuring this time, the supercontinent Pangea was largely assembled, enabling land animals to migrate freely from the South Pole to the North Pole. Additionally, warm-water marine species spread across the vast Tethys Sea, supporting a resurgence of biodiversity in the oceans.</string>
    <string name="triassic_additional_title">The Nocturnal Bottleneck</string>
    <string name="triassic_additional">The nocturnal bottleneck hypothesis explains several unique traits of mammals. According to this hypothesis, mammals were primarily—or even exclusively—nocturnal for most of their early evolutionary history, beginning around 225 million years ago during the Late Triassic and continuing until the extinction of the dinosaurs around 65 million years ago. While some mammal groups later adapted to daytime (diurnal) activity, the approximately 160 million years spent in nocturnal niches left a lasting legacy on their anatomy and physiology. As a result, many mammals today retain nocturnal habits.\nMammals evolved from cynodonts, a group of mammal-like reptiles with dog-like features, in the aftermath of the Permian-Triassic mass extinction. Following this extinction, archosaurian reptiles—including ancestors of crocodiles and dinosaurs—rapidly diversified and came to dominate most ecological roles. This competition pushed the larger cynodonts toward extinction, leaving only smaller, more adaptable forms.\nThese surviving cynodonts likely occupied nocturnal, insect-eating niches with less competition from the dominant, diurnal dinosaurs. Over time, they evolved into early mammals—small-bodied, warm-blooded, and adapted to life in the undergrowth.\nEven after the extinction of the dinosaurs, mammals remained small for millions of years. Although mammals now include many large species, most are still relatively small and active at night.\nThe nocturnal bottleneck hypothesis also offers a compelling explanation for the evolution of mammalian warm-bloodedness (endothermy): cooler nighttime temperatures and burrowing lifestyles would have favored efficient internal temperature regulation and insulation.</string>
    <string name="triassic_life_forms">The Permian-Triassic extinction devastated both terrestrial and marine ecosystems. Although biodiversity began to rebound during the Triassic, early recovery stages were dominated by only a few resilient species. For example, up to 90% of large terrestrial vertebrates initially belonged to a single genus of therapsids—Lystrosaurus—highlighting the severe ecological damage and lack of biodiversity. Complex ecosystems with diverse food webs took nearly 30 million years to fully re-establish.\nBy the Middle Triassic, large therapsids had largely disappeared, and archosaurs—relatives of modern crocodiles, birds, and ancestors of dinosaurs—became the dominant land vertebrates. Dinosaurs began to diversify and gradually establish their dominance by the end of the period.\nOn land, seed plants became increasingly dominant over spore-bearing plants. In the Northern Hemisphere, conifers, ferns, and bennettitales thrived, while in the Southern Hemisphere, Glossopteris trees initially remained prominent before disappearing later in the period.\nLike other geological periods, the Triassic ended with a mass extinction. This event led to the disappearance of conodonts (a group of jawless marine vertebrates), many marine reptiles and invertebrates, and some remaining large therapsids and amphibians.</string>

    <string name="jurassic_physics">Mean temperature: 16.5 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 26%</string>
    <string name="jurassic_description">The Jurassic is the second period of the Mesozoic Era, often called the Age of Reptiles. During the Middle Jurassic, the supercontinent Pangaea began to break apart. By the Late Jurassic, the Central Atlantic Ocean had formed as a narrow sea separating Africa from North America. Additionally, Eastern Gondwana had started to drift away from Western Gondwana. This tectonic activity helped shape the continents as we know them today and influenced global climates and ecosystems.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_additional_title">Dinosaurian Prominence</string>
    <string name="jurassic_additional">About 20 million years after the Permian-Triassic extinction, dinosaurs evolved from their archosaurian ancestors and began to compete with the dominant archosauromorphs and therapsids. Initially, they were not the leading terrestrial animals. However, after the Triassic-Jurassic extinction event—which eliminated many of their competitors—dinosaurs rose to dominance and filled most major ecological niches for the next 135 million years.\nTwo major questions remain:\n1. How did some terrestrial dinosaurs grow to such massive sizes? Many sauropods, such as Argentinosaurus (estimated at over 70 tons), Mamenchisaurus, and Diplodocus, were enormous.\n2. Were dinosaurs feathered and warm-blooded?\nThese two questions are closely related, but still not fully resolved.\nThe largest dinosaurs were herbivores, and large body size likely provided protection from predators. In crowded ecosystems, herbivores may have evolved toward unoccupied ecological niches—especially larger size—creating an evolutionary “arms race” toward gigantism, within the constraints of physics and environment.\nFossil evidence shows that sauropods grew at astonishing rates—up to 5,000 kg per year. Such rapid growth suggests a high metabolic rate, unlike that of modern cold-blooded animals. However, high metabolism can become a disadvantage for very large animals, as heating and cooling large volumes of tissue becomes energetically costly. Current research suggests that juvenile sauropods were likely warm-blooded, but their metabolic rate may have decreased as they matured.\nOur understanding of dinosaur physiology continues to evolve. The outdated view of dinosaurs as sluggish, cold-blooded reptiles has largely been replaced by the idea that many species had active metabolisms and some form of thermoregulation. Fossil evidence from North America suggests some dinosaurs lived seasonally in cold climates. The discovery of feathered dinosaurs—including large species like Velociraptor and possibly even Tyrannosaurus rex—supports the theory that feathers were common among theropods. The only dinosaurs to survive the Cretaceous-Paleogene extinction—modern birds—are both feathered and warm-blooded. This raises a compelling question: why wouldn’t many Jurassic dinosaurs share these traits?</string>
    <string name="jurassic_life_forms">During the Jurassic period, the dominant marine vertebrates were fish and a variety of marine reptiles, including ichthyosaurs (marine reptiles that resembled modern dolphins), plesiosaurs (long-necked, paddle-limbed swimmers), pliosaurs (a group of plesiosaurs with shorter necks and larger heads), and marine-adapted crocodilians. Numerous turtles inhabited freshwater environments such as lakes and rivers.\nThe Jurassic was a golden age for sauropods—gigantic, long-necked herbivores like Diplodocus, Brachiosaurus, and Apatosaurus. It also saw the appearance of the first avialans (early bird-like dinosaurs), including the famous Archaeopteryx, which had feathers and could likely glide or make short powered flights.\nThe arid, continental conditions that characterized the Triassic gradually gave way to a more humid and tropical climate during the Jurassic. This warmer, wetter environment allowed dense forests and lush vegetation to spread. Conifers, along with cycads, ginkgoes, and ferns, dominated the plant life.</string>

    <string name="cretaceous_physics">Mean temperature: 18 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 30%</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_description">The Cretaceous was the final period of the Mesozoic Era, ending about 66 million years ago with a massive mass extinction — famously caused by an asteroid impact that contributed to the extinction of non-avian dinosaurs. This period was characterized by a relatively warm global climate and high sea levels, which formed vast shallow inland seas.\nDuring the Cretaceous, the South Atlantic Ocean began to open as South America and Africa drifted apart. India separated from Madagascar and moved rapidly northward toward a future collision with Eurasia — a movement that would eventually form the Himalayas. North America was still connected to Europe at times, and Australia remained attached to Antarctica.\n\nThe Cretaceous also saw the diversification of flowering plants (angiosperms), which began to transform ecosystems and food chains. Many modern insect groups appeared, co-evolving with these plants. In the oceans, large marine reptiles like mosasaurs thrived, while the skies were dominated by pterosaurs and early birds.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_additional_title">End of the Age of Dinosaurs</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_additional">The Cretaceous Period ended with a massive extinction event, known as the Cretaceous–Paleogene (K–Pg) extinction. Numerous plant and animal species were wiped out, including all non-avian dinosaurs. With the exception of some cold-blooded species like turtles and crocodilians, no tetrapods weighing more than 25 kilograms are known to have survived. This event marked the end of both the Cretaceous Period and the entire Mesozoic Era, ushering in the Cenozoic Era that continues to this day.\nWhat could cause such a devastating extinction? Today, there is overwhelming scientific consensus that the main cause was a massive asteroid — approximately 10 to 15 kilometers in diameter — that struck near what is now Mexico’s Yucatán Peninsula. The impact triggered global catastrophe: debris and dust ejected into the atmosphere blocked sunlight for months to years, halting photosynthesis. As a result, plant life collapsed, followed by the extinction of herbivores and then carnivores higher up the food chain.\nThe asteroid struck a region rich in sulfur-containing carbonate rock, releasing sulfur aerosols and causing acid rain and ocean acidification. This sharp drop in pH levels devastated marine ecosystems, wiping out many shell-forming organisms like ammonites and corals, along with the animals that fed on them. Sea surface temperatures fell by as much as 7°C, and it took hundreds of thousands of years for Earth’s climate and ecosystems to recover.\nOne intriguing question is why some of the dinosaurs’ close relatives, like crocodilians, survived. It is believed that their cold-blooded metabolism and ability to survive long periods without food helped them endure the harsh post-impact conditions — further evidence that non-avian dinosaurs were likely warm-blooded, at least to some extent.\nThe elimination of dominant Cretaceous species opened ecological niches for new life forms. This led to a remarkable period of adaptive radiation in the Paleogene. The most striking example is the rise of mammals, which quickly diversified to occupy roles previously held by dinosaurs. In a profound sense, the eventual evolution of humans may have depended on the extinction of the dinosaurs.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_life_forms">Flowering plants (angiosperms) first appeared during the Cretaceous, though they did not become ecologically dominant until the latter part of the period. Their evolution was closely tied to the emergence of pollinating insects, especially bees. In fact, angiosperms and insects are classic examples of coevolution — each influencing the evolution of the other. The Cretaceous also saw the first appearances of many modern leafy trees, such as figs, plane trees, and magnolias.\nOn land, mammals were typically small, but they were a vital part of the ecosystem. The dominant terrestrial predators remained archosaurian reptiles — especially dinosaurs, which reached their peak in diversity during this time. Pterosaurs were widespread in the Early and Middle Cretaceous, though their diversity declined later in the period for reasons that remain unclear.\nInsects underwent a significant diversification during the Cretaceous, with the emergence of many modern groups including ants, termites, butterflies and moths, aphids, grasshoppers, and gall wasps.\nIn the oceans, rays, modern sharks, and bony fishes became increasingly common. Marine reptiles included ichthyosaurs, which thrived in the Early and Middle Cretaceous, and later plesiosaurs and mosasaurs, which rose to prominence before the end of the period.</string>

    <string name="paleogene_physics">Mean temperature: 18 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 26%</string>
    <string name="paleogene_description">The Paleogene is the first period of the Cenozoic Era and includes the Paleocene, Eocene, and Oligocene epochs. The end of the Paleocene (around 55 million years ago) was marked by the Paleocene–Eocene Thermal Maximum (PETM), one of the most significant global warming events of the Cenozoic. This event caused rapid increases in temperature, major shifts in ecosystems, and the extinction of many deep-sea species.\nThroughout the Paleogene, Earth’s climate gradually cooled and dried, though this trend was occasionally interrupted by short-lived warming events. One major factor contributing to the cooling was the formation of the Antarctic Circumpolar Current, which thermally isolated Antarctica and significantly cooled ocean waters.\nDuring this period, the Indian subcontinent began colliding with Asia, giving rise to the Himalayan Mountains and the Tibetan Plateau. Australia, previously connected to Antarctica, started drifting northward, eventually influencing the formation of unique ecosystems like those found today.</string>
    <string name="paleogene_additional_title">PETM</string>
    <string name="paleogene_additional">The Paleocene–Eocene Thermal Maximum (PETM) was a period when global average temperatures were 5–8 °C warmer than today. This major climate event began around 55.5 million years ago, at the boundary between the Paleocene and Eocene epochs.\nIt was triggered by two massive releases of carbon into the atmosphere, each lasting approximately 1,500 years. In total, the PETM lasted about 200,000 years. The amount of carbon released during this period was more than 30 times greater than all fossil fuels burned to date and comparable to the total known fossil fuel reserves.\nThe likely causes of this carbon surge include the melting of methane clathrates (frozen methane on the ocean floor) and volcanic activity heating organic-rich sediments, releasing large amounts of methane.\nThis warming led to increased storminess in some areas (similar to today’s Caribbean and East Asia), higher aridity in tropical regions, and greater humidity near the poles. While ecosystems were severely disrupted, most species—except deep-sea foraminifera—survived by adapting or migrating. This period also saw the rise of many modern mammal groups, including early primates, hoofed mammals (ungulates), and ancestors of whales (cetaceans). There were widespread shifts in plant and animal ranges across continents.\nNotably, many mammal species underwent dwarfing, likely due to higher temperatures and lower nutrient content in plants. Under elevated CO₂ levels, plants can grow faster but tend to have reduced nutritional value, which may explain why early horses shrank in size by 20–30%.\nThe PETM offers a valuable ancient parallel to today’s human-driven global warming, providing important insights into how Earth’s systems and species respond to rapid climate change.</string>
    <string name="paleogene_life_forms">Mammals underwent rapid diversification during the Paleogene period. Some evolved into large land-dwelling forms that would dominate terrestrial ecosystems, while others adapted to life in the oceans, eventually giving rise to modern whales and dolphins (cetaceans). Still others took to the trees and became early primates, the ancestors of monkeys, apes, and humans.\nBirds, already well established by the end of the Cretaceous, also experienced a major adaptive radiation. With the extinction of pterosaurs, they became the dominant flying vertebrates, spreading into a wide variety of ecological niches.\nAs the global climate cooled over the course of the Paleogene, tropical plant species became less widespread, retreating toward equatorial regions. In contrast, temperate forests and grasslands began to expand, shaping the habitats available for the evolving animal life.</string>

    <string name="neogene_physics">Mean temperature: 14 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 21.5%</string>
    <string name="neogene_description">The Neogene is a period that spans 20.45 million years. It is sub-divided into two epochs, the earlier Miocene and the later Pliocene. The Isthmus of Panama connected North and South America later in the Pliocene, cutting off the Atlantic Ocean from the warm ocean currents from the Pacific, and leaving only the Gulf Stream to transfer heat to the Arctic Ocean. The global climate cooled considerably over the course of the Neogene, culminating in a series of continental glaciations in the Quaternary period that follows.\n20 million years ago, Antarctica was covered by ice and the northern continents were cooling rapidly. The world has taken on a \"modern\" look, but notice that Florida and parts of Asia were under water.</string>
    <string name="neogene_additional_title">Cooler effect</string>
    <string name="neogene_additional">During the Neogene world became much drier and cooler, culminating disaster of the Pleistocene ice ages and the harsh conditions of our own day. During this interval, the relatively uniform and stable climatic regime which had cradled the world’s ecosystems for 200 million years, since the Late Triassic, came to a comparatively quick end. The drift of the continents had sealed off the waters of the far arctic, as the northern margins of Asia and North America crowded together. The closing of the Isthmus of Panama prevented warm currents from the Pacific to the Atlantic. In the south, Antarctica, now out of contact with any other landmass, was circled by a continuous circum-polar current. Perhaps for the first time since the Ordovician, both poles were thermally isolated from the warm equatorial waters and started accumulating heavy coverings of ice. The ice sheets, in turn reflected more sunlight and lowered sea levels, further reducing temperatures and warm-water circulation.\nThe world dried out, huge deserts developed in North Africa and Central Asia. The deep forests of the continental interiors were replaced by arid plains, steppe, prairie or tundra. Many herbivorous animal species died out or were forced to change together with their predators. By the end of the period, the world became similar to what we see now.</string>
    <string name="neogene_life_forms">During this period, mammals and birds continued to evolve into roughly modern forms, while other groups remained relatively unchanged. Early hominids, the ancestors of humans, appeared in Africa near the end of this period and later spread into Eurasia. Tropical plant species gave way to deciduous ones and grasslands replaced many forests. Grasses therefore greatly diversified, and herbivorous mammals evolved alongside it, creating the many grazing animals of today, such as horses and antelopes.</string>

    <string name="quaternary_physics">Mean temperature: 14 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 20.8%</string>
    <string name="quaternary_description">The Quaternary Period is the current and most recent of the three periods of the Cenozoic Era. It is divided into two epochs: the Pleistocene and the Holocene (which began 11,700 years ago). The Quaternary is typically defined by the cyclic growth and decay of continental ice sheets driven by Milankovitch cycles and the associated climate and environmental changes that occurred. The last expansion of the polar ice sheets took place about 12,000 years ago.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_additional_title">Ice Age</string>
    <string name="quaternary_additional">The Quaternary is a period of the repeating glaciations, which are defined by the previously mentioned Milankovitch cycles. The angle of Earth’s axial tilt with respect to the orbital plane varies between 22.1 and 24.5 degrees over a cycle of about 41,000 years. The current tilt is 23.44 degrees, roughly halfway between its extreme values. Increased tilt increases the amplitude of the seasonal cycle, providing more solar radiation in each hemisphere’s summer and less in winter – in other words, climate at higher latitudes becomes warmer and stops glaciation. The tilt last reached its maximum 10,700 years ago and now is in the decreasing phase of its cycle and will reach its minimum in 9,800 years. The current trend of decreasing tilt will promote milder seasons, as well as an overall cooling trend. A new Ice Age is approaching.\nIn order to understand the impact of the glaciations, we should compare three regions at roughly the same latitude – China, North America, and Europe. Chinese flora is extremely rich, with million-year-old relics like Ginkgo, Magnolia, and Thujopsis. North America, too, has such ancient plants as Taxodium and Sequoiadendron.  Europe, however, has essentially no ancient plant groups at all (except for a few in the Mediterranean). Why is it that the Ice Ages affected plants in China and North America so differently from those in Europe?  The answer lies in geography.  Glaciations affect European plant life more severely: during the last glaciation, most of Europe was buried under ice and it was very difficult for Europe’s plants to escape southwards, because they were blocked by the Alps and Mediterranean Sea, both of which extend generally from east to west. (The Mediterranean region was able to retain some ancient plants like Platanus and Olea). North America, especially it’s eastern coastal region, was usually free of snow, and its mountains run generally north-south, making it easier for plants to retreat southward, away from the encroaching glaciers. China, in contrast, was not covered by glaciers at all. It’s hard to imagine that before the Quaternary, Europe was home to gingkoes and beautiful Magnolias.\nQuaternary glaciations also obstructed humans from migrating into Europe, and repeatedly destroyed the populations that did settle there.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_life_forms">The Quaternary is the modern period, and it represents our current fauna and flora. However, periodic glaciations had a huge impact on the terrestrial biota, frequently destroying plant and animal species. After the last ice age, many large Pleistocene mammals such as saber-tooth cats, mammoths, and mastodons became extinct worldwide.</string>

    <string name="future_physics">Mean temperature: x °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: y%</string>
    <string name="future_description">It is very hard to predict the future; however, we as an intelligent life forms can try to contemplate it. \nEarth will vanish eventually, because the Sun has its lifetime and will swallow our planet (unless our future siblings will be able to transfer Earth somewhere else). It is thought, that Earth’s habitable-zone lifespan is as long as 7.79 billion years. Because we already spent 4.56 billion years, we got around 3.23 billion years left, or even less – 1.75 billion years due to some scientists. It will get progressively hotter and there is nothing we can do about it. Sun converts hydrogen into helium and when the significant portion of it will be converted – it will undergo an internal change and become a Red Giant. This is how it is.\nBut it is an ideal case.</string>
    <string name="future_additional_title">Anthropogenic Future</string>
    <string name="future_additional" formatted="false">Life already showed it’s persistence and will to exist, so it will flourish with humans or without them. The current trends and risen concern in society about the ecology bring some optimism, because about 20 years ago people still believed EXXON lying about the non existent climate change and no one was thinking about the pollution etc. However, changes will occur anyway despite our wishes.\nThere is a hidden bomb in our understanding of the economy. Usually if country shows an economic growth of below the 3% it is portrayed as a slow growing one. But what does it mean to grow 3% per year? It basically means, that every 20 years economy doubles and current economy trends show, that with economic growth, energy consumption grows too. Since the industrial revolution we increased our energy consumption rates dramatically and we still use carbon-rich fossil fuel everywhere. Renewable energy still occupies just a tiny part of our produced energy.\nThe main law in physics states, that energy always emits heat – by the current calculations in 400 years we will need as much energy as the Sun provides and we will basically boil our oceans, if energy will be used as inefficiently as it is used today. And in 2000 years we will need energy of all the Milky Way galaxy stars. Now imagine Milky Way and its minimum diameter of 100,000 light years and ask yourself – is it possible to retain such consumption tempo?\nIt is more likely, that humanity will discover way more efficient energy sources and will adapt to live on Earth, because now humanity is trying to adapt Earth for life with people.\nAt the moment something similar to the Permian-Triassic extinction is happening now, but in faster rates. We dump tons of the carbon dioxide, Earth started to heat and already melts its polar caps, which contain massive amounts of trapped methane inside. Oceanic acidity had already risen during the recent years and it caused the partial death of the worldwide coral reefs, and anoxia is already spreading. Forests, which should fixate all the carbon dioxide are being cut for economic purposes. The sea levels will continue to rise. Such places like Florida, East Asia already suffer from the mass floods.\nCurrent events are driving Earth’s life towards the next mass extinction, however at least now it gather much more publicity and required attention.</string>
    <string name="future_life_forms">Life will always flourish. Even in the radioactive bogs full of acid.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="archean_banded_iron_formation">Banded iron formations</string>
    <string name="archean_stromatolites">Stromatolites</string>
    <string name="archean_primaevifilum_amoenum">Primaevifilum amoenum</string>
    <string name="archean_acritarcha">Acritarcha</string>

    <string name="archean_banded_iron_formation_description">Banded iron formations (BIFs) are distinctive sedimentary rock units composed of alternating layers of iron-rich minerals and iron-poor silica-rich bands, typically red due to hematite. These formations provide critical evidence of early biological and geochemical processes.\nThe prevailing hypothesis suggests that BIFs formed in ancient oceans as a result of oxygen released by photosynthetic cyanobacteria. Their presence in the Early Archean suggests that life may have existed as early as 3.85 billion years ago.\nDuring this period, Earth\'s oceans contained vast amounts of dissolved iron. As photosynthetic organisms produced oxygen, the iron reacted with it, precipitating as iron oxides and accumulating in these layered deposits. BIFs are rare in younger geological periods because most of the dissolved iron in the oceans was eventually removed, marking the Great Oxidation Event around 2.4 billion years ago.</string>
    <string name="archean_stromatolites_description">Stromatolites are layered, accretionary structures formed in shallow water through the trapping, binding, and cementation of sedimentary grains by microbial mats, primarily composed of cyanobacteria.\Fossilized stromatolites provide some of the oldest direct evidence of life on Earth, with examples dating back over 3.45 billion years. They exhibit a variety of forms and structures, ranging from columnar to domal shapes. While stromatolites are typically associated with biological activity, some possess features consistent with abiotic precipitation, making their origin a subject of ongoing study.\nStromatolites reached their peak diversity around 1.25 billion years ago, after which they declined in abundance and morphological variety, likely due to the rise of grazing organisms. Today, modern stromatolites are rare and primarily found in extreme environments such as hypersaline lakes and marine lagoons, where high salinity deters most grazing animals.</string>
    <string name="archean_primaevifilum_amoenum_description">Primaevifilum amoenum is one of the oldest known bacteria, with fossilized remains discovered in Western Australia. It was a filamentous microorganism that primarily lived in individual clasts, though it may have been part of a loosely organized benthic microbial community embedded in mucilage.\nUnlike many early microbial fossils, its microfossils have not been detected in stromatolite-like laminated clasts, suggesting a different ecological niche. These findings contribute to our understanding of early microbial diversity and the environmental conditions of the Archean Earth.</string>
    <string name="archean_acritarcha_description">Acritarchs are small, organic-walled microfossils that are resistant to acid dissolution and remain taxonomically unclassified. They represent a diverse group of structures, including the resting cysts of various green algae and possibly other microorganisms. Some acritarchs may also be linked to the reproductive or protective stages of unknown ancient eukaryotic life forms.\nDue to their resilience and abundance in the fossil record, acritarchs serve as valuable biostratigraphic markers, helping scientists understand the evolution of early life and past environmental conditions.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="proterozoic_bangiomorpha_pubescens">Bangiomorpha pubescens</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_nemiana_simplex">Nemiana simplex</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_tribrachidium_heraldicum">Tribrachidium heraldicum</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_dickinsonia">Dickinsonia</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_cloudina">Cloudina</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_charnia">Charnia</string>

    <string name="proterozoic_bangiomorpha_pubescens_description">Bangiomorpha pubescens is the earliest known sexually reproducing organism, dating to approximately 1.2 billion years ago. It belongs to the red algae (Rhodophyta) and is considered one of the first complex multicellular eukaryotes. The emergence of sexual reproduction was a pivotal moment in evolutionary history, not only because of the benefits of genetic recombination but also because it enabled the development of complex multicellularity. This evolutionary breakthrough laid the foundation for the diversification of eukaryotic life, making Bangiomorpha a crucial organism in the history of life on Earth.</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_nemiana_simplex_description">Nemiana simplex is one of the simplest sessile organisms of the Ediacaran biota, resembling a cnidarian-like jellyfish or a basal, soft-bodied polyp. It consists of a jelly-like sac that likely housed internal structures, though its anatomy remains poorly understood. Some hypotheses suggest it may have possessed small tentacle-like structures.\nIt is possible that this organism was entirely immobile, adhering to the seafloor, and fed through passive suspension feeding or direct absorption of dissolved nutrients from the water, possibly relying on microbial or algal matter for sustenance.</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_tribrachidium_heraldicum_description">Tribrachidium heraldicum was a tri-radially symmetrical organism that lived during the Late Ediacaran Period of the Proterozoic Eon, approximately 555 million years ago. It was a soft-bodied, benthic organism that likely rested on or was temporarily attached to the seafloor.\nUnlike most modern animals, Tribrachidium does not fit into any known major animal group, and its exact classification remains uncertain. It likely fed using a unique form of suspension feeding, generating microcurrents to capture organic particles suspended in the water.</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_dickinsonia_description">Dickinsonia is one of the earliest known organisms exhibiting bilateral symmetry, a body plan that later became dominant among modern animals. Its growth was likely indeterminate, as fossil specimens range from a few millimeters to approximately 1.4 meters in length. Evidence suggests that Dickinsonia grew continuously until it was buried by ocean sediments or otherwise perished.\nUnlike true bilaterians, Dickinsonia lacked a rigid body structure and may have absorbed nutrients directly from microbial mats on the seafloor. It spent most, if not all, of its life with its body in close contact with the sediment, possibly anchoring itself partially to the substrate.</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_cloudina_description">Cloudinids are among the earliest known animals with mineralized skeletons, dating to the late Ediacaran Period, approximately 550–541 million years ago. Their fossils consist of millimeter-scale calcareous cones nested within one another, forming tube-like structures. The emergence of mineralized skeletons may indicate the evolution of more complex ecological interactions by the end of the Proterozoic Eon.\nUntil this time, most organisms were benthic filter feeders, but fossil evidence from the late Proterozoic suggests the first appearance of predators. The presence of boreholes in Cloudina fossils provides some of the earliest direct evidence of predation, marking a significant shift in the evolution of marine ecosystems.</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_charnia_description">Charnia is a highly significant fossil, as it was the first Precambrian organism to be formally described from undoubted Precambrian rocks. It is also thought to be among the earliest known animals capable of sexual reproduction. Although its frond-like appearance resembles that of a fern, Charnia was neither a plant nor an algae, as it lived in deep-water environments well below the photic zone, where photosynthesis is impossible.\nInstead, it is believed to have absorbed nutrients directly from the surrounding water, possibly through osmotrophy, a feeding strategy common among some modern marine organisms.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="cambrian_treptichnus_pedum">Treptichnus pedum</string>
    <string name="cambrian_conodonta">Conodonta</string>
    <string name="cambrian_archaeocyatha">Archaeocyatha</string>
    <string name="cambrian_trilobita">Trilobita</string>
    <string name="cambrian_wiwaxia">Wiwaxia</string>
    <string name="cambrian_myllokunmingia">Myllokunmingia</string>
    <string name="cambrian_pikaia">Pikaia</string>
    <string name="cambrian_anomalocaris">Anomalocaris</string>
    <string name="cambrian_opabinia">Opabinia</string>
    <string name="cambrian_marrella">Marrella</string>
    <string name="cambrian_foraminifera">Foraminifera</string>
    <string name="cambrian_hallucigenia">Hallucigenia</string>

    <string name="cambrian_treptichnus_pedum_description">Treptichnus pedum is a crucial trace fossil because it marks the first known burrowing behavior, helping to define the boundary between the Ediacaran and Cambrian periods.\nSince only its burrows have been found, scientists infer that the organism responsible for Treptichnus pedum lacked hard anatomical features such as shells or bones. It is likely related to modern priapulid worms, which also exhibit similar burrowing behaviors.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_conodonta_description">Conodonta were ancient, eel-like, jawless vertebrates whose fossilized elements serve as crucial index fossils for stratigraphic correlation. Although these tooth-like elements appear formidable, the animals themselves were likely not active predators, possibly due to the lateral placement of their eyes. Estimates suggest that conodonts ranged in body length from 1 to 40 cm, highlighting the diversity among these early chordates.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_archaeocyatha_description">Archaeocyatha were the first large skeletal animals and the earliest known reef builders of the Cambrian, thriving in warm tropical and subtropical waters. Some archaeocyaths lived as solitary organisms, while others formed colonies, contributing to the structure of early marine ecosystems.\nThey resembled hollow horn corals, with porous, cup-shaped skeletons composed of calcite, which allowed water to circulate through their bodies for filter feeding.\nAround 516 million years ago, archaeocyaths experienced a sharp decline, coinciding with the rapid diversification of demosponges, which may have competed for ecological niches.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_trilobita_description">Trilobites represent one of the earliest known groups of arthropods and are iconic examples of Cambrian marine life. They flourished throughout the Paleozoic Era but experienced a significant decline during the Devonian before going extinct at the end of the Permian.\nTrilobites were among the most successful early animals, thriving in the oceans for over 270 million years. They exhibited a wide range of lifestyles—some crawled along the seafloor as predators, scavengers, or filter feeders, while others swam through the water column, feeding on plankton.\nIf you ever visit Morocco, you will likely encounter many merchants selling trilobite fossils, as the Anti-Atlas Mountains are composed of Paleozoic rocks rich in these ancient arthropods.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_wiwaxia_description">Wiwaxia is a genus of soft-bodied, bottom-dwelling animals covered in rows of carbonaceous scales and long, sharp spines. These dorsal spines may have served as a defense mechanism against predators. Wiwaxia likely moved by contracting a slug-like foot on its underside, similar to modern mollusks.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_myllokunmingia_description">Myllokunmingia is a genus of basal chordates, measuring approximately 28 mm in length and 6 mm in height. It is one of the oldest known possible craniates, possessing a skull and skeletal structures made of cartilage. Its anatomy suggests it was an early step in vertebrate evolution, sharing characteristics with modern jawless fish.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_pikaia_description">Pikaia is one of the oldest known relatives of vertebrates, exhibiting a worm-like body and likely swimming in an eel-like manner. Fossils reveal key chordate features, including an elongated notochord, a dorsal nerve cord, and segmented myotomes—critical characteristics in the early evolution of vertebrates.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_anomalocaris_description">Anomalocaris was a marine predator closely related to ancestral arthropods. It was one of the largest animals of the Cambrian oceans, reaching up to a meter in length. It possessed highly sophisticated stalked eyes, each with at least 16,000 lenses, providing vision as acute as that of modern insects. Its circular mouth was lined with a ring of hardened plates, adapted for grasping and consuming prey.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_opabinia_description">Opabinia was a soft-bodied marine animal of modest size, measuring between 4 and 7 cm in length. Its segmented body featured lateral lobes for swimming and a fan-shaped tail for propulsion. The head had highly unusual characteristics, including five eyes, a downward-facing mouth positioned beneath the head, and a flexible proboscis likely used to grasp and transfer food to the mouth.\nOpabinia likely lived on the seafloor, using its proboscis to search for and capture small, soft-bodied prey.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_marrella_description">Marrella was a small arthropod from the Middle Cambrian, measuring up to 2 cm in length. It scavenged organic debris along the seafloor. Marrella is considered a stem-group arthropod, meaning it shares a common ancestor with most or all later major arthropod groups but does not belong to any modern lineage.\nDespite its superficial resemblance to trilobites, Marrella is not more closely related to them than to other arthropods.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_foraminifera_description">Foraminifera are a group of amoeboid protists characterized by a streaming granular ectoplasm, which they use for capturing food and interacting with their environment. They are commonly encased in an external shell, or test, composed of various materials and exhibiting diverse forms. Most foraminifera are marine, with only a few species known from freshwater habitats.\nTheir shells are typically made of calcium carbonate and are usually less than 1 mm in size, though some species can grow up to 20 cm. Foraminifera are widely used as index fossils, particularly for dating rock layers from the Permian, Jurassic, Cretaceous, and Cenozoic periods.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_hallucigenia_description">Hallucigenia is thought to be an early relative of modern velvet worms (onychophorans), though some researchers suggest a closer relationship to arthropods. Its quirky name reflects its unusual appearance and the eccentric history of its study. This small, tubular organism measured between 0.5 and 3.5 cm in length and had seven or eight pairs of slender legs, each ending in a pair of claws. Additionally, it possessed spiny dorsal projections, likely serving as a defense against predators.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="ordovician_orthoceras">Orthoceras</string>
    <string name="ordovician_pentecopterus">Pentecopterus decorahensis</string>
    <string name="ordovician_sacabambaspis">Sacabambaspis</string>
    <string name="ordovician_astraspis">Astraspis</string>
    <string name="ordovician_rugosa">Rugosa</string>
    <string name="ordovician_tabulata">Tabulata</string>

    <string name="ordovician_orthoceras_description">Orthoceras is a genus of extinct nautiloid cephalopods characterized by their long, straight, conical shells. These ancient marine animals lived during the Ordovician period and were among the earliest cephalopods. Based on their anatomy and the behavior of their modern relatives—squid, octopuses, cuttlefish, and the nautilus—it is likely that Orthoceras was a predator in the Paleozoic seas, hunting smaller marine creatures such as trilobites. Their streamlined shells allowed them to move through the water using jet propulsion, similar to modern cephalopods.</string>
    <string name="ordovician_pentecopterus_description">Pentecopterus decorahensis is the oldest known eurypterid, or "sea scorpion," dating back to the early Ordovician period. It could reach lengths of up to 1.83 meters, making it not only the earliest but also one of the largest arthropods ever discovered.\nSea scorpions were formidable marine predators that dominated coastal environments for millions of years, until their extinction during the Permian mass extinction event. They are closely related to modern horseshoe crabs—an ancient group of arthropods that still exists today.</string>
    <string name="ordovician_sacabambaspis_description">Sacabambaspis is a jawless fish and one of the earliest known vertebrates to possess skeletal tissues similar to those of modern vertebrates. It lived during the Ordovician period and had a distinctive armored head shield. Sacabambaspis also featured a primitive lateral line system—an early sensory structure still found in modern fish—that allowed it to detect vibrations and movement in the water.</string>
    <string name="ordovician_astraspis_description">Astraspis is one of the oldest known armored jawless fish, dating back to the Ordovician period. Its body was protected by large bony plates on the head and smaller, scale-like plates covering the rest of the body. It also had a mobile, flexible tail that aided in swimming, covered with small protective plate-like scales. Astraspis is significant in early vertebrate evolution as it shows the development of dermal armor, a key adaptation for defense in prehistoric seas.</string>
    <string name="ordovician_rugosa_description">Rugosa is an extinct order of corals that lived from the Middle Ordovician to the Late Permian. They existed in both solitary and colonial forms. Solitary individuals are commonly called horn corals due to their distinctive horn-shaped skeletons. Their hard skeletons were composed of calcite, which contributed to fossil preservation. Rugose corals played an important role in reef ecosystems before going extinct during the Permian mass extinction, also known as the Great Dying.</string>
    <string name="ordovician_tabulata_description">Tabulata is an extinct order of colonial corals that lived from the Early Ordovician to the end of the Permian period, coexisting with Rugosa. Their tightly packed, tube-like coral structures gave them a honeycomb-like appearance. Like Rugosa, their skeletons were composed of calcite, which helped preserve them as fossils. Tabulate corals were major reef builders in Paleozoic seas and played an important role in forming ancient marine ecosystems. They went extinct during the Permian mass extinction, the most severe extinction event in Earth\'s history.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="silurian_eurypterus">Eurypterus</string>
    <string name="silurian_pneumodesmus">Pneumodesmus</string>
    <string name="silurian_cooksonia">Cooksonia</string>
    <string name="silurian_baragwanathia">Baragwanathia</string>
    <string name="silurian_acanthodii">Acanthodii</string>
    <string name="silurian_entelognathus">Entelognathus</string>

    <string name="silurian_eurypterus_description">Eurypterus is an extinct genus of sea scorpions (eurypterids), and its fossils are among the most commonly found within this group. These ancient arthropods were both predators and scavengers, capable of growing up to 1.3 meters in length. While primarily aquatic, they possessed the ability to breathe air and walk on land for brief periods, possibly to move between water bodies or escape unfavorable conditions.</string>
    <string name="silurian_pneumodesmus_description">Pneumodesmus is the earliest known myriapod and the oldest documented creature to have lived on land. It is also the first arthropod discovered with a tracheal system, making it the earliest known oxygen-breathing animal on land. Its fossil, found in Scotland, dates back to approximately 428 million years ago, providing significant insights into the early colonization of terrestrial environments.</string>
    <string name="silurian_cooksonia_description">Cooksonia is an extinct group of primitive land plants, representing some of the earliest vascular plants. They include the oldest known plant to possess a stem with vascular tissue, which allowed efficient water and nutrient transport. Cooksonia lacked leaves, flowers, and roots, and they were typically small, standing only a few centimeters tall. Each branch terminated in a sporangium, a spore-bearing capsule, which played a crucial role in their reproduction.</string>
    <string name="silurian_baragwanathia_description">Baragwanathia is a genus of extinct Lycopodiophyta plants, considered one of the earliest known vascular plants. They had unbranched, strap-shaped microphylls (small, simple leaves), and their stems contained an actinostele, a primitive type of vascular bundle arranged in a star-like pattern. These features indicate that Baragwanathia was an early representative of clubmoss-like plants, which would later diversify significantly.</string>
    <string name="silurian_acanthodii_description">Acanthodians, sometimes called spiny sharks, are an extinct group of fish that shared characteristics with both bony (Osteichthyes) and cartilaginous fish (Chondrichthyes). Despite their common name, they are not true sharks but represent several independent phylogenetic branches of early jawed fish. Acanthodians are considered ancestors to modern cartilaginous fish, such as sharks and chimaeras, and are significant for being among the first vertebrates to develop jaws, a major evolutionary advancement.</string>
    <string name="silurian_entelognathus_description">Entelognathus is an ancient placoderm fish and represents one of the earliest known jawed vertebrates. It is the first fish to possess dermal marginal jaw bones, including the premaxilla, maxilla, and dentary, which are typically found in modern bony fish. This discovery provides important evidence of the evolutionary transition from armored jawless fish to jawed vertebrates.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="devonian_prototaxites">Prototaxites</string>
    <string name="devonian_wattieza">Wattieza</string>
    <string name="devonian_archaeopteris">Archaeopteris</string>
    <string name="devonian_tiktaalik">Tiktaalik</string>
    <string name="devonian_ichthyostega">Ichthyostega</string>
    <string name="devonian_bothriolepis">Bothriolepis</string>
    <string name="devonian_cladoselache">Cladoselache</string>
    <string name="devonian_dunkleosteus">Dunkleosteus</string>
    <string name="devonian_acanthostega">Acanthostega</string>
    <string name="devonian_materpiscis">Materpiscis</string>

    <string name="devonian_prototaxites_description">Prototaxites is a genus of ancient organisms that formed large trunk-like structures, up to 1 meter wide and reaching heights of up to 8 meters. Although it first appeared in the Late Silurian period, it reached its greatest diversity during the Devonian. Initially believed to be a giant fungus, recent discoveries indicate the presence of algal symbionts, suggesting that Prototaxites was more likely a lichen rather than a fungus in the strict sense.\nPrototaxites became extinct as shrubs and vascular trees rose to dominance, gradually replacing these massive structures in terrestrial ecosystems.</string>
    <string name="devonian_wattieza_description">Wattieza is a genus of prehistoric trees, considered to be the oldest known trees on Earth. They existed during the Middle Devonian period and were closely related to modern ferns and horsetails. Wattieza trees could grow up to 8 meters or more in height and reproduced by releasing spores, much like their modern relatives.</string>
    <string name="devonian_archaeopteris_description">Archaeopteris is an extinct genus of tree-like plants characterized by fern-like leaves. These plants could grow up to 10 meters in height, with trunks exceeding 1.5 meters in diameter. Archaeopteris thrived in wet soils, typically growing near river systems and within floodplain woodlands. It is considered a distant ancestor of modern gymnosperm plants, such as conifers, and played a significant role in forming some of the earliest forest ecosystems on Earth.</string>
    <string name="devonian_tiktaalik_description">Although it resembles an amphibian, Tiktaalik is a lobe-finned fish from the Late Devonian period, possessing many features similar to those of tetrapods. Tiktaalik is considered a key representative of the evolutionary transition from fish to amphibians. It exemplifies one of several ancient sarcopterygian fish lineages that developed adaptations for surviving in oxygen-poor, shallow-water habitats—environmental conditions that are believed to have driven the evolution of tetrapods.\nIt is thought that Tiktaalik was specialized for living in swampy, pond-like environments and may have occasionally used its uniquely adapted fins to move short distances over land.</string>
    <string name="devonian_ichthyostega_description">Ichthyostega is one of the earliest known tetrapods in the fossil record, living at the end of the Devonian period. It possessed lungs and limbs, adaptations that allowed it to navigate through shallow swamp waters. Although it resembles an amphibian, Ichthyostega is considered a stem group tetrapod and one of the closest known ancestors of modern amphibians. It had a fish-like tail and gills, but also possessed an amphibian-like skull and robust limbs, reflecting its transitional status between aquatic and terrestrial life.</string>
    <string name="devonian_bothriolepis_description">Bothriolepis is a widespread, abundant, and diverse genus of placoderms that thrived during the Middle to Late Devonian period. The largest species could reach about 1 meter in length. Bothriolepis was a bottom-dwelling, armored fish that primarily fed on detritus, algae, and small microorganisms, using its specialized mouthparts to sift through sediment.</string>
    <string name="devonian_cladoselache_description">Cladoselache is one of the earliest known shark groups, dating back to the Late Devonian period. These ancient sharks could grow up to 1.8 meters in length. They were fast and agile predators, characterized by having 5 to 7 gill slits and a short, rounded mouth. Unlike modern sharks, Cladoselache lacked scales and had a streamlined body, allowing for swift movement in the water.</string>
    <string name="devonian_dunkleosteus_description">Dunkleosteus is an extinct genus of placoderm fish that existed during the Late Devonian period. The largest species could grow up to 6 meters in length and weigh up to 1 tonne. As a hypercarnivorous apex predator, Dunkleosteus was known for its incredibly strong bite, capable of crushing hard-shelled prey such as ammonites and other armored fish.\nDue to its heavily armored exterior, Dunkleosteus was likely a relatively slow but powerful swimmer. Its massive, bony head shield provided both protection and a powerful leverage system for its jaw, compensating for its lack of true teeth with sharp bony plates.</string>
    <string name="devonian_acanthostega_description">Acanthostega is an extinct genus of stem-tetrapods and is among the earliest vertebrate animals to have recognizable limbs. It represents an anatomically intermediate form between lobe-finned fishes and fully terrestrial tetrapods. Acanthostega could grow up to 60 cm in length and had eight digits on each hand, linked by webbing.\nDespite having limbs, Acanthostega was primarily an aquatic animal, likely inhabiting shallow, weed-choked swamps. Its limbs were not well adapted for walking on land, indicating that it was still more suited for life in water.</string>
    <string name="devonian_materpiscis_description">Materpiscis is a genus of placoderm fish that lived near what is now Western Australia. Known from only one specimen, it is unique for containing an unborn embryo preserved inside the mother, along with a mineralized placental feeding structure. This remarkable find makes Materpiscis the oldest known vertebrate to exhibit viviparity, or giving birth to live young.\nMaterpiscis is represented by a single species, Materpiscis attenboroughi, named in honor of Sir David Attenborough, who first highlighted the significance of the Gogo fish sites in his 1979 documentary series "Life on Earth."</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="carboniferous_lepidodendron">Lepidodendron</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_sigillaria">Sigillaria</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_calamites">Calamites</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_akmonistion">Akmonistion</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_helicoprion">Helicoprion</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_pederpes">Pederpes</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_pterogyrinus">Proterogyrinus</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_hylonomus">Hylonomus</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_archaeothyris">Archaeothyris</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_pulmonoscorpius">Pulmonoscorpius</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_arthropleura">Arthropleura</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_meganeura">Meganeura</string>

    <string name="carboniferous_lepidodendron_description">Lepidodendron was an extinct, tree-like lycopsid and a dominant component of the Carboniferous coal forest flora. These plants could grow over 30 meters tall, with trunks exceeding 1 meter in diameter. They are believed to have grown rapidly and lived for only 10–15 years. Most species were likely monocarpic, meaning they reproduced just once near the end of their life cycle. By the Mesozoic era, Lepidodendron and its relatives had largely disappeared, likely outcompeted by emerging woody gymnosperms such as conifers, which were better adapted to changing climates and soil conditions.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_sigillaria_description">Sigillaria was an extinct, tree-like lycopsid closely related to Lepidodendron. It could grow up to 30 meters tall and had a relatively short life cycle, characterized by rapid growth and reaching maturity within just a few years. Sigillaria was a prominent member of the Carboniferous coal forests, with its distinctive vertical leaf scars forming a pattern that gives the plant its name.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_calamites_description">Calamites was an extinct, tree-like horsetail and a major component of the Carboniferous coal swamps. It could grow up to 30 meters tall and had a hollow, jointed stem structure similar to modern horsetails, but on a much larger scale. Calamites often grew in dense stands along rivers and floodplains, contributing significantly to the formation of coal deposits.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_akmonistion_description">Akmonistion was a shark-like chimaera that lived during the Early Carboniferous. Males had a distinctive anvil-shaped crest instead of a dorsal fin, with barbs on top and a triangular patch of spines located in front of the crest on the head. Females likely resembled the males but may have lacked both the crest and the patch of spines. Akmonistion is sometimes informally called the “ironing board shark” due to the unusual shape of its crest.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_helicoprion_description">Helicoprion was a long-lived genus of shark-like fish known for its unusual spiral arrangement of teeth, often called a "tooth whorl." These teeth were positioned in the lower jaw and may have been used for slicing soft-bodied prey. Helicoprion could reach lengths of 3–4 meters, with some large specimens estimated to grow up to 7.5 meters. Although it resembled a shark, it was more closely related to chimaeras.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_pederpes_description">Pederpes is the earliest known tetrapod to show clear adaptations for walking on land. Although not classified as an amphibian, it represents a very basal (primitive) member of the tetrapod lineage. Pederpes measured about 1 meter in length and displayed features well suited for terrestrial life, such as forward-facing feet for more effective movement on land. It is currently considered the earliest known fully terrestrial vertebrate.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_pterogyrinus_description">Proterogyrinus was a reptile-like amphibian and one of the early tetrapods that likely shares ancestry with the first reptiles. It could venture farther from water than most contemporary amphibians and was a top predator in both terrestrial and aquatic environments. Proterogyrinus had strong limbs and a flexible body, allowing it to move efficiently on land while still being an effective swimmer.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_hylonomus_description">Hylonomus is the earliest known unquestionable reptile. It measured about 20 centimeters in length and resembled modern lizards in appearance. With its small, sharp teeth, it likely fed on small invertebrates such as millipedes and early insects. Fossils of Hylonomus have been found inside fossilized tree stumps, suggesting it may have used them for shelter or hunting.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_archaeothyris_description">Archaeothyris is the oldest known synapsid—the group of vertebrates that includes modern mammals and their extinct relatives. It resembled a modern-day lizard in appearance, but at around 50 centimeters long, it was one of the largest carnivores in the Carboniferous forests. Archaeothyris had sharp teeth and strong jaws, allowing it to prey on smaller vertebrates and insects.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_pulmonoscorpius_description">Pulmonoscorpius was a giant species of extinct scorpion that could grow up to 70 centimeters long. While its exact diet is not known, it likely preyed on smaller arthropods, and its powerful sting may have been capable of killing small early tetrapods. Pulmonoscorpius lived in the humid coal forests of the Carboniferous and is one of the largest scorpions known from the fossil record.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_arthropleura_description">Arthropleura was one of the largest known land invertebrates of all time and had few, if any, natural predators. It could grow up to 2.3 meters in length and about 50 centimeters in width. Like other Carboniferous arthropods, Arthropleura was able to grow so large due to the higher partial pressure of oxygen in Earth\'s atmosphere and the absence of large terrestrial vertebrate predators. This helps explain why similarly sized arthropods did not exist during later periods like the Cretaceous, despite similar oxygen levels.\nContrary to earlier and popular beliefs, Arthropleura was not a predator but an herbivorous arthropod, likely feeding on decaying plant material on the forest floor.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_meganeura_description">Meganeura was an extinct genus of giant dragonfly-like insects, with a wingspan reaching up to 65 centimeters. Like Arthropleura, they were able to grow so large due to the higher atmospheric oxygen levels and the absence of large aerial predators during the Carboniferous period. Meganeura is one of the largest known flying insects in Earth’s history.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="permian_glossopteris">Glossopteris</string>
    <string name="permian_dimetrodon">Dimetrodon</string>
    <string name="permian_titanophoneus">Titanophoneus</string>
    <string name="permian_estemmenosuchus">Estemmenosuchus</string>
    <string name="permian_gorgonops">Gorgonops</string>
    <string name="permian_cynodontia">Cynodontia</string>

    <string name="permian_glossopteris_description">Glossopteris was the largest and best-known genus of seed ferns that flourished in the Southern Hemisphere during the Permian period. These were woody, seed-bearing shrubs or trees, with some species reaching up to 30 meters in height. They thrived in waterlogged soils and eventually outcompeted older plant groups such as the lycopsids Sigillaria and Lepidodendron.</string>
    <string name="permian_dimetrodon_description">Dimetrodon was an extinct synapsid—a group more closely related to mammals than to reptiles. It could reach up to 4.6 meters in length and may have weighed as much as 250 kilograms. Dimetrodon was likely one of the apex predators of its time, feeding on fish and early tetrapods. Its distinctive sail, formed by elongated spines on its back, may have helped stabilize its spine or acted as a thermoregulatory device, allowing it to absorb or release heat depending on environmental conditions.</string>
    <string name="permian_titanophoneus_description">Titanophoneus—meaning "titanic murderer"—was a carnivorous dinocephalian therapsid that lived during the Middle Permian. It belonged to a group of early, mammal-like reptiles known for their bulky skulls and powerful jaws. The adult skull of Titanophoneus could reach up to 80 centimeters in length, with a long, heavy snout. Its total body length was about 2.9 meters, and it likely hunted other vertebrates in its ecosystem.</string>
    <string name="permian_estemmenosuchus_description">Estemmenosuchus, meaning "crowned crocodile" in Greek, was a large omnivorous therapsid that lived during the Middle Permian. It could grow up to 3 meters in length and is notable for the unusual horn-like structures on its skull, which may have been used for display or species recognition. Despite its fearsome appearance, it likely fed on both plants and small animals.</string>
    <string name="permian_gorgonops_description">Gorgonops were the dominant predators of the Late Permian. These saber-toothed therapsids could grow up to 3 meters in length and had powerful jaws equipped with two enlarged canine teeth, which could reach up to 12 centimeters. As agile hunters with sharp senses, they likely preyed on large herbivores, including early therapsids and reptiles.</string>
    <string name="permian_cynodontia_description">Cynodonts, meaning "dog teeth," were a group of therapsids that first appeared in the Late Permian. This lineage includes modern mammals—including humans—as well as their extinct ancestors and close relatives. Non-mammalian cynodonts were widespread across Southern Gondwana and already exhibited many skeletal features typical of mammals, such as differentiated teeth and a secondary palate. They likely laid eggs, similar to today’s monotremes like the platypus, and showed signs of warm-blooded metabolism. The presence of fur in many species suggests they had some capacity to regulate their body temperature.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="triassic_bennettitales">Bennettitales</string>
    <string name="triassic_morganucodon">Morganucodon</string>
    <string name="triassic_lystrosaurus">Lystrosaurus</string>
    <string name="triassic_pterosauria">Pterosauria</string>
    <string name="triassic_plesiosauria">Plesiosauria</string>
    <string name="triassic_ichthyosauria">Ichthyosauria</string>
    <string name="triassic_mystriosuchus">Mystriosuchus</string>
    <string name="triassic_plateosaurus">Plateosaurus</string>
    <string name="triassic_desmatosuchus">Desmatosuchus</string>
    <string name="triassic_longisquama">Longisquama</string>
    <string name="triassic_sharovipteryx">Sharovipteryx</string>
    <string name="triassic_tanystropheus">Tanystropheus</string>

    <string name="triassic_bennettitales_description">Bennettitales were extinct seed plants that resembled flowering plants due to their flower-like reproductive structures. Despite this similarity, they are more closely related to cycads, ginkgos, and conifers than to true flowering plants (angiosperms). The evolutionary relationships of Bennettitales remain debated, and while they are generally not considered direct ancestors of angiosperms, some studies suggest that certain members might share a common ancestry with them.</string>
    <string name="triassic_morganucodon_description">Morganucodon was an early mammaliaform cynodont that lived during the Late Triassic. It was a small, likely nocturnal animal, with a body length of up to 10 cm. Morganucodon is often cited as an example of the nocturnal bottleneck effect in early mammalian evolution.</string>
    <string name="triassic_lystrosaurus_description">Lystrosaurus was a herbivorous genus of therapsids that lived during the Late Permian and Early Triassic. It was roughly the size of a modern pig. At least one species of Lystrosaurus survived the Permian-Triassic mass extinction and, in the absence of many predators and herbivorous competitors, it became the most common terrestrial vertebrate of the Early Triassic. At one point, nearly 90% of all land vertebrates belonged to this single genus!</string>
    <string name="triassic_pterosauria_description">Pterosaurs were flying reptiles that lived from the Late Triassic to the end of the Cretaceous period. They were the first vertebrates to evolve powered flight. Although often mistaken for flying dinosaurs, pterosaurs did not belong to the Dinosauria clade; instead, they were close relatives within the larger group Archosauria, which also includes dinosaurs and crocodiles.</string>
    <string name="triassic_plesiosauria_description">Plesiosauria was a group of marine reptiles that lived throughout much of the Mesozoic Era, from the Late Triassic to the end of the Cretaceous. They had broad, flat bodies, short tails, and typically long necks with small heads, although some species had shorter necks and larger heads. Plesiosaurs breathed atmospheric air and gave birth to live young. Some evidence also suggests they may have been warm-blooded.</string>
    <string name="triassic_ichthyosauria_description">Ichthyosaurs were large marine reptiles that thrived during much of the Mesozoic Era, especially from the Early Triassic to the Late Cretaceous. Shaped like modern dolphins, they were fast swimmers and among the top marine predators of their time. Ichthyosaurs reached their peak during the Triassic and Early Jurassic, but their diversity declined afterward. Contrary to earlier beliefs, they were not outcompeted by plesiosaurs, as the two groups coexisted for millions of years. Instead, their extinction likely resulted from a combination of environmental changes and ecological shifts in marine ecosystems.</string>
    <string name="triassic_mystriosuchus_description">Mystriosuchus was a crocodile-like reptile that lived during the Late Triassic period. It could grow up to 4 meters long. Its skull and jaw structure suggest a primarily fish-based diet, with long, narrow jaws resembling those of modern gharials. Mystriosuchus belonged to the phytosaurs, an extinct group of semi-aquatic archosaurs that were similar in appearance to crocodiles but not closely related to them.</string>
    <string name="triassic_plateosaurus_description">Plateosaurus was a basal sauropodomorph dinosaur, part of the group that would later include some of the largest land animals on Earth, such as Diplodocus and Argentinosaurus. Fully grown individuals measured between 5 and 10 meters in length and weighed between 600 and 4,000 kilograms. Fossil evidence suggests they commonly lived for at least 12 to 20 years.</string>
    <string name="triassic_desmatosuchus_description">Desmatosuchus was an extinct genus of armored archosaurs that lived during the Late Triassic period. It could grow up to 4.5 meters in length and had a distinctive row of long shoulder spikes. Fossil evidence suggests it was likely herbivorous, although some researchers have proposed that it may have also fed on insects or small animals, making it possibly omnivorous.</string>
    <string name="triassic_longisquama_description">Longisquama was a genus of extinct reptile that lived during the Triassic period. It is best known for the long, scale-like appendages on its back. While once controversially proposed as a possible relative of birds, current evidence suggests that Longisquama is not closely related to the origin of birds. The structures on its back are now thought to be elongated scales rather than true feathers.</string>
    <string name="triassic_sharovipteryx_description">Sharovipteryx was one of the earliest known gliding reptiles, dating to the Middle to Late Triassic. It is known from a single fossil discovered in Central Asia. Unlike modern gliders, Sharovipteryx had a unique gliding membrane attached primarily to its hind limbs, giving it a distinctive appearance and flight style.</string>
    <string name="triassic_tanystropheus_description">Tanystropheus was a reptile that grew up to 6 meters long, with an extraordinarily elongated neck measuring about 3 meters—half its total body length. Although it resembles a dinosaur at first glance, it actually belonged to a different reptile group called Protosauria and is not closely related to long-necked dinosaurs like sauropods. Fossil evidence suggests Tanystropheus was likely aquatic or semi-aquatic and probably fed on fish and other small marine animals.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="jurassic_archaeopteryx">Archaeopteryx</string>
    <string name="jurassic_allosaurus">Allosaurus</string>
    <string name="jurassic_mamenchisaurus">Mamenchisaurus</string>
    <string name="jurassic_stegosaurus">Stegosaurus</string>
    <string name="jurassic_epidexipteryx">Epidexipteryx</string>
    <string name="jurassic_dilophosaurus">Dilophosaurus</string>
    <string name="jurassic_dimorphodon">Dimorphodon</string>
    <string name="jurassic_epidendrosaurus">Epidendrosaurus</string>
    <string name="jurassic_liopleurodon">Liopleurodon</string>
    <string name="jurassic_kentrosaurus">Kentrosaurus</string>

    <string name="jurassic_archaeopteryx_description">Archaeopteryx is a genus of bird-like dinosaurs that represents a transitional form between non-avian feathered dinosaurs and modern birds. The largest individuals may have resembled modern ravens in size and shape, but they also had jaws with sharp teeth, three clawed fingers on each wing, and a long, bony tail—traits inherited from their dinosaur ancestors.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_allosaurus_description">Allosaurus was a large bipedal predator that could grow up to 8.5 meters in length and was likely near the top of the Jurassic food chain. Its potential prey included ornithopods, stegosaurids, and juvenile or weakened sauropods. Some paleontologists suggest that Allosaurus may have exhibited cooperative behavior and hunted in groups, while others believe individuals were solitary and that multiple fossils found together may represent scavenging at a shared carcass. It may have ambushed large prey, using its powerful jaws in a hatchet-like motion to deliver slashing bites.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_mamenchisaurus_description">Mamenchisaurus was a genus of sauropod dinosaurs known for its extraordinarily long neck, which could make up about half of its total body length. The largest species may have reached up to 35 meters in length and possibly weighed between 50 and 75 tons. Its neck likely helped it feed across a wide area without needing to move its massive body, possibly giving it access to high or scattered vegetation in Jurassic forests.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_stegosaurus_description">Stegosaurus is a genus of armored dinosaurs known for their distinctive double row of large, bony plates along the back and the spiked tail, or thagomizer. These large, heavily built herbivores likely used their plates for thermoregulation, species recognition, or display rather than defense. The first Stegosaurus specimen was discovered during the “Bone Wars”—the famous fossil rivalry between paleontologists Edward Drinker Cope and Othniel Charles Marsh in the late 19th century.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_epidexipteryx_description">Epidexipteryx was a small, bird-like dinosaur that represents one of the earliest known examples of ornamental feathers in the fossil record. These long, ribbon-like tail feathers were likely used for display, possibly in mating rituals or for species recognition, rather than for flight.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_dilophosaurus_description">Dilophosaurus was one of the largest predators of the Early Jurassic period and is easily recognized by the pair of rounded crests on its skull. It measured around 7 meters in length and weighed approximately 400 kilograms. This dinosaur was inaccurately portrayed in the movie Jurassic Park—it did not have neck frills, could not spit venom, and was significantly larger than shown in the film.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_dimorphodon_description">Dimorphodon was a medium-sized pterosaur that likely lived in coastal regions during the Early Jurassic period. It had relatively short wings compared to other pterosaurs, suggesting it was not a strong flier. Instead, it may have relied on quick, flapping bursts of flight similar to those of modern chickens or woodpeckers. Its name means “two-form tooth,” referring to its distinctive combination of long and short teeth.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_epidendrosaurus_description">Epidendrosaurus was a sparrow-sized, feathered avialan dinosaur that likely lived in trees and fed on insects. It had elongated fingers with curved claws, which may have helped it climb or grasp branches. As one of the earliest known tree-dwelling dinosaurs, Epidendrosaurus provides important clues about the evolution of flight-related adaptations in birds.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_liopleurodon_description">Liopleurodon was a genus of large, carnivorous marine reptiles belonging to the Pliosauridae family, a subgroup of Plesiosauria. Fossils have been found mainly in England and France. Liopleurodon was a powerful swimmer, with strong flippers and a streamlined body, and typically grew to about 5–7 meters in length, though some fragmentary remains suggest the possibility of larger individuals.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_kentrosaurus_description">Kentrosaurus is a genus of stegosaurian dinosaur from the Late Jurassic period, known from fossils found in what is now Tanzania. It measured around 4.5 meters in length and weighed about one tonne. Kentrosaurus was a herbivore and likely lived in an environment with many predators, as suggested by its defensive adaptations—including a double row of plates and spikes along its back and tail, which may have served both protection and display functions.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="cretaceous_tyrannosaurus">Tyrannosaurus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_velociraptor">Velociraptor</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_spinosaurus">Spinosaurus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_pachycephalosaurus">Pachycephalosaurus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_triceratops">Triceratops</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_ankylosaurus">Ankylosaurus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_mosasaurus">Mosasaurus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_ammonite">Ammonoidea</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_therizinosaurus">Therizinosaurus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_tsintaosaurus">Tsintaosaurus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_deinocherus">Deinocheirus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_quetzalcoatlus">Quetzalcoatlus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_giganotosaurus">Giganotosaurus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_linhenykus">Linhenykus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_sarcosuchus">Sarcosuchus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_microraptor">Microraptor</string>

    <string name="cretaceous_tyrannosaurus_description">Tyrannosaurus is arguably the most famous dinosaur, widely recognized from films such as “Jurassic Park” and “The Lost World.” It is also one of the best-represented large theropods in the fossil record. Tyrannosaurus lived during the Late Cretaceous in what is now western North America. The most complete specimen discovered measures approximately 12.3 meters in length and stands up to 3.7 meters tall.\nWhile no direct evidence of feathers has been found on Tyrannosaurus itself, many paleontologists believe it likely had feathers on at least some parts of its body, based on evidence from closely related species. Below is an artistic interpretation of T. rex.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_velociraptor_description">Velociraptor was a bipedal, feathered carnivore with a long, stiff tail and an enlarged, sickle-shaped claw on each hind foot. Like Tyrannosaurus, it is one of the most familiar dinosaurs thanks to its prominent role in the “Jurassic Park” films. In reality, however, Velociraptor was roughly the size of a large turkey — much smaller than the human-sized predators depicted in the movies. Fossil evidence confirms that real Velociraptors had feathers and were likely warm-blooded, sharing many traits with modern birds.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_spinosaurus_description">Spinosaurus was one of the largest known carnivorous dinosaurs — possibly even larger than Tyrannosaurus rex. It could grow up to 14.3 meters in length and weigh around 20 tonnes. Fossil evidence indicates that it primarily ate fish, and most scientists believe it hunted both on land and in water. Spinosaurus likely led a semi-aquatic lifestyle, similar to that of modern crocodiles, with adaptations such as paddle-like feet and a long, narrow snout ideal for catching prey in aquatic environments.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_pachycephalosaurus_description">Pachycephalosaurus was a bipedal herbivorous dinosaur best known for its extremely thick, domed skull roof, which could be over 25 centimeters thick. It lived during the Late Cretaceous and was among the last non-avian dinosaurs to exist before the Cretaceous–Paleogene extinction event. Some scientists believe it may have used its thick skull for head-butting or display behavior, though this remains debated.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_triceratops_description">Triceratops was a herbivorous dinosaur and one of the last known non-avian dinosaurs, living during the very end of the Late Cretaceous. It is estimated that Triceratops could grow up to 9 meters in length, 3 meters in height, and weigh around 12 tonnes. It is easily recognized by its large bony frill and three facial horns, which may have been used for defense, mating displays, or social interactions within the species.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_ankylosaurus_description">Ankylosaurus was a genus of heavily armored dinosaurs and among the last surviving non-avian dinosaurs, living during the Late Cretaceous. Large individuals could reach up to 6.25 meters in length, 1.7 meters in height, and weigh around 6 tonnes. Ankylosaurus is most famous for its massive club-like tail, which may have been used for defense against predators like Tyrannosaurus.\nRecent fossil discoveries suggest that some ankylosaurs may have had countershading — a form of camouflage where the body is darker on top and lighter underneath — providing protection from predators. This indicates a high level of predation pressure during the final stages of the Cretaceous.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_mosasaurus_description">Mosasaurus was an extinct genus of large, carnivorous marine lizards that lived during the Late Cretaceous. It could grow up to 17 meters in length, making it one of the top predators of its time. Fossil evidence suggests that it lived near the ocean surface, where it hunted a wide range of prey, including fish, turtles, ammonites, smaller mosasaurs, seabirds, pterosaurs, and plesiosaurs. Its long, streamlined body and powerful tail made it an efficient swimmer, and it likely used ambush tactics to capture its prey.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_ammonite_description">Ammonites were an extinct group of marine mollusks, closely related to modern squids and octopuses. They are well-known for their spiral shells and are considered excellent index fossils because they evolved rapidly and were widespread. Ammonites first appeared in the Devonian Period and thrived for hundreds of millions of years. They are mentioned here because they were among the most iconic marine creatures to go extinct during the Cretaceous–Paleogene extinction event.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_therizinosaurus_description">Therizinosaurus cheloniformis was a large and unusual theropod dinosaur that lived during the Late Cretaceous. It could reach up to 10 meters in length and weigh around 5 tonnes. Therizinosaurus is best known for its enormous claws — the longest of any known animal — which could grow up to 70 centimeters in length. Although it belonged to a group of theropods, which are typically carnivorous, Therizinosaurus was likely herbivorous, with long necks, small heads, and a beaked mouth adapted for browsing vegetation.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_tsintaosaurus_description">Tsintaosaurus was a herbivorous hadrosaurid dinosaur, easily recognized by its characteristic “duck-billed” snout and a battery of strong, closely packed teeth adapted for chewing tough vegetation. It measured about 10 meters in length and stood approximately 3.6 meters tall. Tsintaosaurus lived during the Late Cretaceous and may have had a hollow, unicorn-like crest on its head, although the structure and function of this crest remain subjects of scientific debate.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_deinocherus_description">Deinocheirus was a highly unusual dinosaur that lived during the Late Cretaceous. It could grow up to 11 meters in length and weigh around 6.4 tonnes, making it one of the largest members of the ornithomimosaur group. It had a pair of massive arms with long claws, which were likely used for foraging, possibly to dig or gather plants. Fossil evidence suggests that Deinocheirus was omnivorous, feeding on a mix of plants, small animals, and possibly fish. It is also thought to have been a slow-moving animal with a bulky build and a sail-like structure along its back.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_quetzalcoatlus_description">Quetzalcoatlus was a giant pterosaur and one of the largest known flying animals of all time. Its name is derived from the Mesoamerican feathered serpent god, Quetzalcoatl. With an estimated wingspan of 10–11 meters, it likely stood around 3 meters tall when on the ground. Quetzalcoatlus lived during the Late Cretaceous and may have soared long distances using thermal air currents. Despite its size, it is believed to have been capable of flight and may have hunted small animals or scavenged for food on land.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_giganotosaurus_description">Giganotosaurus was a giant theropod dinosaur that lived during the Late Cretaceous in what is now Argentina. It was comparable in size — and possibly even slightly longer — than Tyrannosaurus rex, though it was more lightly built. Like Tyrannosaurus, it is believed to have had a metabolism somewhere between that of modern reptiles and mammals, allowing it to maintain a relatively stable body temperature. Giganotosaurus was likely a top predator in its ecosystem, preying on large herbivorous dinosaurs such as sauropods.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_linhenykus_description">Linhenykus is the only known non-avian dinosaur to have had a single functional finger. It was a small-bodied theropod that lived during the Late Cretaceous in what is now Mongolia. Although its body shape resembles that of a modern ostrich, it was not closely related to birds like ostriches. Linhenykus belonged to a group called alvarezsaurids, which were specialized for digging and may have used their single large claw to break into insect nests, such as those of termites.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_sarcosuchus_description">Sarcosuchus was an extinct genus of crocodyliform and a distant relative of modern crocodilians. It was one of the largest crocodile-like reptiles to have ever lived and existed during the Early Cretaceous in what is now Africa and South America. Sarcosuchus could grow up to 11–12 meters in length and weigh as much as 8 tonnes — nearly twice the size of today\'s saltwater crocodile. It lived in freshwater environments and likely hunted both aquatic prey such as fish and terrestrial animals, similar to the behavior of modern Nile crocodiles.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_microraptor_description">Microraptor was a genus of small, four-winged paravian dinosaurs that lived during the Early Cretaceous. Its exceptionally well-preserved fossils provide crucial evidence for the evolutionary link between birds and dinosaurs. Microraptor was one of the most abundant non-avialan dinosaurs in its ecosystem. Adult specimens are estimated to have reached up to 77 centimeters in length and weighed around 1 kilogram. It was an opportunistic predator that likely fed on small mammals, bird-like dinosaurs, lizards, and even fish, suggesting it may have been capable of gliding or controlled flight to ambush prey.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="paleogene_titanoboa">Titanoboa</string>
    <string name="paleogene_gastornis">Gastornis</string>
    <string name="paleogene_basilosaurus">Basilosaurus</string>
    <string name="paleogene_paraceratherium">Paraceratherium</string>
    <string name="paleogene_daeodon">Daeodon</string>
    <string name="paleogene_pyrotherium">Pyrotherium</string>
    <string name="paleogene_archaeotherium">Archaeotherium</string>
    <string name="paleogene_arsinoitherium">Arsinoitherium</string>

    <string name="paleogene_titanoboa_description">Titanoboa is the largest known snake, which could reach 13 meters in length and weigh up to 1.2 tonnes. It mostly fed on fish and lived in the Paleocenian tropics.</string>
    <string name="paleogene_gastornis_description">Gastornis were very large birds that lived during the Late Paleocene and Eocene. They could grow up to 2 metres in height and have traditionally been considered to be predators of small mammals. However, several lines of evidence, including the lack of hooked claws in known Gastornis footprints and studies of their beak structure have caused scientists to reinterpret these birds as herbivores that probably fed on tough plant material and seeds.</string>
    <string name="paleogene_basilosaurus_description">Basilosaurus is a genus of the early whales that lived in the Late Eocene. Unlike modern whales, Basilosaurus was an apex predator.\nBelow you can see the currently known transitional whale evolution forms.</string>
    <string name="paleogene_paraceratherium_description">Paraceratherium is an extinct genus of hornless rhinoceros and one of the largest terrestrial mammals that has ever existed. Its height was about 4.8 metres, and the length about 7.4 metres, and weight is estimated to have been 15 to 20 tonnes.</string>
    <string name="paleogene_daeodon_description">Daeodon is an extinct genus of artiodactyl (elks, boars, bisons etc. are artiodactyls too) that inhabited North America during the Late Oligocene and Early Miocene epochs. They were around 1.8 m tall at the shoulders and had skulls about 90 cm long.</string>
    <string name="paleogene_pyrotherium_description">Pyrotherium is an extinct mammal genus related to the modern ungulates (like pigs, cattle, deers), that lived in Argentina during the Early Oligocene. They could weigh up to 3500 kg and were about 1.5 metres tall.</string>
    <string name="paleogene_archaeotherium_description">Archaeotherium is an extinct animal related to the pigs, which lived in the modern North America. It was about 1.2 metres tall and weighed around 270 kg.</string>
    <string name="paleogene_arsinoitherium_description">Arsinoitherium is an extinct mammal related to the modern elephants. They were rhinoceros-like herbivores that lived in the northern Africa, in areas of the tropical rainforest and at the margin of the mangrove swamps. Adult species stood around 1.75 meters tall.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="neogene_argentavis">Argentavis</string>
    <string name="neogene_ardipithecus">Ardipithecus</string>
    <string name="neogene_megalodon">Megalodon</string>
    <string name="neogene_levyatan">Livyatan</string>
    <string name="neogene_titanis">Titanis</string>
    <string name="neogene_deinotherium">Deinotherium</string>
    <string name="neogene_platybelodon">Platybelodon</string>
    <string name="neogene_stegotetrabelodon">Stegotetrabelodon</string>

    <string name="neogene_argentavis_description">Argentavis is among the largest flying birds ever to exist, having an estimated wing span of 5&#8211;6 meters, a height of 1.5&#8211;2 meters and a mass of approximately 70 kilograms. It probably preferred to scavenge for carrion.</string>
    <string name="neogene_ardipithecus_description">Ardipithecus might be one of the earliest ancestors of humans after they diverged from the main ape lineage, although it is still a matter of debate. It was very similar to chimpanzees and lived in the territory of the modern Ethiopia. Ardipithecus had a small brain, measuring between 300 and 350 cm3. This is slightly smaller than a modern chimpanzee brain and roughly 20% the size of the modern human brain. Nevertheless, it is in some ways unlike chimpanzees, suggesting that the common ancestor differs from the modern chimpanzee. After the chimpanzee and human lineages diverged, both underwent substantial evolutionary change. Chimp feet are specialized for grasping trees; Ardipithecus feet are better suited for walking.</string>
    <string name="neogene_megalodon_description">Carcharodon megalodon also known as megalodon is an extinct species of shark which lived almost until the end of the Neogene. It was one of the largest and most powerful predators in vertebrate history, reaching 18 metres in length. It is known, that they preyed on whales and fish. They extinct probably because of the multiple reasons, including the oceanic cooling, sea level drops and the decline in food supply.</string>
    <string name="neogene_levyatan_description">Livyatan is an extinct whale, similar in size to the modern sperm whale. It reached almost 18 meters in length and had powerful functional teeth in both of its jaws. It was an apex predator along with the giant megalodon. Its extinction was likely caused by a cooling event at the end of the Miocene which resulted in a drop in food populations. The formations where the whale has been found have also preserved a large assemblage of marine life, such as sharks and marine mammals.</string>
    <string name="neogene_titanis_description">Titanis walleri is a large extinct flightless carnivorous bird, which lived in the North America. It was about 2.5 meters tall and weighed approximately 150 kilograms. It is one of the famous terror birds, which were dominant predators in the early Cenozoic and Middle Cenozoic era.</string>
    <string name="neogene_deinotherium_description">Deinotherium was a large prehistoric relative of the modern-day elephants. They differed only by a shorter trunk, and it had downward curling tusks attached to the lower jaw. They could grow up to 4 meters tall and weigh about 12 tonnes.</string>
    <string name="neogene_platybelodon_description">Platybelodon was a large herbivorous mammal related to the elephants. They lived in Asia and the Caucascus.</string>
    <string name="neogene_stegotetrabelodon_description">Stegotetrabelodon is an extinct primitive elephant with four tusks instead of two. They lived in Africa and were very similar to the modern elephants. Below is an artist interpretation, how it really could look like.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="quaternary_mammutus">Mammuthus</string>
    <string name="quaternary_coelodonta">Coelodonta</string>
    <string name="quaternary_megatherium">Megatherium</string>
    <string name="quaternary_smilodon">Smilodon</string>
    <string name="quaternary_coelacanth">Coelacanth</string>
    <string name="quaternary_xiphosura">Horse-shoe crab</string>
    <string name="quaternary_ginkgo">Ginkgo</string>
    <string name="quaternary_welwitschia">Welwitschia</string>
    <string name="quaternary_tuatara">Tuatara</string>
    <string name="quaternary_human">Human</string>
    <string name="quaternary_dodo">Dodo</string>
    <string name="quaternary_megalania">Megalania</string>

    <string name="quaternary_mammutus_description">Mammoths were large mammals, close elephant relatives covered by the long hair. Most of the mammoths were as large as the modern Asian elephants and lived in the northern hemisphere where colder climate was prevalent.\nThey fed on trees and shrubs. Mammoths vanished from Africa about 3&#8211;4 million years ago, from Europe and American mainland – about 10,000 years ago and some small populations survived almost until the recent days. The last known population lived in Wrangel island, until it died 3750 years ago.\nThe main cause of their extinction was the warming climate that occurred 12,000 years ago, accompanied by a glacial retreat, rising sea levels and diminishing of the plain tundra by the forests.\nCurrently, there are two separate projects in Japan and South Korea working towards recreating mammoth specimens from the DNA extracted from the frozen mammoths. Also, there is an ongoing project in the northeastern part of Russia called Pleistocene Park, where the russian scientist S. Zimov and his team are trying to prepare pasture for the possibly cloned mammoths. I really recommend watching a VICE documentary called “The Crazy Solution For Keeping The Melting Arctic Frozen”.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_coelodonta_description">Coelodonta is an extinct genus of woolly rhinoceros that lived in Eurasia almost until the recent days. Many species of Pleistocene megafauna, like woolly rhinoceros, became extinct around the same period. Human hunting is often cited as the possible cause of their extinction. Other extinction theories are associated with the climate change and the receding ice age. The last woolly rhinoceros population lived in Western Siberia about 10,000 years ago.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_megatherium_description">Megatherium was a genus of elephant-size ground sloths, that lived in South America. It weighed around 4 tonnes and measured up to 6 meters in length. It was adapted to temperate, arid or semi-arid open habitats. It fed on leaves such as yuccas, agaves and grasses. They died about 10,000 years ago because of the fragmentation of their habitats.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_smilodon_description">Smilodon is the best known as the saber tooth cat. It lived in the Americas almost until the recent days and could weigh almost 400 kilograms and grow up to 120 cm tall. They hunted large herbivores such as bisons and camels. They extinct together with the other large herbivores, because prey became smaller and more agile.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_coelacanth_description">Latimeria (or Coelacanth) is the oldest known living lobe-finned fish, known as the living fossil. They may live as long as 80 to 100 years and live as deep as 700 m below sea level. They feed on squids, small sharks and other fish. Scientists suspect one reason this fish has been so successful is that the specimens are able to slow down their metabolism at will. They live near the Sodwana Bay, South Africa.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_xiphosura_description">The Xiphosura, which includes the horseshoe crabs is the group, that hardly changed in millions of years and are considered to be the living fossils. They are related with another dominant Paleozoic arthropod group – trilobites. Their blood is very important for the modern medicine, because it is used for the detection of the bacterial endotoxins.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_ginkgo_description">Ginkgo is the only living species of the ancient plant division Ginkgophyta. It is found in fossils dating back 270 million years. Native to China, the tree is widely cultivated and is used in traditional medicine and as a source of food.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_welwitschia_description">Welwitschia is one of the three genus of the ancient plant division Gnetophyta. It grows in the Namib desert and is known as a living fossil. Many current individuals are over 1000 years old and some may be more than 2000 years old. Welwitschia produces a single pair of foliage leaves. Gnetophyta plants are relatives of the modern flowering plants.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_tuatara_description">Tuatara are reptiles endemic to New Zealand and the only alive specimens of the ancient reptile group – Rhynchocephalia, which flourished around 200 million years ago. They measure up to 80 cm and weigh up to 1.3 kg. They are terrestrial and nocturnal and thrive in much lower temperatures than those tolerated by most reptiles and hibernate during winter.\nNow they are extremely endangered because of the introduced rats and the habitat loss.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_human_description">Human or Homo sapiens is the most successful large vertebrate species to ever roam the Earth.  The estimated human population by the 2017 is around 7.5 billion and humans occupy most of the natural niches except the deep oceans, salt lakes, deep caves and Antarctica (although there are some specimens reported to live there, at least seasonally). It is currently deemed of “least concern” on the Red List of endangered species by the IUCN.\nTraditionally, there are two competing views of paleoanthropology about the origin of the H. sapiens: the recent African origin and the multiregional origin. More accepted single origin theory states, that modern humans appeared in East Africa and later migrated up north, when the glaciers retreated. They overwhelmed northern living H. neanderthalensis, which were already losing their genetic diversity and later migrated all around the world, by killing and destroying most of the natural habitats and animal species on their way. Later it became an apex, opportunistic predator, however different human populations specialized in different kind of food, for example: Japanese are regarded as the most ferocious marine predators, killing thousands of whales, dolphins, sharks and other sea animals each year; Chinese are known for their passion of killing rhinoceros, elephants and other horned animals, they even recently wiped out the Northern White Rhinoceros species in Africa, great job! European populations have depleted their natural resources long time ago, so they usually use other populations to bring them food and are best known for their manipulative skills and so on.\nThe human creating this application is about 1.83 meters long and weights about 69 kilograms, and is alive because of the photosynthesis.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_dodo_description">The dodo is an extinct flightless bird that was endemic to the island of Mauritius, east of Madagascar in the Indian Ocean. It was about 1 metre tall and may have weighed up to 17 kg and is related to the pigeons. The dodo was historically been considered fat and clumsy, but it was well-adapted for its ecosystem. It used gizzard stones to help digest their food (mainly fruits).\nThe first recorded mention of the dodo was by Dutch sailors in 1598. In the following years, the bird was hunted by sailors and invasive species, while its habitat was being destroyed. The last widely accepted sighting of a dodo was in 1662. The extinction of the dodo within less than a century of its discovery called attention to the previously unrecognized problem of human involvement in the disappearance of entire species.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_megalania_description">Megalania is an extinct giant lizard and it was a part of a megafauna that inhabited southern Australia during the Pleistocene. The youngest fossil remains date around 50,000 years ago. The first aboriginal settlers of Australia might have encountered them and been a factor in their extinction. Largest individuals could grow up to 7 m long with a maximum weight of approximately 600&#8211;620 kg. It fed mostly upon medium to large sized animals and had a jaw full of serrated blade-like teeth.</string>

</resources>