<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>

    <string name="geological_time_scale">Geological time scale</string>

    <string name="environment">Environment</string>
    <string name="general_information">Description</string>
    <string name="life_forms">Life</string>

    <string name="map_author_1">&#169; Masato Hattori</string>
    <string name="map_author_2">&#169; C. R. Scotese</string>

    <string name="mya">%s mya</string>

    <string name="hadean">Hadean</string>
    <string name="archean">Archean</string>
    <string name="proterozoic">Proterozoic</string>
    <string name="cambrian">Cambrian</string>
    <string name="ordovician">Ordovician</string>
    <string name="silurian">Silurian</string>
    <string name="devonian">Devonian</string>
    <string name="carboniferous">Carboniferous</string>
    <string name="permian">Permian</string>
    <string name="triassic">Triassic</string>
    <string name="jurassic">Jurassic</string>
    <string name="cretaceous">Cretaceous</string>
    <string name="paleogene">Paleogene</string>
    <string name="neogene">Neogene</string>
    <string name="quaternary">Quaternary</string>
    <string name="future">Future</string>

    <string name="hadean_short_description">Early Earth formation, first water.</string>
    <string name="archean_short_description">Single-celled life traces, first oxygen. Photosynthesis.</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_short_description">Multi-celled life traces, atmospheric oxygen. Global glaciations.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_short_description">Modern complex life appearance.</string>
    <string name="ordovician_short_description">Modern life diversification trends continue.</string>
    <string name="silurian_short_description">First terrestrial plants.</string>
    <string name="devonian_short_description">First terrestrial tetrapods.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_short_description">Times of the large forests and insects. Pangaea formation.</string>
    <string name="permian_short_description">Arid Earth period. Largest mass extinction in the Earth history.</string>
    <string name="triassic_short_description">First mammals and dinosaurs.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_short_description">Dinosaur dominance. Division of the Pangaea.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_short_description">Flowering plants appearance. Dinosaur extinction.</string>
    <string name="paleogene_short_description">Mammal dominance. Eocene thermal maximum.</string>
    <string name="neogene_short_description">Modern fauna formation. First hominids.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_short_description">Time of the Ice Ages. Current times.</string>
    <string name="future_short_description">Who knows.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="hadean_physics">Mean temperature: 70&#8211;2100 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 0%</string>
    <string name="hadean_description">Hadean Eon – the earliest period of Earth\'s history, spanning from the planet\'s formation approximately 4.56 billion years ago until the emergence of stable tectonic plates around 4.0 billion years ago.\nThe landscape of the Early Hadean was extremely hostile, resembling a hellish environment. The surface was dominated by widespread volcanic activity, molten rock, and frequent bombardment by meteorites and comets.\nThe first 100 million years were far too inhospitable for any form of life, with surface temperatures reaching around 230 degrees Celsius—and in the earliest stages, even exceeding 2000 degrees Celsius. Atmospheric pressure was estimated to be about 27 times higher than today. While Earth possessed a primitive atmosphere, it was repeatedly stripped away by intense collisions with other celestial bodies.\nAround 4.4 billion years ago, the planet began to cool, as evidenced by zircon crystals, which suggest the presence of liquid water during this period. The end of the Hadean Eon is marked by the stabilization of Earth\'s crust, the formation of early oceans, and the beginnings of continental crust.</string>
    <string name="hadean_additional_title"></string>
    <string name="hadean_additional"></string>
    <string name="hadean_life_forms">There is no definitive proof that life could have existed in such a harsh environment. However, 4.1-billion-year-old graphite deposits found in Western Australia contain carbon isotopes that suggest possible biological origins, indicating that conditions for life may have been sustainable earlier than previously thought. Some scientists hypothesize that life may have emerged multiple times during the Hadean Eon, only to be repeatedly annihilated by catastrophic asteroid impacts and extreme volcanic activity. Additionally, carbon-rich meteorites, which delivered organic molecules to early Earth, support the idea that the building blocks of life may have originated in space.</string>

    <string name="archean_physics">Mean temperature: 45&#8211;70 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 0%</string>
    <string name="archean_description">The Archean Eon – the second eon in Earth\'s history – spans from approximately 4.0 billion years ago, when the first tectonic plates began to form, to around 2.5 billion years ago, just before the Great Oxidation Event.\nAt the beginning of this eon, Earth\'s temperature was 2–3 times higher than today. This was primarily due to a high concentration of greenhouse gases (dozens of times higher than today) and residual heat from planetary accretion and core formation.\nDuring this period, the Sun\'s luminosity was about 70–75% of its present level, leading to a \"faint young Sun paradox\", which was mitigated by the greenhouse effect. By the end of the Archean, Earth\'s tectonic activity had evolved into a more modern-like system, and vast oceans of liquid water covered much of the planet, providing the conditions for the emergence of early microbial life.</string>
    <string name="archean_additional_title">Late heavy bombardment</string>
    <string name="archean_additional">Around 4.0 billion years ago, the planets of our solar system, including Earth, experienced intense bombardment by large cosmic bodies for approximately 200 million years. This period, known as the Late Heavy Bombardment (LHB), is evidenced by lunar samples collected by Apollo astronauts, which contain high-impact melt formations.\nExtrapolating lunar cratering rates to Earth at this time suggests that the planet would have experienced:\n1. Approximately 22,000 craters with diameters greater than 20 km.\n2. Around 40 craters with diameters exceeding 1,000 km.\n3. Several craters with diameters close to 5,000 km.\nThe prevailing hypothesis for this bombardment is that the giant planets – such as Jupiter, Saturn, and Neptune – underwent orbital migration. This gravitational disturbance scattered objects from the asteroid and/or Kuiper belts into eccentric orbits, increasing the impact rate on the inner planets. This event may have delayed the emergence of life during the Early Archean by creating a hostile surface environment through frequent, high-energy impacts.</string>
    <string name="archean_life_forms">Unlike in the Hadean, the presence of life during the Archean is well established, though the exact timing of its emergence remains debated.\nThe earliest solid evidence of life comes from 3.48-billion-year-old stromatolites found in Australia. Additionally, 3.85-billion-year-old isotopic signatures in Greenland suggest biological activity, though their interpretation is contested.\nBanded iron formations (BIFs) also date back to this period. While some argue that their formation required oxygen from early photosynthetic microbes, others suggest alternative abiotic processes could have played a role.\nPossible early prokaryotes have been identified in Canadian rocks at least 3.77 billion years old, and lipid biomarker analysis suggests that the first eukaryotes may have emerged by the late Archean, around 2.7 billion years ago.</string>

    <string name="proterozoic_physics">Mean temperature: 5&#8211;45 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 0&#8211;12%</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_description">The Proterozoic Eon – the third major eon in Earth\'s history, spanning from approximately 2.5 billion to 541 million years ago, just before the widespread emergence of complex life. Key events of this eon include the transition to an oxygen-rich atmosphere during the Great Oxidation Event, multiple global glaciations (such as those associated with the Snowball Earth hypothesis during the Huronian, Sturtian, and Marinoan glaciations), and the evolution of early multicellular eukaryotic organisms, including soft-bodied life forms like those of the Ediacaran biota.\nThis is a hypothetical reconstruction of a Snowball Earth scenario during the Huronian and Cryogenian glaciations.</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_additional_title">Great Oxidation Event</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_additional">The Great Oxidation Event was the biologically induced rise of oxygen in Earth\'s atmosphere, occurring around 2.4 to 2.1 billion years ago. The widely accepted hypothesis states that the primary driver of this event was the evolution of oxygenic photosynthesis in cyanobacteria.\nBefore this event, any free oxygen produced was rapidly consumed by chemical reactions with dissolved iron or organic matter. However, once these oxygen sinks became saturated, excess oxygen began accumulating in the atmosphere.\nFree oxygen is toxic to obligate anaerobic organisms, leading to a major extinction event. Additionally, atmospheric oxygen reacted with methane, a potent greenhouse gas, significantly lowering its concentration. This process likely triggered the Huronian glaciation, which lasted approximately 300 million years (from ~2.4 to ~2.1 billion years ago).\nThese profound changes in Earth\'s atmospheric and chemical cycles created new evolutionary pressures and opportunities. Life adapted first to tolerate and then to harness atmospheric oxygen, leading to the development of aerobic respiration. This metabolic breakthrough vastly increased the available energy supply, enabling the evolution of more complex, multicellular organisms.</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_life_forms">The Proterozoic Eon marks a crucial transition in the evolution of life, from simple unicellular organisms to more complex forms. During the Great Oxidation Event, many anaerobic organisms declined due to oxygen toxicity, while oxygen-tolerant and aerobic life forms, including early eukaryotic protists and bacteria, proliferated. By the mid-Proterozoic, stromatolites—microbial reef-like structures built by cyanobacteria—reached their peak diversity. During this time, the ancestors of fungi diverged from the ancestors of animals, marking an important evolutionary split within eukaryotes. By the Ediacaran Period (635–541 million years ago), the first complex, soft-bodied multicellular organisms had appeared, including members of the enigmatic Ediacaran biota, which represent some of the earliest known macroscopic life forms.</string>

    <string name="cambrian_physics">Mean temperature: 21 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 12.5%</string>
    <string name="cambrian_description">The Cambrian Period was the first geological period of the Paleozoic Era and marked a profound transformation in life on Earth. Before the Cambrian, most living organisms were microscopic and relatively simple. However, the Cambrian saw an unprecedented diversification of life in an event known as the Cambrian Explosion. During this time, many major animal phyla first appeared in the fossil record, and complex ecosystems emerged.\nThe great glaciers of the late Proterozoic Eon had long melted, leading to high sea levels that flooded vast areas of continents with warm, shallow seas—an ideal environment for marine life. The Earth was generally cool during the Early Cambrian, likely due to the supercontinent Gondwana covering the South Pole, which disrupted polar ocean currents. However, global temperatures were still around 7°C higher than today. While polar ice caps and glaciations may have existed, the climate gradually warmed toward the end of the period. Glaciers retreated, sea levels rose dramatically, and this warming trend continued into the Ordovician Period.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_additional_title">The Cambrian Explosion</string>
    <string name="cambrian_additional">The Cambrian Explosion was a relatively brief evolutionary event, during which approximately 63% of all biological classes and most of the major modern animal phyla first appeared. This period saw the emergence of complex ecosystems, with the development of burrowing behaviors and the widespread diversification of skeletonized animals, which were previously absent or rare.\nPossible causes of this evolutionary event:\n1. Increased atmospheric oxygen levels, which supported larger and more complex organisms.\n2. The formation of an ozone layer, reducing the harmful effects of ultraviolet (UV) radiation and enabling life to thrive in shallower waters.\n3. The Snowball Earth events during the late Proterozoic, which led to mass extinctions and opened up ecological niches for new life forms.\n4. Higher calcium concentrations in Cambrian seawater, allowing marine organisms to develop skeletons, shells, and other hard body structures.\n5. Developmental changes, including the evolution of Hox genes, which played a key role in organizing body plans and enabling more complex organisms to form.\n6. Changes in the food web, leading to coevolution and predator-prey “arms races” that drove anatomical and behavioral innovations.\nThe Cambrian was also a time of evolutionary experimentation, resulting in many bizarre and unique body plans, some of which have no modern descendants.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_life_forms">Most animal life during the Cambrian was aquatic. Arthropods were by far the most dominant animals in the ocean, with trilobites being particularly abundant. This period also saw the emergence of many new mineralized organisms, as well as the first widespread burrowing animals, which played a key role in reshaping seafloor ecosystems. However, unlike in modern times, most animals lived on or near the sea floor, with very few swimming or pelagic species.</string>

    <string name="ordovician_physics">Mean temperature: 16 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 13.5%</string>
    <string name="ordovician_description">The Ordovician is the second of six periods of the Paleozoic Era. During this period, ancient oceans separated the largely barren continents of Laurentia, Baltica, Siberia, and the supercontinent Gondwana. The Ordovician saw a great diversification of marine life, including the rise of early corals, cephalopods, and the first jawless fish. However, the period ended with one of the most severe ice ages in Earth’s history, leading to the second-largest mass extinction, which wiped out around 85% of marine species. Ice sheets covered much of the southern region of Gondwana, dramatically altering global sea levels and climate.</string>
    <string name="ordovician_additional_title">Ordovician Radiation</string>
    <string name="ordovician_additional">The Ordovician period is notable for the Great Ordovician Biodiversification Event (GOBE), a time of rapid biological diversification that replaced the distinctive Cambrian fauna with a Paleozoic fauna rich in suspension feeders and pelagic animals. This event followed the Cambrian-Ordovician extinction, which was likely caused by a sudden glaciation and a depletion of available oxygen in the oceans.\nThe primary driver of the Ordovician radiation was a major shift in paleogeography. Due to high sea levels, continents became highly fragmented into distinct marine provinces, fostering regional biodiversity. Intense orogeny (mountain-building events), along with increased erosion, contributed to high ecosystem productivity by delivering abundant nutrients into the oceans.\nWhile the Cambrian Explosion was crucial in establishing most modern animal phyla, the GOBE can be seen as the event that diversified these phyla into modern classes and lower-level taxa, significantly shaping marine ecosystems that would persist for millions of years.</string>
    <string name="ordovician_life_forms">Life during the Ordovician continued to flourish, with an explosion of marine biodiversity, including the rise of the first coral reefs, trilobites, brachiopods, mollusks, and the first true vertebrates—jawless fish. However, the period ended with a catastrophic mass extinction at the boundary with the Silurian. This extinction was primarily driven by severe global cooling, glaciation, and associated sea-level changes. Despite this, the fauna that emerged and thrived during the Ordovician laid the foundation for marine ecosystems throughout the remainder of the Paleozoic Era.</string>

    <string name="silurian_physics">Mean temperature: 17 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 14%</string>
    <string name="silurian_description">The Silurian is a relatively short geological period, lasting approximately 24 to 28 million years. During this time, Laurentia collided with Baltica, closing the northern branch of the Iapetus Ocean and forming the "Old Red Sandstone" continent. Coral reefs thrived, becoming more widespread and diverse, and the first vascular land plants began to colonize the previously barren continents, marking a significant evolutionary step in the history of life on land.</string>
    <string name="silurian_additional_title">Terrestrial plant diversification</string>
    <string name="silurian_additional">The evolutionary appearance of vascular plants dramatically altered Earth\'s environment, paving the way for animal life on land and fundamentally changing Earth\'s atmosphere. Interestingly, plant evolution progressed much faster than animal evolution: during the Late Silurian, plants were structurally simple and small, but by the end of the Devonian (approximately 46 million years later), almost all present-day plant lineages (except flowering plants) had emerged.\nOne possible explanation is that adapting to terrestrial life posed a greater challenge for plants than for animals. At the level of the individual organism, all plants (except parasitic ones) must perform four essential functions to grow and survive:\n1. Intercept sunlight.\n2. Exchange atmospheric gases with the environment.\n3. Acquire, transport, and conserve water.\n4. Cope with external mechanical forces.\nThese tasks are interdependent and often conflict with one another. For example: a) Increasing surface area to capture more sunlight and facilitate gas exchange can reduce water conservation. b) Positioning leaves horizontally to maximize light interception increases mechanical stress.\nAquatic environments are relatively uniform and stable, while terrestrial environments are affected by wind, temperature changes, unpredictable precipitation, and varying sunlight. Adapting to diverse terrestrial conditions required innovative solutions for each of the basic functions, leading to significant diversification in plant body forms.\nAdditionally, greater exposure to ultraviolet light above the wate\'s surface likely caused more mutations, accelerating evolutionary changes. However, the theory of plant fitness – how well plants adapted to the challenges of terrestrial life – best explains the rapid evolution of land plants.</string>
    <string name="silurian_life_forms">Multicellular life began to appear on land in the form of small, bryophyte-like and early vascular plants that grew near lakes, streams, and coastlines. The Silurian period also marked the first appearance of arthropods on land, including primitive millipedes and arachnids. However, terrestrial life would not significantly diversify or impact the landscape until the Devonian period.\nA major evolutionary milestone during the Silurian was the diversification of bony fishes (Osteichthyes), which began to dominate marine ecosystems. This diversification laid the foundation for the evolution of many modern fish lineages.</string>

    <string name="devonian_physics">Mean temperature: 20 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 15%</string>
    <string name="devonian_description">The Devonian is the fourth of the six periods of the Paleozoic era. It was a relatively warm period, though occasionally disrupted by glaciations. The climate was generally arid, particularly near the equator. During this time, the Early Paleozoic oceans were gradually closing, leading to the formation of a “pre-Pangea” supercontinent. This continental configuration allowed fish to migrate from the southern hemisphere continents to North America and Europe. For the first time, extensive forests appeared in the equatorial regions of what is now Arctic Canada. The period concluded with the Late Devonian extinction, which resulted in the loss of about 50% of all genera, significantly impacting marine life, including many fish and reef-building organisms.</string>
    <string name="devonian_additional_title">The Late Devonian extinction</string>
    <string name="devonian_additional" formatted="false">The Late Devonian extinction was one of the five major extinction events in Earth\'s history. Rather than being a single event, it consisted of a series of two major crises known as the Kellwasser and Hangenberg events. It is estimated that around 75% of all animal species disappeared during this time. The extinction primarily affected marine life, severely impacting groups such as brachiopods, trilobites, and reef-building organisms, which almost completely collapsed. Major fish groups like Placodermi, Heterostraci, and Anaspida were completely wiped out. The extinction event destroyed approximately 97% of all vertebrate species, with only smaller forms surviving. In the aftermath, no sharks larger than a meter and almost no fishes or tetrapods larger than 10 centimeters remained, and it would take around 10 million years before they began to increase in size again. However, despite its catastrophic impact, the Late Devonian extinction crucially paved the way for the evolution of modern vertebrate fauna, including actinopterygians (ray-finned fishes), chondrichthyans (cartilaginous fishes), and tetrapods.\nThe crash in biodiversity during the Late Devonian was more drastic than the famous mass extinction event at the end of the Cretaceous.\nThe causes of this extinction event remain uncertain. Some proposed explanations include:\n1. An asteroid impact.\n2. Evolutionary changes in plants, particularly the development of root systems, which led to massive water eutrophication and subsequent anoxia.\n3. A reduction in atmospheric carbon dioxide, causing global cooling.\n4. Increased magmatism and volcanic activity.</string>
    <string name="devonian_life_forms">Free-sporing vascular plants began to spread across dry land during the Devonian period, covering the continents with extensive forests. By the Middle Devonian, several groups of plants had evolved leaves and true roots, marking significant advancements in plant evolution. Groups such as lycophytes, equisetophytes, and pteridophytes diversified, forming the first complex terrestrial ecosystems.\nFish achieved remarkable diversity during this time, earning the Devonian the nickname “Age of Fish”. Placoderms, armored prehistoric fish, were the most dominant group. The ancestors of tetrapods, particularly lobe-finned fish, began to adapt to walking on land, as their robust pectoral and pelvic fins gradually evolved into legs. These transitional species paved the way for the later evolution of amphibians.\nThe first ammonites (a group of molluscs) appeared, marking an important diversification of marine life. Trilobites and large coral reef systems remained common, with one notable now-dry barrier reef, located in what is now the Kimberley Basin of Northwest Australia, once extending approximately a thousand kilometers.</string>

    <string name="carboniferous_physics">Mean temperature: 14 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 32.5%</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_description">The name "Carboniferous" means “coal-bearing,” referring to the extensive coal deposits formed during this period. In the Early Carboniferous, the Paleozoic oceans between Euramerica and Gondwana began to close, giving rise to mountain ranges such as the Appalachians and the Variscans. A large ice cap developed over the South Pole, while lush, tropical coal swamps near the Equator supported the evolution of four-legged vertebrates (tetrapods) and the first winged insects.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_additional_title">Carboniferous collapse and coal</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_additional">The Carboniferous Rainforest Collapse was a significant ecological event that occurred around 305 million years ago. It disrupted the vast coal forests that once covered the equatorial region, fragmenting them into isolated patches. This fragmentation led to dwarfism and the eventual extinction of many plant and animal species.\nThe collapse resulted in the extinction of dominant lycopsid trees and a shift toward ecosystems dominated by more opportunistic plants like tree ferns. Before the event, animal species were distributed widely across the forests, but afterward, each isolated “island” of rainforest developed its own unique mix of species—this process is known as endemism.\nOxygen levels reached a record high of approximately 32.5% during the Carboniferous, allowing enormous arthropods like Meganeura (a giant dragonfly-like insect) and Arthropleura (a giant millipede-like arthropod) to thrive. However, following the rainforest collapse, oxygen levels declined, leading to the extinction of many of these giants. The increasingly arid climate also caused a mass decline in amphibian diversity, opening ecological space for reptiles to diversify—organisms better suited to dry environments.\nSeveral hypotheses have been proposed to explain the collapse, with the most widely accepted being climate aridification and increased volcanic activity.\nThis event also played a role in the formation of large coal deposits. During the Carboniferous, extensive swamp forests prevented the full decomposition of dead plant material. At the time, few animals or microbes had evolved enzymes to break down tough substances like phenolic lignin and waxy suberin. Fungi capable of decomposing these materials appeared only toward the end of the period, which is one reason why massive coal formation is largely limited to the Carboniferous.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_life_forms">The Carboniferous is renowned for its vast tropical rainforests dominated by towering plants like Lepidodendron, Sigillaria, and Calamites—some of the largest and most extensive forests in Earth’s history. Giant arthropods and insects thrived during this time, aided by high atmospheric oxygen levels and the absence of effective predators. Terrestrial vertebrates became increasingly abundant: amphibians diversified greatly, and following the Carboniferous Rainforest Collapse, reptiles began to flourish due to their better adaptation to drier environments.</string>

    <string name="permian_physics">Mean temperature: 16 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 23%</string>
    <string name="permian_description" formatted="false">The Permian was the final period of the Paleozoic Era, it ended with the most extensive mass extinction in Earth’s history, wiping out approximately 90% of marine species and 70% of terrestrial species. During this time, most of the world\'s landmasses were joined into two large continents—Pangaea and Siberia—surrounded by a vast global ocean called Panthalassa. Western Pangaea was dominated by arid deserts, while reptiles, including early ancestors of mammals, diversified and spread widely across the supercontinent.</string>
    <string name="permian_additional_title">Great Dying</string>
    <string name="permian_additional" formatted="false">The Permian and the entire Paleozoic Era ended 252 million years ago with the most severe mass extinction in Earth\'s history. The Permian-Triassic extinction event, also known as the Great Dying, wiped out about 95% of all marine species and 70% of all terrestrial species.\nMarine environments were hit particularly hard. Entire groups such as acanthodians (spiny sharks), sea scorpions, trilobites (already in decline), fusulinids, and Tabulata and Rugosa corals became completely extinct. Shelled marine animals were severely affected – 96% of brachiopod species, 97% of ammonites, 59% of bivalves, and 98% of gastropods perished.\nTerrestrial ecosystems also suffered enormously. Most large tetrapods disappeared, and around 80% of insect species were lost. Paleozoic wet forests, once dominated by ancient plants like Sigillaria, Lepidodendron, and Gigantopteris, were devastated due to widespread aridification and intense wildfires.\nSeveral interlinked causes contributed to this catastrophe:\n1. Massive volcanic eruptions in the region now known as the Siberian Traps released enormous quantities of carbon dioxide, methane, and hydrogen sulfide. These gases drastically altered atmospheric chemistry. Methane reacted with atmospheric oxygen, reducing oxygen levels from 30% to around 13%. The ozone layer was damaged, exposing the surface to harmful ultraviolet radiation. This led to a rapid increase in global temperatures—by as much as 8°C.\n2. Oceans became dangerously deoxygenated. Warmer temperatures reduced oxygen absorption, and toxic gases led to acidification. Acidic water dissolved the calcium carbonate shells of mollusks and corals, leading to their mass extinction. The proliferation of cyanobacteria and microbial mats further consumed what little oxygen remained, turning the seas into anoxic, acidic, nearly lifeless zones.\n3. A temporary weakening of Earth\'s magnetic field may have allowed increased solar radiation to reach the surface, creating extreme seasonal swings with scorching summers followed by bitterly cold winters.\nThe devastation was so profound that ecosystems took over 30 million years to recover their former diversity—not until the Middle Triassic. The extinction selectively eliminated dominant Paleozoic life forms, erasing 79% of their families, while only 27% of the lineages that would come to thrive in the Mesozoic were affected.</string>
    <string name="permian_life_forms">The Permian began with Carboniferous-era plant life still thriving. In the Middle Permian, a major shift in vegetation occurred: swamp-loving lycopod trees such as Lepidodendron and Sigillaria were gradually replaced by more advanced seed ferns like Glossopteris, along with early conifers, ginkgoes, and cycads.\nInsects during this time were dominated by primitive relatives of cockroaches and early dragonflies. Early Permian terrestrial ecosystems were populated by pelycosaurs (sail-backed synapsids like Dimetrodon) and large amphibians. By the Middle Permian, these groups declined and were succeeded by primitive therapsids – mammal-like reptiles. In the Late Permian, more advanced therapsids such as gorgonopsians emerged, becoming top predators.\nToward the very end of the Permian, the first archosaurs appeared—a group that would later evolve into dinosaurs, pterosaurs, and crocodiles. Also emerging in this period were the earliest cynodonts, small therapsids that would eventually give rise to mammals in the Triassic.</string>

    <string name="triassic_physics">Mean temperature: 17 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 16%</string>
    <string name="triassic_description">The Triassic began in the aftermath of the Permian-Triassic extinction event, the most severe extinction in Earth\'s history, which left the biosphere severely impoverished. Life began to recover significantly only by the middle of the Triassic period. \nDuring this time, the supercontinent Pangea was largely assembled, enabling land animals to migrate freely from the South Pole to the North Pole. Additionally, warm-water marine species spread across the vast Tethys Sea, supporting a resurgence of biodiversity in the oceans.</string>
    <string name="triassic_additional_title">The Nocturnal Bottleneck</string>
    <string name="triassic_additional">The nocturnal bottleneck hypothesis explains several unique traits of mammals. According to this hypothesis, mammals were primarily—or even exclusively—nocturnal for most of their early evolutionary history, beginning around 225 million years ago during the Late Triassic and continuing until the extinction of the dinosaurs around 65 million years ago. While some mammal groups later adapted to daytime (diurnal) activity, the approximately 160 million years spent in nocturnal niches left a lasting legacy on their anatomy and physiology. As a result, many mammals today retain nocturnal habits.\nMammals evolved from cynodonts, a group of mammal-like reptiles with dog-like features, in the aftermath of the Permian-Triassic mass extinction. Following this extinction, archosaurian reptiles—including ancestors of crocodiles and dinosaurs—rapidly diversified and came to dominate most ecological roles. This competition pushed the larger cynodonts toward extinction, leaving only smaller, more adaptable forms.\nThese surviving cynodonts likely occupied nocturnal, insect-eating niches with less competition from the dominant, diurnal dinosaurs. Over time, they evolved into early mammals—small-bodied, warm-blooded, and adapted to life in the undergrowth.\nEven after the extinction of the dinosaurs, mammals remained small for millions of years. Although mammals now include many large species, most are still relatively small and active at night.\nThe nocturnal bottleneck hypothesis also offers a compelling explanation for the evolution of mammalian warm-bloodedness (endothermy): cooler nighttime temperatures and burrowing lifestyles would have favored efficient internal temperature regulation and insulation.</string>
    <string name="triassic_life_forms">The Permian-Triassic extinction devastated both terrestrial and marine ecosystems. Although biodiversity began to rebound during the Triassic, early recovery stages were dominated by only a few resilient species. For example, up to 90% of large terrestrial vertebrates initially belonged to a single genus of therapsids—Lystrosaurus—highlighting the severe ecological damage and lack of biodiversity. Complex ecosystems with diverse food webs took nearly 30 million years to fully re-establish.\nBy the Middle Triassic, large therapsids had largely disappeared, and archosaurs—relatives of modern crocodiles, birds, and ancestors of dinosaurs—became the dominant land vertebrates. Dinosaurs began to diversify and gradually establish their dominance by the end of the period.\nOn land, seed plants became increasingly dominant over spore-bearing plants. In the Northern Hemisphere, conifers, ferns, and bennettitales thrived, while in the Southern Hemisphere, Glossopteris trees initially remained prominent before disappearing later in the period.\nLike other geological periods, the Triassic ended with a mass extinction. This event led to the disappearance of conodonts (a group of jawless marine vertebrates), many marine reptiles and invertebrates, and some remaining large therapsids and amphibians.</string>

    <string name="jurassic_physics">Mean temperature: 16.5 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 26%</string>
    <string name="jurassic_description">The Jurassic is the second period of the Mesozoic Era, often called the Age of Reptiles. During the Middle Jurassic, the supercontinent Pangaea began to break apart. By the Late Jurassic, the Central Atlantic Ocean had formed as a narrow sea separating Africa from North America. Additionally, Eastern Gondwana had started to drift away from Western Gondwana. This tectonic activity helped shape the continents as we know them today and influenced global climates and ecosystems.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_additional_title">Dinosaurian Prominence</string>
    <string name="jurassic_additional">About 20 million years after the Permian-Triassic extinction, dinosaurs evolved from their archosaurian ancestors and began to compete with the dominant archosauromorphs and therapsids. Initially, they were not the leading terrestrial animals. However, after the Triassic-Jurassic extinction event—which eliminated many of their competitors—dinosaurs rose to dominance and filled most major ecological niches for the next 135 million years.\nTwo major questions remain:\n1. How did some terrestrial dinosaurs grow to such massive sizes? Many sauropods, such as Argentinosaurus (estimated at over 70 tons), Mamenchisaurus, and Diplodocus, were enormous.\n2. Were dinosaurs feathered and warm-blooded?\nThese two questions are closely related, but still not fully resolved.\nThe largest dinosaurs were herbivores, and large body size likely provided protection from predators. In crowded ecosystems, herbivores may have evolved toward unoccupied ecological niches—especially larger size—creating an evolutionary “arms race” toward gigantism, within the constraints of physics and environment.\nFossil evidence shows that sauropods grew at astonishing rates—up to 5,000 kg per year. Such rapid growth suggests a high metabolic rate, unlike that of modern cold-blooded animals. However, high metabolism can become a disadvantage for very large animals, as heating and cooling large volumes of tissue becomes energetically costly. Current research suggests that juvenile sauropods were likely warm-blooded, but their metabolic rate may have decreased as they matured.\nOur understanding of dinosaur physiology continues to evolve. The outdated view of dinosaurs as sluggish, cold-blooded reptiles has largely been replaced by the idea that many species had active metabolisms and some form of thermoregulation. Fossil evidence from North America suggests some dinosaurs lived seasonally in cold climates. The discovery of feathered dinosaurs—including large species like Velociraptor and possibly even Tyrannosaurus rex—supports the theory that feathers were common among theropods. The only dinosaurs to survive the Cretaceous-Paleogene extinction—modern birds—are both feathered and warm-blooded. This raises a compelling question: why wouldn’t many Jurassic dinosaurs share these traits?</string>
    <string name="jurassic_life_forms">During the Jurassic period, the dominant marine vertebrates were fish and a variety of marine reptiles, including ichthyosaurs (marine reptiles that resembled modern dolphins), plesiosaurs (long-necked, paddle-limbed swimmers), pliosaurs (a group of plesiosaurs with shorter necks and larger heads), and marine-adapted crocodilians. Numerous turtles inhabited freshwater environments such as lakes and rivers.\nThe Jurassic was a golden age for sauropods—gigantic, long-necked herbivores like Diplodocus, Brachiosaurus, and Apatosaurus. It also saw the appearance of the first avialans (early bird-like dinosaurs), including the famous Archaeopteryx, which had feathers and could likely glide or make short powered flights.\nThe arid, continental conditions that characterized the Triassic gradually gave way to a more humid and tropical climate during the Jurassic. This warmer, wetter environment allowed dense forests and lush vegetation to spread. Conifers, along with cycads, ginkgoes, and ferns, dominated the plant life.</string>

    <string name="cretaceous_physics">Mean temperature: 18 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 30%</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_description">The Cretaceous was the final period of the Mesozoic Era, ending about 66 million years ago with a massive mass extinction — famously caused by an asteroid impact that contributed to the extinction of non-avian dinosaurs. This period was characterized by a relatively warm global climate and high sea levels, which formed vast shallow inland seas.\nDuring the Cretaceous, the South Atlantic Ocean began to open as South America and Africa drifted apart. India separated from Madagascar and moved rapidly northward toward a future collision with Eurasia — a movement that would eventually form the Himalayas. North America was still connected to Europe at times, and Australia remained attached to Antarctica.\nThe Cretaceous also saw the diversification of flowering plants (angiosperms), which began to transform ecosystems and food chains. Many modern insect groups appeared, co-evolving with these plants. In the oceans, large marine reptiles like mosasaurs thrived, while the skies were dominated by pterosaurs and early birds.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_additional_title">End of the Age of Dinosaurs</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_additional">The Cretaceous Period ended with a massive extinction event, known as the Cretaceous–Paleogene (K–Pg) extinction. Numerous plant and animal species were wiped out, including all non-avian dinosaurs. With the exception of some cold-blooded species like turtles and crocodilians, no tetrapods weighing more than 25 kilograms are known to have survived. This event marked the end of both the Cretaceous Period and the entire Mesozoic Era, ushering in the Cenozoic Era that continues to this day.\nWhat could cause such a devastating extinction? Today, there is overwhelming scientific consensus that the main cause was a massive asteroid — approximately 10 to 15 kilometers in diameter — that struck near what is now Mexico’s Yucatán Peninsula. The impact triggered global catastrophe: debris and dust ejected into the atmosphere blocked sunlight for months to years, halting photosynthesis. As a result, plant life collapsed, followed by the extinction of herbivores and then carnivores higher up the food chain.\nThe asteroid struck a region rich in sulfur-containing carbonate rock, releasing sulfur aerosols and causing acid rain and ocean acidification. This sharp drop in pH levels devastated marine ecosystems, wiping out many shell-forming organisms like ammonites and corals, along with the animals that fed on them. Sea surface temperatures fell by as much as 7°C, and it took hundreds of thousands of years for Earth’s climate and ecosystems to recover.\nOne intriguing question is why some of the dinosaurs’ close relatives, like crocodilians, survived. It is believed that their cold-blooded metabolism and ability to survive long periods without food helped them endure the harsh post-impact conditions — further evidence that non-avian dinosaurs were likely warm-blooded, at least to some extent.\nThe elimination of dominant Cretaceous species opened ecological niches for new life forms. This led to a remarkable period of adaptive radiation in the Paleogene. The most striking example is the rise of mammals, which quickly diversified to occupy roles previously held by dinosaurs. In a profound sense, the eventual evolution of humans may have depended on the extinction of the dinosaurs.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_life_forms">Flowering plants (angiosperms) first appeared during the Cretaceous, though they did not become ecologically dominant until the latter part of the period. Their evolution was closely tied to the emergence of pollinating insects, especially bees. In fact, angiosperms and insects are classic examples of coevolution — each influencing the evolution of the other. The Cretaceous also saw the first appearances of many modern leafy trees, such as figs, plane trees, and magnolias.\nOn land, mammals were typically small, but they were a vital part of the ecosystem. The dominant terrestrial predators remained archosaurian reptiles — especially dinosaurs, which reached their peak in diversity during this time. Pterosaurs were widespread in the Early and Middle Cretaceous, though their diversity declined later in the period for reasons that remain unclear.\nInsects underwent a significant diversification during the Cretaceous, with the emergence of many modern groups including ants, termites, butterflies and moths, aphids, grasshoppers, and gall wasps.\nIn the oceans, rays, modern sharks, and bony fishes became increasingly common. Marine reptiles included ichthyosaurs, which thrived in the Early and Middle Cretaceous, and later plesiosaurs and mosasaurs, which rose to prominence before the end of the period.</string>

    <string name="paleogene_physics">Mean temperature: 18 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 26%</string>
    <string name="paleogene_description">The Paleogene is the first period of the Cenozoic Era and includes the Paleocene, Eocene, and Oligocene epochs. The end of the Paleocene (around 55 million years ago) was marked by the Paleocene–Eocene Thermal Maximum (PETM), one of the most significant global warming events of the Cenozoic. This event caused rapid increases in temperature, major shifts in ecosystems, and the extinction of many deep-sea species.\nThroughout the Paleogene, Earth’s climate gradually cooled and dried, though this trend was occasionally interrupted by short-lived warming events. One major factor contributing to the cooling was the formation of the Antarctic Circumpolar Current, which thermally isolated Antarctica and significantly cooled ocean waters.\nDuring this period, the Indian subcontinent began colliding with Asia, giving rise to the Himalayan Mountains and the Tibetan Plateau. Australia, previously connected to Antarctica, started drifting northward, eventually influencing the formation of unique ecosystems like those found today.</string>
    <string name="paleogene_additional_title">PETM</string>
    <string name="paleogene_additional">The Paleocene–Eocene Thermal Maximum (PETM) was a period when global average temperatures were 5–8°C warmer than today. This major climate event began around 55.5 million years ago, at the boundary between the Paleocene and Eocene epochs.\nIt was triggered by two massive releases of carbon into the atmosphere, each lasting approximately 1,500 years. In total, the PETM lasted about 200,000 years. The amount of carbon released during this period was more than 30 times greater than all fossil fuels burned to date and comparable to the total known fossil fuel reserves.\nThe likely causes of this carbon surge include the melting of methane clathrates (frozen methane on the ocean floor) and volcanic activity heating organic-rich sediments, releasing large amounts of methane.\nThis warming led to increased storminess in some areas (similar to today’s Caribbean and East Asia), higher aridity in tropical regions, and greater humidity near the poles. While ecosystems were severely disrupted, most species—except deep-sea foraminifera—survived by adapting or migrating. This period also saw the rise of many modern mammal groups, including early primates, hoofed mammals (ungulates), and ancestors of whales (cetaceans). There were widespread shifts in plant and animal ranges across continents.\nNotably, many mammal species underwent dwarfing, likely due to higher temperatures and lower nutrient content in plants. Under elevated CO₂ levels, plants can grow faster but tend to have reduced nutritional value, which may explain why early horses shrank in size by 20–30%.\nThe PETM offers a valuable ancient parallel to today’s human-driven global warming, providing important insights into how Earth’s systems and species respond to rapid climate change.</string>
    <string name="paleogene_life_forms">Mammals underwent rapid diversification during the Paleogene period. Some evolved into large land-dwelling forms that would dominate terrestrial ecosystems, while others adapted to life in the oceans, eventually giving rise to modern whales and dolphins (cetaceans). Still others took to the trees and became early primates, the ancestors of monkeys, apes, and humans.\nBirds, already well established by the end of the Cretaceous, also experienced a major adaptive radiation. With the extinction of pterosaurs, they became the dominant flying vertebrates, spreading into a wide variety of ecological niches.\nAs the global climate cooled over the course of the Paleogene, tropical plant species became less widespread, retreating toward equatorial regions. In contrast, temperate forests and grasslands began to expand, shaping the habitats available for the evolving animal life.</string>

    <string name="neogene_physics">Mean temperature: 14 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 21.5%</string>
    <string name="neogene_description">The Neogene is a geological period that spans approximately 20.45 million years, following the Paleogene and preceding the Quaternary. It is subdivided into two epochs: the earlier Miocene and the later Pliocene. During the Pliocene, the formation of the Isthmus of Panama connected North and South America, reshaping ocean currents by cutting off warm Pacific waters from the Atlantic. This event intensified the Gulf Stream, helping transfer more heat toward the Arctic Ocean.\nThroughout the Neogene, Earth\'s global climate cooled significantly, setting the stage for the extensive glaciations of the Quaternary period. Around 20 million years ago, Antarctica was already covered by ice sheets, and northern continents experienced steady cooling. By this time, the world had begun to resemble its modern form, although regions like Florida and parts of Southeast Asia were still submerged under shallow seas.</string>
    <string name="neogene_additional_title">Cooler effect</string>
    <string name="neogene_additional">During the Neogene, the world became significantly drier and cooler, setting the stage for the dramatic climate changes of the Pleistocene ice ages and the challenging conditions of the present day. This period marked the end of the relatively uniform and stable climate that had supported Earth\'s ecosystems for nearly 200 million years, since the Late Triassic.\nAs continental drift continued, the northern continents moved closer together, sealing off the Arctic Ocean. The formation of the Isthmus of Panama blocked warm Pacific currents from entering the Atlantic, altering global ocean circulation. In the south, Antarctica — now isolated from other landmasses — became encircled by the Antarctic Circumpolar Current, further cooling the continent.\nFor the first time since the Ordovician, both poles were thermally isolated from equatorial warmth and began accumulating massive ice sheets. These ice sheets reflected more sunlight, lowering global temperatures and sea levels, and further reducing the circulation of warm water.\nAs the climate cooled and dried, vast deserts formed across North Africa and Central Asia. Lush interior forests gave way to arid plains, steppes, prairies, and tundras. Many herbivorous animals either went extinct or adapted to these new environments, along with their predators. By the end of the Neogene, Earth had come to resemble the world we know today.</string>
    <string name="neogene_life_forms">During the Neogene, mammals and birds continued to evolve into forms that closely resemble those of today, while some other groups remained relatively unchanged. Early hominins—the ancestors of modern humans—appeared in Africa near the end of this period and later began migrating into Eurasia.\nTropical plant species gradually declined, giving way to more temperate deciduous vegetation. Grasslands expanded significantly, replacing many former forested regions. As a result, grasses diversified, and many herbivorous mammals evolved specialized teeth and digestive systems to graze on them. This led to the rise of modern grazing animals, such as horses, antelopes, and bovids.</string>

    <string name="quaternary_physics">Mean temperature: 14 °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: 20.8%</string>
    <string name="quaternary_description">The Quaternary Period is the current and most recent of the three periods within the Cenozoic Era. It is divided into two epochs: the Pleistocene, marked by repeated glacial cycles, and the Holocene, which began approximately 11,700 years ago and continues today. The Quaternary is characterized by cyclic growth and retreat of massive continental ice sheets, driven primarily by variations in Earth\'s orbit and tilt, known as Milankovitch cycles. These cycles significantly influenced global climate patterns, sea levels, and biodiversity. The most recent major glaciation peaked around 21,000 years ago during the Last Glacial Maximum, and the ice sheets began their significant retreat about 12,000 years ago.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_additional_title">Ice Age</string>
    <string name="quaternary_additional">The Quaternary Period is characterized by repeated glaciations driven primarily by the previously mentioned Milankovitch cycles. Earth\'s axial tilt varies between approximately 22.1 and 24.5 degrees over a cycle lasting about 41,000 years. Currently, the tilt is 23.44 degrees, roughly midway between its extremes. A greater tilt increases seasonal contrasts, causing warmer summers and colder winters at higher latitudes, conditions that tend to inhibit glaciation. The Earth\'s tilt last reached its maximum around 10,700 years ago; now, it is decreasing and is expected to reach its minimum in approximately 9,800 years. This decreasing tilt trend promotes milder seasonal variation and a gradual overall cooling, potentially leading to conditions favorable for future ice ages.\nTo appreciate the impact of glaciations, consider three regions at similar latitudes—China, North America, and Europe. China\'s flora remains exceptionally diverse, preserving ancient plant species such as Ginkgo, Magnolia, and Thujopsis, which date back millions of years. Similarly, North America retains ancient species like Taxodium and Sequoiadendron. In contrast, Europe has virtually no ancient plant groups remaining, except a few species in the Mediterranean region. This notable difference is primarily due to geographic factors: during the last Ice Age, extensive ice sheets covered much of Europe. European plants attempting to escape southward faced formidable geographic barriers—the Alps and the Mediterranean Sea—both running predominantly east-west. Consequently, many plant species became extinct in Europe, though some, such as Platanus and Olea, survived in the Mediterranean region. North America, particularly along its eastern coastal regions, remained largely ice-free. Additionally, North American mountain ranges run north-south, providing natural migration corridors for plants fleeing southward ahead of advancing ice. China was largely free of extensive glaciation, allowing its ancient flora to persist with minimal disruption. Remarkably, before the Quaternary glaciations, Europe hosted lush forests filled with ginkgoes and magnolias, a stark contrast to today\'s ecosystems.\nQuaternary glaciations also significantly impacted human migration patterns, repeatedly hindering early human populations from settling permanently in Europe and occasionally wiping out established communities during colder climatic episodes.\nInterestingly, the cycles of glacial advance and retreat significantly shaped modern landscapes worldwide. Iconic features such as fjords, the Great Lakes in North America, and the fertile plains of northern Europe were sculpted directly by these glacial processes. Moreover, the fluctuating sea levels associated with these glacial cycles repeatedly created and destroyed land bridges, influencing the migration and evolution of numerous species, including humans.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_life_forms">The Quaternary is the modern geological period and reflects today\'s familiar fauna and flora. However, repeated glaciations significantly impacted terrestrial life, frequently causing widespread extinction of various plant and animal species. After the last Ice Age ended around 11,700 years ago, many large mammals of the Pleistocene, such as saber-toothed cats, woolly mammoths, mastodons, giant ground sloths, and Irish elk, became extinct worldwide. While climate change played a major role, human activities, including hunting and habitat alteration, also contributed significantly to these extinctions. Today, the legacy of these extinctions can be seen in ecosystems across the globe, influencing current biodiversity patterns and ecological relationships.</string>

    <string name="future_physics">Mean temperature: x °C\nAtmospheric oxygen: y%</string>
    <string name="future_description">Predicting the future is extremely difficult; however, as intelligent life forms, we can try to imagine it. \nEarth will eventually disappear, as the Sun has a finite lifespan and will one day engulf our planet—unless our future descendants find a way to move Earth elsewhere. It is estimated that Earth’s habitable-zone lifespan is around 7.79 billion years. Since we’ve already used up 4.56 billion of those years, we may have about 3.23 billion left—or possibly only 1.75 billion, according to some scientists. The planet will gradually become hotter, and there’s nothing we can do to stop it. The Sun is converting hydrogen into helium, and once a significant amount is used up, it will undergo internal changes and expand into a Red Giant. That’s the reality. \nBut this is the ideal scenario.</string>
    <string name="future_additional_title">Anthropogenic Future</string>
    <string name="future_additional" formatted="false">Life has already demonstrated its persistence and will to exist—it will continue to flourish, with or without humans. Recent trends and growing concern about ecology in society offer a bit of optimism. Just 20 years ago, many people still believed Exxon’s false claims that climate change wasn’t real, and issues like pollution were barely discussed. However, change will happen regardless of our hopes or efforts.\nThere is a hidden risk in our understanding of the economy. A country with an economic growth rate below 3% is often seen as growing too slowly. But what does 3% annual growth really mean? It means the economy doubles roughly every 20 years. Current trends show that economic growth is closely tied to increased energy consumption. Since the Industrial Revolution, our energy usage has skyrocketed, and we still rely heavily on carbon-rich fossil fuels. Renewable energy accounts for only a small fraction of global energy production.\nOne of the fundamental laws of physics states that energy use always generates heat. According to current estimates, in just 400 years we may require as much energy as the Sun produces—and if we continue using energy inefficiently, we could end up boiling our oceans. In 2,000 years, at the current pace, we would need the combined energy of all the stars in the Milky Way galaxy. Now consider the Milky Way’s minimum diameter of 100,000 light-years and ask yourself: can such a rate of consumption be sustained?\nIt is more likely that humanity will discover much more efficient energy sources and adapt to life on Earth, rather than continuing the current path of reshaping Earth to suit human needs.\nRight now, we are experiencing something similar to the Permian-Triassic extinction—only at a much faster pace. We are releasing enormous amounts of carbon dioxide, causing global temperatures to rise and melting polar ice caps that hold vast quantities of trapped methane. Ocean acidity has already increased in recent years, contributing to widespread coral reef die-offs. Anoxic zones are spreading. Forests, which should be absorbing carbon dioxide, are being cut down for economic gain. Sea levels are rising. Areas like Florida and parts of East Asia are already suffering from massive floods.\nCurrent events are steering life on Earth toward the next mass extinction. However, at least now these issues are receiving far more public attention and awareness than ever before.</string>
    <string name="future_life_forms">Life will always find a way to flourish—even in radioactive swamps filled with acid.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="archean_banded_iron_formation">Banded iron formations</string>
    <string name="archean_stromatolites">Stromatolites</string>
    <string name="archean_primaevifilum_amoenum">Primaevifilum amoenum</string>
    <string name="archean_acritarcha">Acritarcha</string>

    <string name="archean_banded_iron_formation_description">Banded iron formations (BIFs) are distinctive sedimentary rock units composed of alternating layers of iron-rich minerals and iron-poor silica-rich bands, typically red due to hematite. These formations provide critical evidence of early biological and geochemical processes.\nThe prevailing hypothesis suggests that BIFs formed in ancient oceans as a result of oxygen released by photosynthetic cyanobacteria. Their presence in the Early Archean suggests that life may have existed as early as 3.85 billion years ago.\nDuring this period, Earth\'s oceans contained vast amounts of dissolved iron. As photosynthetic organisms produced oxygen, the iron reacted with it, precipitating as iron oxides and accumulating in these layered deposits. BIFs are rare in younger geological periods because most of the dissolved iron in the oceans was eventually removed, marking the Great Oxidation Event around 2.4 billion years ago.</string>
    <string name="archean_stromatolites_description">Stromatolites are layered, accretionary structures formed in shallow water through the trapping, binding, and cementation of sedimentary grains by microbial mats, primarily composed of cyanobacteria.\nFossilized stromatolites provide some of the oldest direct evidence of life on Earth, with examples dating back over 3.45 billion years. They exhibit a variety of forms and structures, ranging from columnar to domal shapes. While stromatolites are typically associated with biological activity, some possess features consistent with abiotic precipitation, making their origin a subject of ongoing study.\nStromatolites reached their peak diversity around 1.25 billion years ago, after which they declined in abundance and morphological variety, likely due to the rise of grazing organisms. Today, modern stromatolites are rare and primarily found in extreme environments such as hypersaline lakes and marine lagoons, where high salinity deters most grazing animals.</string>
    <string name="archean_primaevifilum_amoenum_description">Primaevifilum amoenum is one of the oldest known bacteria, with fossilized remains discovered in Western Australia. It was a filamentous microorganism that primarily lived in individual clasts, though it may have been part of a loosely organized benthic microbial community embedded in mucilage.\nUnlike many early microbial fossils, its microfossils have not been detected in stromatolite-like laminated clasts, suggesting a different ecological niche. These findings contribute to our understanding of early microbial diversity and the environmental conditions of the Archean Earth.</string>
    <string name="archean_acritarcha_description">Acritarchs are small, organic-walled microfossils that are resistant to acid dissolution and remain taxonomically unclassified. They represent a diverse group of structures, including the resting cysts of various green algae and possibly other microorganisms. Some acritarchs may also be linked to the reproductive or protective stages of unknown ancient eukaryotic life forms.\nDue to their resilience and abundance in the fossil record, acritarchs serve as valuable biostratigraphic markers, helping scientists understand the evolution of early life and past environmental conditions.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="proterozoic_bangiomorpha_pubescens">Bangiomorpha pubescens</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_nemiana_simplex">Nemiana simplex</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_tribrachidium_heraldicum">Tribrachidium heraldicum</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_dickinsonia">Dickinsonia</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_cloudina">Cloudina</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_charnia">Charnia</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_grypania_spiralis">Grypania spiralis</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_spriggina">Spriggina</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_kimberella">Kimberella</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_rangea">Rangea</string>

    <string name="proterozoic_bangiomorpha_pubescens_description">Bangiomorpha pubescens is the earliest known sexually reproducing organism, dating to approximately 1.2 billion years ago. It belongs to the red algae (Rhodophyta) and is considered one of the first complex multicellular eukaryotes. The emergence of sexual reproduction was a pivotal moment in evolutionary history, not only because of the benefits of genetic recombination but also because it enabled the development of complex multicellularity. This evolutionary breakthrough laid the foundation for the diversification of eukaryotic life, making Bangiomorpha a crucial organism in the history of life on Earth.</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_nemiana_simplex_description">Nemiana simplex is one of the simplest sessile organisms of the Ediacaran biota, resembling a cnidarian-like jellyfish or a basal, soft-bodied polyp. It consists of a jelly-like sac that likely housed internal structures, though its anatomy remains poorly understood. Some hypotheses suggest it may have possessed small tentacle-like structures.\nIt is possible that this organism was entirely immobile, adhering to the seafloor, and fed through passive suspension feeding or direct absorption of dissolved nutrients from the water, possibly relying on microbial or algal matter for sustenance.</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_tribrachidium_heraldicum_description">Tribrachidium heraldicum was a tri-radially symmetrical organism that lived during the Late Ediacaran Period of the Proterozoic Eon, approximately 555 million years ago. It was a soft-bodied, benthic organism that likely rested on or was temporarily attached to the seafloor.\nUnlike most modern animals, Tribrachidium does not fit into any known major animal group, and its exact classification remains uncertain. It likely fed using a unique form of suspension feeding, generating microcurrents to capture organic particles suspended in the water.</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_dickinsonia_description">Dickinsonia is one of the earliest known organisms exhibiting bilateral symmetry, a body plan that later became dominant among modern animals. Its growth was likely indeterminate, as fossil specimens range from a few millimeters to approximately 1.4 meters in length. Evidence suggests that Dickinsonia grew continuously until it was buried by ocean sediments or otherwise perished.\nUnlike true bilaterians, Dickinsonia lacked a rigid body structure and may have absorbed nutrients directly from microbial mats on the seafloor. It spent most, if not all, of its life with its body in close contact with the sediment, possibly anchoring itself partially to the substrate.</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_cloudina_description">Cloudinids are among the earliest known animals with mineralized skeletons, dating to the late Ediacaran Period. Their fossils consist of millimeter-scale calcareous cones nested within one another, forming tube-like structures. The emergence of mineralized skeletons may indicate the evolution of more complex ecological interactions by the end of the Proterozoic Eon.\nUntil this time, most organisms were benthic filter feeders, but fossil evidence from the late Proterozoic suggests the first appearance of predators. The presence of boreholes in Cloudina fossils provides some of the earliest direct evidence of predation, marking a significant shift in the evolution of marine ecosystems.</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_charnia_description">Charnia is a highly significant fossil, as it was the first Precambrian organism to be formally described from undoubted Precambrian rocks. It is also thought to be among the earliest known animals capable of sexual reproduction. Although its frond-like appearance resembles that of a fern, Charnia was neither a plant nor an algae, as it lived in deep-water environments well below the photic zone, where photosynthesis is impossible.\nInstead, it is believed to have absorbed nutrients directly from the surrounding water, possibly through osmotrophy, a feeding strategy common among some modern marine organisms.</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_grypania_spiralis_description">Grypania is one of the oldest known macroscopic, multicellular organisms in the fossil record. Appearing as ribbon-like, coiled impressions up to several centimeters long, Grypania likely represented a eukaryotic alga, possibly an early form of photosynthetic life. Its simple, unsegmented shape suggests it lacked complex tissues, yet it was far larger than typical microscopic life of the time, indicating a significant evolutionary leap toward large, visible organisms. Fossils of Grypania have been found in North America, China, and India, showing that it persisted for over a billion years - a remarkable survival span in Earth’s history. It inhabited shallow marine environments, where it likely floated or attached to the sea floor, contributing to primary production in ancient ecosystems. Grypania’s existence marks a critical step in the transition from microbial worlds to the diverse multicellular life that would later flourish in the Cambrian Explosion.</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_spriggina_description">Spriggina was a small, bilaterally symmetrical organism from the Ediacaran biota, growing to about 3-5 centimeters (1-2 inches) in length. Its body was elongated and segmented, with a distinct head-like front end, making it one of the earliest known animals to show clear signs of a front and rear. The segments were arranged in a slightly offset, “glide reflection” pattern, a feature that has sparked debate over its evolutionary relationships - some researchers suggest it was an early arthropod or annelid relative, while others view it as part of an extinct lineage unique to the Ediacaran Period. Spriggina likely moved slowly across the sea floor, possibly grazing on microbial mats that covered the sediment. Fossils are best known from the Ediacara Hills of South Australia, where they preserve fine surface details of the creature’s body. Spriggina’s combination of symmetry, segmentation, and a differentiated body axis marks it as a key transitional form leading toward the complex animals of the Cambrian Explosion.</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_kimberella_description">Kimberella was a soft-bodied, oval-shaped organism that is widely regarded as one of the earliest animals showing evidence of bilaterality-a body plan with distinct left and right sides. Measuring up to 15 centimeters (6 inches) in length, it had a low, dome-like body covered by a flexible, non-mineralized “shell” or outer covering. The front of Kimberella’s body was broader and more rounded, while the rear tapered slightly, suggesting a clear direction of movement. Fossil evidence, including scratch marks preserved in the sediment, indicates it used a proboscis-like feeding organ to scrape microbial mats from the sea floor, much like modern mollusks use a radula. This has led many paleontologists to propose that Kimberella was an early stem-group mollusk, making it one of the oldest known members of the lineage leading to snails, clams, and squids. Fossils are best known from the Ediacara Hills of South Australia and the White Sea region of Russia. Kimberella’s anatomy and feeding traces offer a rare glimpse into the evolutionary steps that bridged simple Ediacaran life and the more complex, mobile animals of the Cambrian.</string>
    <string name="proterozoic_rangea_description">Rangea was a frond-like organism and one of the most iconic members of the Ediacaran biota. It consisted of six radially arranged, leaf-like fronds connected at a central base, giving it a symmetrical, star-shaped appearance when viewed from above. Each frond displayed intricate quilt-like branching patterns, thought to have maximized surface area for nutrient absorption. Rangea lacked a mouth, gut, or any internal organs, and instead likely absorbed dissolved nutrients directly from seawater-a feeding strategy common among many Ediacaran organisms. Anchored to the sea floor in shallow marine environments, it may have stood partially upright in the water column, swaying gently with currents. Fossils of Rangea have been found in Namibia, where fine-grained sediments preserved their delicate three-dimensional structure in remarkable detail. Its body plan is so unlike any modern animal that its evolutionary relationships remain uncertain, though it is often placed within the extinct group Rangeomorpha, a unique branch of multicellular life that vanished before the Cambrian Explosion. Rangea exemplifies the strange and experimental nature of life in the late Proterozoic oceans.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="cambrian_treptichnus_pedum">Treptichnus pedum</string>
    <string name="cambrian_conodonta">Conodonta</string>
    <string name="cambrian_archaeocyatha">Archaeocyatha</string>
    <string name="cambrian_trilobita">Trilobita</string>
    <string name="cambrian_wiwaxia">Wiwaxia</string>
    <string name="cambrian_myllokunmingia">Myllokunmingia</string>
    <string name="cambrian_pikaia">Pikaia</string>
    <string name="cambrian_anomalocaris">Anomalocaris</string>
    <string name="cambrian_opabinia">Opabinia</string>
    <string name="cambrian_marrella">Marrella</string>
    <string name="cambrian_foraminifera">Foraminifera</string>
    <string name="cambrian_hallucigenia">Hallucigenia</string>
    <string name="cambrian_nectocaris">Nectocaris</string>
    <string name="cambrian_omnidens">Omnidens</string>

    <string name="cambrian_treptichnus_pedum_description">Treptichnus pedum is a crucial trace fossil because it marks the first known burrowing behavior, helping to define the boundary between the Ediacaran and Cambrian periods.\nSince only its burrows have been found, scientists infer that the organism responsible for Treptichnus pedum lacked hard anatomical features such as shells or bones. It is likely related to modern priapulid worms, which also exhibit similar burrowing behaviors.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_conodonta_description">Conodonta were ancient, eel-like, jawless vertebrates whose fossilized elements serve as crucial index fossils for stratigraphic correlation. Although these tooth-like elements appear formidable, the animals themselves were likely not active predators, possibly due to the lateral placement of their eyes. Estimates suggest that conodonts ranged in body length from 1 to 40 cm, highlighting the diversity among these early chordates.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_archaeocyatha_description">Archaeocyatha were the first large skeletal animals and the earliest known reef builders of the Cambrian, thriving in warm tropical and subtropical waters. Some archaeocyaths lived as solitary organisms, while others formed colonies, contributing to the structure of early marine ecosystems.\nThey resembled hollow horn corals, with porous, cup-shaped skeletons composed of calcite, which allowed water to circulate through their bodies for filter feeding.\nAround 516 million years ago, archaeocyaths experienced a sharp decline, coinciding with the rapid diversification of demosponges, which may have competed for ecological niches.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_trilobita_description">Trilobites represent one of the earliest known groups of arthropods and are iconic examples of Cambrian marine life. They flourished throughout the Paleozoic Era but experienced a significant decline during the Devonian before going extinct at the end of the Permian.\nTrilobites were among the most successful early animals, thriving in the oceans for over 270 million years. They exhibited a wide range of lifestyles—some crawled along the seafloor as predators, scavengers, or filter feeders, while others swam through the water column, feeding on plankton.\nIf you ever visit Morocco, you will likely encounter many merchants selling trilobite fossils, as the Anti-Atlas Mountains are composed of Paleozoic rocks rich in these ancient arthropods.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_wiwaxia_description">Wiwaxia is a genus of soft-bodied, bottom-dwelling animals covered in rows of carbonaceous scales and long, sharp spines. These dorsal spines may have served as a defense mechanism against predators. Wiwaxia likely moved by contracting a slug-like foot on its underside, similar to modern mollusks.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_myllokunmingia_description">Myllokunmingia is a genus of basal chordates, measuring approximately 28 mm in length and 6 mm in height. It is one of the oldest known possible craniates, possessing a skull and skeletal structures made of cartilage. Its anatomy suggests it was an early step in vertebrate evolution, sharing characteristics with modern jawless fish.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_pikaia_description">Pikaia is one of the oldest known relatives of vertebrates, exhibiting a worm-like body and likely swimming in an eel-like manner. Fossils reveal key chordate features, including an elongated notochord, a dorsal nerve cord, and segmented myotomes—critical characteristics in the early evolution of vertebrates.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_anomalocaris_description">Anomalocaris was a marine predator closely related to ancestral arthropods. It was one of the largest animals of the Cambrian oceans, reaching up to a meter in length. It possessed highly sophisticated stalked eyes, each with at least 16,000 lenses, providing vision as acute as that of modern insects. Its circular mouth was lined with a ring of hardened plates, adapted for grasping and consuming prey.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_opabinia_description">Opabinia was a soft-bodied marine animal of modest size, measuring between 4 and 7 cm in length. Its segmented body featured lateral lobes for swimming and a fan-shaped tail for propulsion. The head had highly unusual characteristics, including five eyes, a downward-facing mouth positioned beneath the head, and a flexible proboscis likely used to grasp and transfer food to the mouth.\nOpabinia likely lived on the seafloor, using its proboscis to search for and capture small, soft-bodied prey.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_marrella_description">Marrella was a small arthropod from the Middle Cambrian, measuring up to 2 cm in length. It scavenged organic debris along the seafloor. Marrella is considered a stem-group arthropod, meaning it shares a common ancestor with most or all later major arthropod groups but does not belong to any modern lineage.\nDespite its superficial resemblance to trilobites, Marrella is not more closely related to them than to other arthropods.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_foraminifera_description">Foraminifera are a group of amoeboid protists characterized by a streaming granular ectoplasm, which they use for capturing food and interacting with their environment. They are commonly encased in an external shell, or test, composed of various materials and exhibiting diverse forms. Most foraminifera are marine, with only a few species known from freshwater habitats.\nTheir shells are typically made of calcium carbonate and are usually less than 1 mm in size, though some species can grow up to 20 cm. Foraminifera are widely used as index fossils, particularly for dating rock layers from the Permian, Jurassic, Cretaceous, and Cenozoic periods.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_hallucigenia_description">Hallucigenia is thought to be an early relative of modern velvet worms (onychophorans), though some researchers suggest a closer relationship to arthropods. Its quirky name reflects its unusual appearance and the eccentric history of its study. This small, tubular organism measured between 0.5 and 3.5 cm in length and had seven or eight pairs of slender legs, each ending in a pair of claws. Additionally, it possessed spiny dorsal projections, likely serving as a defense against predators.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_nectocaris_description">Nectocaris was a small, soft-bodied marine animal whose exact classification puzzled paleontologists for decades. Growing to about 5–10 centimeters (2–4 inches) in length, it had a flattened, kite-shaped body with two long, flexible tentacle-like appendages at the front, a pair of lateral fins for swimming, and a broad tail fan for steering. Its large, stalked eyes suggest it was an active visual hunter, likely preying on small arthropods and other soft-bodied creatures in Cambrian seas. Fossils from the Burgess Shale in Canada have revealed fine details of its anatomy, leading researchers to propose that Nectocaris may be an early relative of cephalopods, making it potentially the oldest known member of this group, hundreds of millions of years older than previously thought. Its streamlined body and predatory lifestyle hint at the early evolutionary experiments that would later produce squids, cuttlefish, and octopuses.</string>
    <string name="cambrian_omnidens_description">Omnidens was an enigmatic marine animal known only from its distinctive mouthparts, found in fossil beds in what is now China. Its name, meaning “all teeth,” refers to the circular arrangement of tough, tooth-like plates that formed its feeding structure. Based on these remains, paleontologists believe Omnidens may have been related to anomalocaridids - large, soft-bodied predators of the Cambrian seas, but it was even larger than most, with estimates suggesting a total body length of over 1 meter (3.3 feet). Its formidable mouth would have been well-suited for grasping and crushing prey such as trilobites and other hard-shelled animals. Though much of its anatomy remains a mystery, Omnidens highlights the diversity and evolutionary experimentation that characterized the Cambrian Explosion, when early animal life rapidly branched into a variety of forms.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="ordovician_orthoceras">Orthoceras</string>
    <string name="ordovician_pentecopterus">Pentecopterus decorahensis</string>
    <string name="ordovician_sacabambaspis">Sacabambaspis</string>
    <string name="ordovician_astraspis">Astraspis</string>
    <string name="ordovician_rugosa">Rugosa</string>
    <string name="ordovician_tabulata">Tabulata</string>
    <string name="ordovician_aegirocassis">Aegirocassis</string>
    <string name="ordovician_cameroceras">Cameroceras</string>

    <string name="ordovician_orthoceras_description">Orthoceras is a genus of extinct nautiloid cephalopods characterized by their long, straight, conical shells. These ancient marine animals lived during the Ordovician period and were among the earliest cephalopods. Based on their anatomy and the behavior of their modern relatives—squid, octopuses, cuttlefish, and the nautilus—it is likely that Orthoceras was a predator in the Paleozoic seas, hunting smaller marine creatures such as trilobites. Their streamlined shells allowed them to move through the water using jet propulsion, similar to modern cephalopods.</string>
    <string name="ordovician_pentecopterus_description">Pentecopterus decorahensis is the oldest known eurypterid, or "sea scorpion," dating back to the early Ordovician period. It could reach lengths of up to 1.83 meters, making it not only the earliest but also one of the largest arthropods ever discovered.\nSea scorpions were formidable marine predators that dominated coastal environments for millions of years, until their extinction during the Permian mass extinction event. They are closely related to modern horseshoe crabs—an ancient group of arthropods that still exists today.</string>
    <string name="ordovician_sacabambaspis_description">Sacabambaspis is a jawless fish and one of the earliest known vertebrates to possess skeletal tissues similar to those of modern vertebrates. It lived during the Ordovician period and had a distinctive armored head shield. Sacabambaspis also featured a primitive lateral line system—an early sensory structure still found in modern fish—that allowed it to detect vibrations and movement in the water.</string>
    <string name="ordovician_astraspis_description">Astraspis is one of the oldest known armored jawless fish, dating back to the Ordovician period. Its body was protected by large bony plates on the head and smaller, scale-like plates covering the rest of the body. It also had a mobile, flexible tail that aided in swimming, covered with small protective plate-like scales. Astraspis is significant in early vertebrate evolution as it shows the development of dermal armor, a key adaptation for defense in prehistoric seas.</string>
    <string name="ordovician_rugosa_description">Rugosa is an extinct order of corals that lived from the Middle Ordovician to the Late Permian. They existed in both solitary and colonial forms. Solitary individuals are commonly called horn corals due to their distinctive horn-shaped skeletons. Their hard skeletons were composed of calcite, which contributed to fossil preservation. Rugose corals played an important role in reef ecosystems before going extinct during the Permian mass extinction, also known as the Great Dying.</string>
    <string name="ordovician_tabulata_description">Tabulata is an extinct order of colonial corals that lived from the Early Ordovician to the end of the Permian period, coexisting with Rugosa. Their tightly packed, tube-like coral structures gave them a honeycomb-like appearance. Like Rugosa, their skeletons were composed of calcite, which helped preserve them as fossils. Tabulate corals were major reef builders in Paleozoic seas and played an important role in forming ancient marine ecosystems. They went extinct during the Permian mass extinction, the most severe extinction event in Earth\'s history.</string>
    <string name="ordovician_aegirocassis_description">Aegirocassis was a giant arthropod that swam in the ancient seas during a time when life was rapidly diversifying. Belonging to the anomalocaridids - a group better known from the Cambrian. Aegirocassis reached lengths of up to 2 meters (6.5 feet), making it one of the largest animals of its era. Unlike its predatory Cambrian relatives, this creature was a gentle filter feeder. It used long, comb-like spines on its head appendages to strain plankton from the water, much like modern baleen whales. Its body was equipped with pairs of flaps for propulsion and stabilization, allowing it to glide gracefully through the water. The discovery of Aegirocassis in Morocco revealed that some anomalocaridids had shifted from hunting to plankton-feeding, showing an early example of large filter-feeding in Earth’s oceans. Its name combines “Aegir,” the Norse sea god, with “cassis,” Latin for helmet, reflecting its oceanic nature and armored head.</string>
    <string name="ordovician_cameroceras_description">Cameroceras was one of the largest known orthoconic (straight-shelled) cephalopods, and a top predator of the Paleozoic seas. Its shell could reach lengths of 6-9 meters (20–30 feet), making it one of the biggest animals of its time. The long, tapered shell housed its soft body at the wider end, with tentacles extending forward to seize prey. Cameroceras had a beak-like mouth capable of crushing the hard shells of trilobites and other armored marine creatures, as well as softer-bodied prey. It propelled itself using jet propulsion, much like modern squids, by expelling water through a siphon. Fossils have been found in North America and parts of Europe, indicating it thrived in warm, shallow epicontinental seas. As an apex predator, Cameroceras played a key role in shaping Late Ordovician marine ecosystems, long before vertebrate predators rose to dominance.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="silurian_eurypterus">Eurypterus</string>
    <string name="silurian_pneumodesmus">Pneumodesmus</string>
    <string name="silurian_cooksonia">Cooksonia</string>
    <string name="silurian_baragwanathia">Baragwanathia</string>
    <string name="silurian_acanthodii">Acanthodii</string>
    <string name="silurian_entelognathus">Entelognathus</string>

    <string name="silurian_eurypterus_description">Eurypterus is an extinct genus of sea scorpions (eurypterids), and its fossils are among the most commonly found within this group. These ancient arthropods were both predators and scavengers, capable of growing up to 1.3 meters in length. While primarily aquatic, they possessed the ability to breathe air and walk on land for brief periods, possibly to move between water bodies or escape unfavorable conditions.</string>
    <string name="silurian_pneumodesmus_description">Pneumodesmus is the earliest known myriapod and the oldest documented creature to have lived on land. It is also the first arthropod discovered with a tracheal system, making it the earliest known oxygen-breathing animal on land. Its fossil, found in Scotland, dates back to approximately 428 million years ago, providing significant insights into the early colonization of terrestrial environments.</string>
    <string name="silurian_cooksonia_description">Cooksonia is an extinct group of primitive land plants, representing some of the earliest vascular plants. They include the oldest known plant to possess a stem with vascular tissue, which allowed efficient water and nutrient transport. Cooksonia lacked leaves, flowers, and roots, and they were typically small, standing only a few centimeters tall. Each branch terminated in a sporangium, a spore-bearing capsule, which played a crucial role in their reproduction.</string>
    <string name="silurian_baragwanathia_description">Baragwanathia is a genus of extinct Lycopodiophyta plants, considered one of the earliest known vascular plants. They had unbranched, strap-shaped microphylls (small, simple leaves), and their stems contained an actinostele, a primitive type of vascular bundle arranged in a star-like pattern. These features indicate that Baragwanathia was an early representative of clubmoss-like plants, which would later diversify significantly.</string>
    <string name="silurian_acanthodii_description">Acanthodians, sometimes called spiny sharks, are an extinct group of fish that shared characteristics with both bony (Osteichthyes) and cartilaginous fish (Chondrichthyes). Despite their common name, they are not true sharks but represent several independent phylogenetic branches of early jawed fish. Acanthodians are considered ancestors to modern cartilaginous fish, such as sharks and chimaeras, and are significant for being among the first vertebrates to develop jaws, a major evolutionary advancement.</string>
    <string name="silurian_entelognathus_description">Entelognathus is an ancient placoderm fish and represents one of the earliest known jawed vertebrates. It is the first fish to possess dermal marginal jaw bones, including the premaxilla, maxilla, and dentary, which are typically found in modern bony fish. This discovery provides important evidence of the evolutionary transition from armored jawless fish to jawed vertebrates.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="devonian_prototaxites">Prototaxites</string>
    <string name="devonian_wattieza">Wattieza</string>
    <string name="devonian_archaeopteris">Archaeopteris</string>
    <string name="devonian_tiktaalik">Tiktaalik</string>
    <string name="devonian_ichthyostega">Ichthyostega</string>
    <string name="devonian_bothriolepis">Bothriolepis</string>
    <string name="devonian_cladoselache">Cladoselache</string>
    <string name="devonian_dunkleosteus">Dunkleosteus</string>
    <string name="devonian_acanthostega">Acanthostega</string>
    <string name="devonian_materpiscis">Materpiscis</string>
    <string name="devonian_jaekelopterus">Jaekelopterus</string>
    <string name="devonian_xenacanthus">Xenacanthus</string>
    <string name="devonian_calamophyton">Calamophyton</string>
    <string name="devonian_elkinsia">Elkinsia</string>

    <string name="devonian_prototaxites_description">Prototaxites is a genus of ancient organisms that formed large trunk-like structures, up to 1 meter wide and reaching heights of up to 8 meters. Although it first appeared in the Late Silurian period, it reached its greatest diversity during the Devonian. Initially believed to be a giant fungus, recent discoveries indicate the presence of algal symbionts, suggesting that Prototaxites was more likely a lichen rather than a fungus in the strict sense.\nPrototaxites became extinct as shrubs and vascular trees rose to dominance, gradually replacing these massive structures in terrestrial ecosystems.</string>
    <string name="devonian_wattieza_description">Wattieza is a genus of prehistoric trees, considered to be the oldest known trees on Earth. They existed during the Middle Devonian period and were closely related to modern ferns and horsetails. Wattieza trees could grow up to 8 meters or more in height and reproduced by releasing spores, much like their modern relatives.</string>
    <string name="devonian_archaeopteris_description">Archaeopteris is an extinct genus of tree-like plants characterized by fern-like leaves. These plants could grow up to 10 meters in height, with trunks exceeding 1.5 meters in diameter. Archaeopteris thrived in wet soils, typically growing near river systems and within floodplain woodlands. It is considered a distant ancestor of modern gymnosperm plants, such as conifers, and played a significant role in forming some of the earliest forest ecosystems on Earth.</string>
    <string name="devonian_tiktaalik_description">Although it resembles an amphibian, Tiktaalik is a lobe-finned fish from the Late Devonian period, possessing many features similar to those of tetrapods. Tiktaalik is considered a key representative of the evolutionary transition from fish to amphibians. It exemplifies one of several ancient sarcopterygian fish lineages that developed adaptations for surviving in oxygen-poor, shallow-water habitats—environmental conditions that are believed to have driven the evolution of tetrapods.\nIt is thought that Tiktaalik was specialized for living in swampy, pond-like environments and may have occasionally used its uniquely adapted fins to move short distances over land.</string>
    <string name="devonian_ichthyostega_description">Ichthyostega is one of the earliest known tetrapods in the fossil record, living at the end of the Devonian period. It possessed lungs and limbs, adaptations that allowed it to navigate through shallow swamp waters. Although it resembles an amphibian, Ichthyostega is considered a stem group tetrapod and one of the closest known ancestors of modern amphibians. It had a fish-like tail and gills, but also possessed an amphibian-like skull and robust limbs, reflecting its transitional status between aquatic and terrestrial life.</string>
    <string name="devonian_bothriolepis_description">Bothriolepis is a widespread, abundant, and diverse genus of placoderms that thrived during the Middle to Late Devonian period. The largest species could reach about 1 meter in length. Bothriolepis was a bottom-dwelling, armored fish that primarily fed on detritus, algae, and small microorganisms, using its specialized mouthparts to sift through sediment.</string>
    <string name="devonian_cladoselache_description">Cladoselache is one of the earliest known shark groups, dating back to the Late Devonian period. These ancient sharks could grow up to 1.8 meters in length. They were fast and agile predators, characterized by having 5 to 7 gill slits and a short, rounded mouth. Unlike modern sharks, Cladoselache lacked scales and had a streamlined body, allowing for swift movement in the water.</string>
    <string name="devonian_dunkleosteus_description">Dunkleosteus is an extinct genus of armored placoderm fish that dominated the seas during the Late Devonian period - an era often called the “Age of Fishes,” when much of North America lay near the latitude of modern Rio de Janeiro. The largest species, Dunkleosteus terrelli, is regarded as Earth’s first vertebrate “superpredator.” First discovered on the shores of Lake Erie in 1867, Dunkleosteus has puzzled scientists for nearly 150 years. Because it was an arthrodire placoderm, only its heavily armored skull and jaw plates fossilized, while the rest of its body made mostly of cartilage - rarely preserved. Early reconstructions gave it a shark-like form and suggested lengths of up to 10 meters, but new research indicates those estimates were exaggerated. Based on comparisons with smaller, more complete relatives and the proportions of its 60-cm-long head, Dunkleosteus terrelli likely reached about 3.5-4 meters in length. This revision doesn’t diminish its fearsome reputation. Its body was likely short, thick, and powerful—more tuna-shaped than shark-shaped—with an enormous head and jaws lined with self-sharpening bony plates. The bite force has been estimated at over 6,000 newtons, among the strongest of any fish in history. A 3.5-meter Dunkleosteus may have weighed as much as a 4.5-meter great white shark, earning it the nickname “a wrecking ball with fins.” With a mouth nearly twice the size of a great white’s, it preyed on armored placoderms, ammonites, and early sharks, securing its place as the top predator of Devonian seas.</string>
    <string name="devonian_acanthostega_description">Acanthostega is an extinct genus of stem-tetrapods and is among the earliest vertebrate animals to have recognizable limbs. It represents an anatomically intermediate form between lobe-finned fishes and fully terrestrial tetrapods. Acanthostega could grow up to 60 cm in length and had eight digits on each hand, linked by webbing.\nDespite having limbs, Acanthostega was primarily an aquatic animal, likely inhabiting shallow, weed-choked swamps. Its limbs were not well adapted for walking on land, indicating that it was still more suited for life in water.</string>
    <string name="devonian_materpiscis_description">Materpiscis is a genus of placoderm fish that lived near what is now Western Australia. Known from only one specimen, it is unique for containing an unborn embryo preserved inside the mother, along with a mineralized placental feeding structure. This remarkable find makes Materpiscis the oldest known vertebrate to exhibit viviparity, or giving birth to live young.\nMaterpiscis is represented by a single species, Materpiscis attenboroughi, named in honor of Sir David Attenborough, who first highlighted the significance of the Gogo fish sites in his 1979 documentary series "Life on Earth."</string>
    <string name="devonian_jaekelopterus_description">Jaekelopterus was one of the largest arthropods to ever live, belonging to the group known as eurypterids or “sea scorpions.” With an estimated length of up to 2.5 meters, it was a top predator of Devonian rivers and estuaries. Its body was protected by a segmented exoskeleton, and it had powerful pincers at the front for seizing prey. Although related to modern horseshoe crabs and scorpions, Jaekelopterus was not a true scorpion. Fossil evidence suggests it inhabited brackish to freshwater environments, where it likely ambushed armored fish and other aquatic animals. Its sheer size and formidable claws make it one of the most iconic examples of Paleozoic “giant” arthropods, highlighting how different ecosystems were before the rise of land-dwelling vertebrate predators.</string>
    <string name="devonian_xenacanthus_description">Xenacanthus was an extinct genus of freshwater sharks that thrived in rivers and lakes for over 150 million years. Unlike the streamlined oceanic sharks we know today, Xenacanthus had a long, eel-like body and a distinctive spine projecting backward from the top of its head, possibly used for defense. Its dorsal fin extended along most of its back, giving it a ribbon-like silhouette. Fossil teeth suggest it fed on small fish and amphibians, adapted to freshwater ecosystems rather than open seas. Reaching lengths of around 1–2 meters, Xenacanthus was a successful and resilient predator, surviving multiple mass extinctions before disappearing in the Late Triassic.</string>
    <string name="devonian_calamophyton_description">Calamophyton was an early tree-like plant that played an important role in the greening of the Devonian landscape. It reached heights of about 2–4 meters and had a slender, branching trunk covered with short, twig-like branchlets. Unlike modern trees, it lacked true leaves, instead, its photosynthesis was carried out by these small branchlets. Calamophyton reproduced with spores and likely formed dense stands in floodplains and river valleys, stabilizing soils and creating new habitats for early terrestrial animals. Its presence contributed to the spread of forest-like ecosystems, influencing atmospheric oxygen levels and shaping the evolution of land life.</string>
    <string name="devonian_elkinsia_description">Elkinsia is considered the earliest known seed plant, marking a crucial evolutionary step in the history of life on land. Unlike spore-bearing plants, Elkinsia produced seeds—protective structures that allowed embryos to survive in harsher, drier environments and spread more effectively. It was a small, shrubby plant with branched stems and fern-like fronds that carried the ovules from which seeds developed. Fossils of Elkinsia, discovered in West Virginia (USA), show cup-shaped structures that enclosed the developing seeds, offering the first glimpse into how this innovation began. Though modest in appearance, Elkinsia’s reproductive breakthrough paved the way for the rise of vast forests of seed plants, including conifers and flowering plants, that would later dominate Earth’s ecosystems.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="carboniferous_lepidodendron">Lepidodendron</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_sigillaria">Sigillaria</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_calamites">Calamites</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_akmonistion">Akmonistion</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_helicoprion">Helicoprion</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_pederpes">Pederpes</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_pterogyrinus">Proterogyrinus</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_hylonomus">Hylonomus</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_archaeothyris">Archaeothyris</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_pulmonoscorpius">Pulmonoscorpius</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_arthropleura">Arthropleura</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_meganeura">Meganeura</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_megarachne">Megarachne</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_edestus">Edestus</string>

    <string name="carboniferous_lepidodendron_description">Lepidodendron was an extinct, tree-like lycopsid and a dominant component of the Carboniferous coal forest flora. These plants could grow over 30 meters tall, with trunks exceeding 1 meter in diameter. They are believed to have grown rapidly and lived for only 10–15 years. Most species were likely monocarpic, meaning they reproduced just once near the end of their life cycle. By the Mesozoic era, Lepidodendron and its relatives had largely disappeared, likely outcompeted by emerging woody gymnosperms such as conifers, which were better adapted to changing climates and soil conditions.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_sigillaria_description">Sigillaria was an extinct, tree-like lycopsid closely related to Lepidodendron. It could grow up to 30 meters tall and had a relatively short life cycle, characterized by rapid growth and reaching maturity within just a few years. Sigillaria was a prominent member of the Carboniferous coal forests, with its distinctive vertical leaf scars forming a pattern that gives the plant its name.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_calamites_description">Calamites was an extinct, tree-like horsetail and a major component of the Carboniferous coal swamps. It could grow up to 30 meters tall and had a hollow, jointed stem structure similar to modern horsetails, but on a much larger scale. Calamites often grew in dense stands along rivers and floodplains, contributing significantly to the formation of coal deposits.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_akmonistion_description">Akmonistion was a shark-like chimaera that lived during the Early Carboniferous. Males had a distinctive anvil-shaped crest instead of a dorsal fin, with barbs on top and a triangular patch of spines located in front of the crest on the head. Females likely resembled the males but may have lacked both the crest and the patch of spines. Akmonistion is sometimes informally called the “ironing board shark” due to the unusual shape of its crest.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_helicoprion_description">Helicoprion was a long-lived genus of shark-like fish known for its unusual spiral arrangement of teeth, often called a "tooth whorl." These teeth were positioned in the lower jaw and may have been used for slicing soft-bodied prey. Helicoprion could reach lengths of 3–4 meters, with some large specimens estimated to grow up to 7.5 meters. Although it resembled a shark, it was more closely related to chimaeras.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_pederpes_description">Pederpes is the earliest known tetrapod to show clear adaptations for walking on land. Although not classified as an amphibian, it represents a very basal (primitive) member of the tetrapod lineage. Pederpes measured about 1 meter in length and displayed features well suited for terrestrial life, such as forward-facing feet for more effective movement on land. It is currently considered the earliest known fully terrestrial vertebrate.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_pterogyrinus_description">Proterogyrinus was a reptile-like amphibian and one of the early tetrapods that likely shares ancestry with the first reptiles. It could venture farther from water than most contemporary amphibians and was a top predator in both terrestrial and aquatic environments. Proterogyrinus had strong limbs and a flexible body, allowing it to move efficiently on land while still being an effective swimmer.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_hylonomus_description">Hylonomus is the earliest known unquestionable reptile. It measured about 20 centimeters in length and resembled modern lizards in appearance. With its small, sharp teeth, it likely fed on small invertebrates such as millipedes and early insects. Fossils of Hylonomus have been found inside fossilized tree stumps, suggesting it may have used them for shelter or hunting.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_archaeothyris_description">Archaeothyris is the oldest known synapsid—the group of vertebrates that includes modern mammals and their extinct relatives. It resembled a modern-day lizard in appearance, but at around 50 centimeters long, it was one of the largest carnivores in the Carboniferous forests. Archaeothyris had sharp teeth and strong jaws, allowing it to prey on smaller vertebrates and insects.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_pulmonoscorpius_description">Pulmonoscorpius was a giant species of extinct scorpion that could grow up to 70 centimeters long. While its exact diet is not known, it likely preyed on smaller arthropods, and its powerful sting may have been capable of killing small early tetrapods. Pulmonoscorpius lived in the humid coal forests of the Carboniferous and is one of the largest scorpions known from the fossil record.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_arthropleura_description">Arthropleura was one of the largest known land invertebrates of all time and had few, if any, natural predators. It could grow up to 2.3 meters in length and about 50 centimeters in width. Like other Carboniferous arthropods, Arthropleura was able to grow so large due to the higher partial pressure of oxygen in Earth\'s atmosphere and the absence of large terrestrial vertebrate predators. This helps explain why similarly sized arthropods did not exist during later periods like the Cretaceous, despite similar oxygen levels.\nContrary to earlier and popular beliefs, Arthropleura was not a predator but an herbivorous arthropod, likely feeding on decaying plant material on the forest floor.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_meganeura_description">Meganeura was an extinct genus of giant dragonfly-like insects, with a wingspan reaching up to 65 centimeters. Like Arthropleura, they were able to grow so large due to the higher atmospheric oxygen levels and the absence of large aerial predators during the Carboniferous period. Meganeura is one of the largest known flying insects in Earth’s history.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_megarachne_description">Megarachne was once thought to be a giant prehistoric spider, but further fossil study revealed it was actually a eurypterid, or “sea scorpion”, closely related to other aquatic arthropods like Jaekelopterus. Measuring about 54 centimeters (21 inches) in length, it was far smaller than originally imagined, yet still an impressive predator for its time. Megarachne had a broad, rounded body, large grasping appendages for catching prey, and a flattened, paddle-like tail segment that helped it swim through the freshwater rivers and swamps of ancient South America. Its strong claws and sharp spines made it effective at capturing fish and other small aquatic animals. The initial misidentification as a spider fueled its fame, but the true identity of Megarachne tells a more accurate - and equally fascinating story about arthropod diversity in the Carboniferous Period, an era rich in giant insects and lush coal-forming forests.</string>
    <string name="carboniferous_edestus_description">Edestus was a prehistoric shark-like fish known for its bizarre, curved tooth blades that projected forward from both the upper and lower jaws. Unlike modern sharks, it didn’t continuously replace individual teeth—instead, the entire tooth row grew forward over time, creating a scissor-like cutting mechanism. Measuring up to 6 meters (20 feet) long, Edestus was a formidable predator in the warm, coal-rich seas and river deltas of the Late Carboniferous. Its unusual dentition has earned it the nickname “scissor-toothed shark,” and paleontologists believe it sliced through soft-bodied prey such as fish and cephalopods with powerful jaw movements. Fossils of Edestus have been found in North America, Europe, and Russia, revealing its wide distribution during an era when ancient oceans teemed with diverse early vertebrates.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="permian_glossopteris">Glossopteris</string>
    <string name="permian_dimetrodon">Dimetrodon</string>
    <string name="permian_titanophoneus">Titanophoneus</string>
    <string name="permian_estemmenosuchus">Estemmenosuchus</string>
    <string name="permian_gorgonops">Gorgonops</string>
    <string name="permian_cynodontia">Cynodontia</string>
    <string name="permian_eryops">Eryops</string>
    <string name="permian_diplocaulus">Diplocaulus</string>

    <string name="permian_glossopteris_description">Glossopteris was the largest and best-known genus of seed ferns that flourished in the Southern Hemisphere during the Permian period. These were woody, seed-bearing shrubs or trees, with some species reaching up to 30 meters in height. They thrived in waterlogged soils and eventually outcompeted older plant groups such as the lycopsids Sigillaria and Lepidodendron.</string>
    <string name="permian_dimetrodon_description">Dimetrodon was an extinct synapsid—a group more closely related to mammals than to reptiles. It could reach up to 4.6 meters in length and may have weighed as much as 250 kilograms. Dimetrodon was likely one of the apex predators of its time, feeding on fish and early tetrapods. Its distinctive sail, formed by elongated spines on its back, may have helped stabilize its spine or acted as a thermoregulatory device, allowing it to absorb or release heat depending on environmental conditions.</string>
    <string name="permian_titanophoneus_description">Titanophoneus—meaning "titanic murderer"—was a carnivorous dinocephalian therapsid that lived during the Middle Permian. It belonged to a group of early, mammal-like reptiles known for their bulky skulls and powerful jaws. The adult skull of Titanophoneus could reach up to 80 centimeters in length, with a long, heavy snout. Its total body length was about 2.9 meters, and it likely hunted other vertebrates in its ecosystem.</string>
    <string name="permian_estemmenosuchus_description">Estemmenosuchus, meaning "crowned crocodile" in Greek, was a large omnivorous therapsid that lived during the Middle Permian. It could grow up to 3 meters in length and is notable for the unusual horn-like structures on its skull, which may have been used for display or species recognition. Despite its fearsome appearance, it likely fed on both plants and small animals.</string>
    <string name="permian_gorgonops_description">Gorgonops were the dominant predators of the Late Permian. These saber-toothed therapsids could grow up to 3 meters in length and had powerful jaws equipped with two enlarged canine teeth, which could reach up to 12 centimeters. As agile hunters with sharp senses, they likely preyed on large herbivores, including early therapsids and reptiles.</string>
    <string name="permian_cynodontia_description">Cynodonts, meaning "dog teeth," were a group of therapsids that first appeared in the Late Permian. This lineage includes modern mammals—including humans—as well as their extinct ancestors and close relatives. Non-mammalian cynodonts were widespread across Southern Gondwana and already exhibited many skeletal features typical of mammals, such as differentiated teeth and a secondary palate. They likely laid eggs, similar to today’s monotremes like the platypus, and showed signs of warm-blooded metabolism. The presence of fur in many species suggests they had some capacity to regulate their body temperature.</string>
    <string name="permian_eryops_description">Eryops was a large, semi-aquatic amphibian and one of the dominant predators of the Early Permian swamps and floodplains. Growing up to 2 meters long, it had a broad, flat skull filled with sharp, conical teeth ideal for gripping slippery prey like fish. Its sturdy body and strong limbs suggest it could haul itself onto land, though it likely spent much of its time in or near water. Eryops breathed air with well-developed lungs, but its lifestyle was similar to that of modern crocodiles - lurking at the water’s edge to ambush prey. Fossils of Eryops are most famously found in Texas and New Mexico, providing insight into the early evolution of large terrestrial vertebrates.</string>
    <string name="permian_diplocaulus_description">Diplocaulus was a distinctive amphibian best known for its boomerang-shaped head, formed by long, sideways extensions of its skull. Growing up to about 1 meter in length, this unusual head shape may have helped it glide through water more efficiently or deter predators by making it harder to swallow. Diplocaulus lived in rivers and lakes, where it likely fed on small fish, insects, and other aquatic animals. Its fossils have been found mainly in North America and Morocco. As one of the most recognizable Paleozoic amphibians, Diplocaulus illustrates the experimental diversity of early tetrapods long before the dominance of dinosaurs.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="triassic_bennettitales">Bennettitales</string>
    <string name="triassic_morganucodon">Morganucodon</string>
    <string name="triassic_lystrosaurus">Lystrosaurus</string>
    <string name="triassic_pterosauria">Pterosauria</string>
    <string name="triassic_plesiosauria">Plesiosauria</string>
    <string name="triassic_ichthyosauria">Ichthyosauria</string>
    <string name="triassic_mystriosuchus">Mystriosuchus</string>
    <string name="triassic_plateosaurus">Plateosaurus</string>
    <string name="triassic_desmatosuchus">Desmatosuchus</string>
    <string name="triassic_longisquama">Longisquama</string>
    <string name="triassic_sharovipteryx">Sharovipteryx</string>
    <string name="triassic_tanystropheus">Tanystropheus</string>

    <string name="triassic_bennettitales_description">Bennettitales were extinct seed plants that resembled flowering plants due to their flower-like reproductive structures. Despite this similarity, they are more closely related to cycads, ginkgos, and conifers than to true flowering plants (angiosperms). The evolutionary relationships of Bennettitales remain debated, and while they are generally not considered direct ancestors of angiosperms, some studies suggest that certain members might share a common ancestry with them.</string>
    <string name="triassic_morganucodon_description">Morganucodon was an early mammaliaform cynodont that lived during the Late Triassic. It was a small, likely nocturnal animal, with a body length of up to 10 cm. Morganucodon is often cited as an example of the nocturnal bottleneck effect in early mammalian evolution.</string>
    <string name="triassic_lystrosaurus_description">Lystrosaurus was a herbivorous genus of therapsids that lived during the Late Permian and Early Triassic. It was roughly the size of a modern pig. At least one species of Lystrosaurus survived the Permian-Triassic mass extinction and, in the absence of many predators and herbivorous competitors, it became the most common terrestrial vertebrate of the Early Triassic. At one point, nearly 90% of all land vertebrates belonged to this single genus!</string>
    <string name="triassic_pterosauria_description">Pterosaurs were flying reptiles that lived from the Late Triassic to the end of the Cretaceous period. They were the first vertebrates to evolve powered flight. Although often mistaken for flying dinosaurs, pterosaurs did not belong to the Dinosauria clade; instead, they were close relatives within the larger group Archosauria, which also includes dinosaurs and crocodiles.</string>
    <string name="triassic_plesiosauria_description">Plesiosauria was a group of marine reptiles that lived throughout much of the Mesozoic Era, from the Late Triassic to the end of the Cretaceous. They had broad, flat bodies, short tails, and typically long necks with small heads, although some species had shorter necks and larger heads. Plesiosaurs breathed atmospheric air and gave birth to live young. Some evidence also suggests they may have been warm-blooded.</string>
    <string name="triassic_ichthyosauria_description">Ichthyosaurs were large marine reptiles that thrived during much of the Mesozoic Era, especially from the Early Triassic to the Late Cretaceous. Shaped like modern dolphins, they were fast swimmers and among the top marine predators of their time. Ichthyosaurs reached their peak during the Triassic and Early Jurassic, but their diversity declined afterward. Contrary to earlier beliefs, they were not outcompeted by plesiosaurs, as the two groups coexisted for millions of years. Instead, their extinction likely resulted from a combination of environmental changes and ecological shifts in marine ecosystems.</string>
    <string name="triassic_mystriosuchus_description">Mystriosuchus was a crocodile-like reptile that lived during the Late Triassic period. It could grow up to 4 meters long. Its skull and jaw structure suggest a primarily fish-based diet, with long, narrow jaws resembling those of modern gharials. Mystriosuchus belonged to the phytosaurs, an extinct group of semi-aquatic archosaurs that were similar in appearance to crocodiles but not closely related to them.</string>
    <string name="triassic_plateosaurus_description">Plateosaurus was a basal sauropodomorph dinosaur, part of the group that would later include some of the largest land animals on Earth, such as Diplodocus and Argentinosaurus. Fully grown individuals measured between 5 and 10 meters in length and weighed between 600 and 4,000 kilograms. Fossil evidence suggests they commonly lived for at least 12 to 20 years.</string>
    <string name="triassic_desmatosuchus_description">Desmatosuchus was an extinct genus of armored archosaurs that lived during the Late Triassic period. It could grow up to 4.5 meters in length and had a distinctive row of long shoulder spikes. Fossil evidence suggests it was likely herbivorous, although some researchers have proposed that it may have also fed on insects or small animals, making it possibly omnivorous.</string>
    <string name="triassic_longisquama_description">Longisquama was a genus of extinct reptile that lived during the Triassic period. It is best known for the long, scale-like appendages on its back. While once controversially proposed as a possible relative of birds, current evidence suggests that Longisquama is not closely related to the origin of birds. The structures on its back are now thought to be elongated scales rather than true feathers.</string>
    <string name="triassic_sharovipteryx_description">Sharovipteryx was one of the earliest known gliding reptiles, dating to the Middle to Late Triassic. It is known from a single fossil discovered in Central Asia. Unlike modern gliders, Sharovipteryx had a unique gliding membrane attached primarily to its hind limbs, giving it a distinctive appearance and flight style.</string>
    <string name="triassic_tanystropheus_description">Tanystropheus was a reptile that grew up to 6 meters long, with an extraordinarily elongated neck measuring about 3 meters—half its total body length. Although it resembles a dinosaur at first glance, it actually belonged to a different reptile group called Protosauria and is not closely related to long-necked dinosaurs like sauropods. Fossil evidence suggests Tanystropheus was likely aquatic or semi-aquatic and probably fed on fish and other small marine animals.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="jurassic_archaeopteryx">Archaeopteryx</string>
    <string name="jurassic_allosaurus">Allosaurus</string>
    <string name="jurassic_mamenchisaurus">Mamenchisaurus</string>
    <string name="jurassic_stegosaurus">Stegosaurus</string>
    <string name="jurassic_epidexipteryx">Epidexipteryx</string>
    <string name="jurassic_dilophosaurus">Dilophosaurus</string>
    <string name="jurassic_dimorphodon">Dimorphodon</string>
    <string name="jurassic_epidendrosaurus">Epidendrosaurus</string>
    <string name="jurassic_liopleurodon">Liopleurodon</string>
    <string name="jurassic_kentrosaurus">Kentrosaurus</string>

    <string name="jurassic_archaeopteryx_description">Archaeopteryx is a genus of bird-like dinosaurs that represents a transitional form between non-avian feathered dinosaurs and modern birds. The largest individuals may have resembled modern ravens in size and shape, but they also had jaws with sharp teeth, three clawed fingers on each wing, and a long, bony tail—traits inherited from their dinosaur ancestors.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_allosaurus_description">Allosaurus was a large bipedal predator that could grow up to 8.5 meters in length and was likely near the top of the Jurassic food chain. Its potential prey included ornithopods, stegosaurids, and juvenile or weakened sauropods. Some paleontologists suggest that Allosaurus may have exhibited cooperative behavior and hunted in groups, while others believe individuals were solitary and that multiple fossils found together may represent scavenging at a shared carcass. It may have ambushed large prey, using its powerful jaws in a hatchet-like motion to deliver slashing bites.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_mamenchisaurus_description">Mamenchisaurus was a genus of sauropod dinosaurs known for its extraordinarily long neck, which could make up about half of its total body length. The largest species may have reached up to 35 meters in length and possibly weighed between 50 and 75 tons. Its neck likely helped it feed across a wide area without needing to move its massive body, possibly giving it access to high or scattered vegetation in Jurassic forests.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_stegosaurus_description">Stegosaurus is a genus of armored dinosaurs known for their distinctive double row of large, bony plates along the back and the spiked tail, or thagomizer. These large, heavily built herbivores likely used their plates for thermoregulation, species recognition, or display rather than defense. The first Stegosaurus specimen was discovered during the “Bone Wars”—the famous fossil rivalry between paleontologists Edward Drinker Cope and Othniel Charles Marsh in the late 19th century.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_epidexipteryx_description">Epidexipteryx was a small, bird-like dinosaur that represents one of the earliest known examples of ornamental feathers in the fossil record. These long, ribbon-like tail feathers were likely used for display, possibly in mating rituals or for species recognition, rather than for flight.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_dilophosaurus_description">Dilophosaurus was one of the largest predators of the Early Jurassic period and is easily recognized by the pair of rounded crests on its skull. It measured around 7 meters in length and weighed approximately 400 kilograms. This dinosaur was inaccurately portrayed in the movie Jurassic Park—it did not have neck frills, could not spit venom, and was significantly larger than shown in the film.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_dimorphodon_description">Dimorphodon was a medium-sized pterosaur that likely lived in coastal regions during the Early Jurassic period. It had relatively short wings compared to other pterosaurs, suggesting it was not a strong flier. Instead, it may have relied on quick, flapping bursts of flight similar to those of modern chickens or woodpeckers. Its name means “two-form tooth,” referring to its distinctive combination of long and short teeth.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_epidendrosaurus_description">Epidendrosaurus was a sparrow-sized, feathered avialan dinosaur that likely lived in trees and fed on insects. It had elongated fingers with curved claws, which may have helped it climb or grasp branches. As one of the earliest known tree-dwelling dinosaurs, Epidendrosaurus provides important clues about the evolution of flight-related adaptations in birds.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_liopleurodon_description">Liopleurodon was a genus of large, carnivorous marine reptiles belonging to the Pliosauridae family, a subgroup of Plesiosauria. Fossils have been found mainly in England and France. Liopleurodon was a powerful swimmer, with strong flippers and a streamlined body, and typically grew to about 5–7 meters in length, though some fragmentary remains suggest the possibility of larger individuals.</string>
    <string name="jurassic_kentrosaurus_description">Kentrosaurus is a genus of stegosaurian dinosaur from the Late Jurassic period, known from fossils found in what is now Tanzania. It measured around 4.5 meters in length and weighed about one tonne. Kentrosaurus was a herbivore and likely lived in an environment with many predators, as suggested by its defensive adaptations—including a double row of plates and spikes along its back and tail, which may have served both protection and display functions.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="cretaceous_tyrannosaurus">Tyrannosaurus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_velociraptor">Velociraptor</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_spinosaurus">Spinosaurus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_pachycephalosaurus">Pachycephalosaurus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_triceratops">Triceratops</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_ankylosaurus">Ankylosaurus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_mosasaurus">Mosasaurus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_ammonite">Ammonoidea</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_therizinosaurus">Therizinosaurus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_tsintaosaurus">Tsintaosaurus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_deinocherus">Deinocheirus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_quetzalcoatlus">Quetzalcoatlus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_giganotosaurus">Giganotosaurus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_linhenykus">Linhenykus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_sarcosuchus">Sarcosuchus</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_microraptor">Microraptor</string>

    <string name="cretaceous_tyrannosaurus_description">Tyrannosaurus is arguably the most famous dinosaur, widely recognized from films such as “Jurassic Park” and “The Lost World.” It is also one of the best-represented large theropods in the fossil record. Tyrannosaurus lived during the Late Cretaceous in what is now western North America. The most complete specimen discovered measures approximately 12.3 meters in length and stands up to 3.7 meters tall.\nWhile no direct evidence of feathers has been found on Tyrannosaurus itself, many paleontologists believe it likely had feathers on at least some parts of its body, based on evidence from closely related species. Below is an artistic interpretation of T. rex.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_velociraptor_description">Velociraptor was a bipedal, feathered carnivore with a long, stiff tail and an enlarged, sickle-shaped claw on each hind foot. Like Tyrannosaurus, it is one of the most familiar dinosaurs thanks to its prominent role in the “Jurassic Park” films. In reality, however, Velociraptor was roughly the size of a large turkey — much smaller than the human-sized predators depicted in the movies. Fossil evidence confirms that real Velociraptors had feathers and were likely warm-blooded, sharing many traits with modern birds.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_spinosaurus_description">Spinosaurus was one of the largest known carnivorous dinosaurs — possibly even larger than Tyrannosaurus rex. It could grow up to 14.3 meters in length and weigh around 20 tonnes. Fossil evidence indicates that it primarily ate fish, and most scientists believe it hunted both on land and in water. Spinosaurus likely led a semi-aquatic lifestyle, similar to that of modern crocodiles, with adaptations such as paddle-like feet and a long, narrow snout ideal for catching prey in aquatic environments.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_pachycephalosaurus_description">Pachycephalosaurus was a bipedal herbivorous dinosaur best known for its extremely thick, domed skull roof, which could be over 25 centimeters thick. It lived during the Late Cretaceous and was among the last non-avian dinosaurs to exist before the Cretaceous–Paleogene extinction event. Some scientists believe it may have used its thick skull for head-butting or display behavior, though this remains debated.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_triceratops_description">Triceratops was a herbivorous dinosaur and one of the last known non-avian dinosaurs, living during the very end of the Late Cretaceous. It is estimated that Triceratops could grow up to 9 meters in length, 3 meters in height, and weigh around 12 tonnes. It is easily recognized by its large bony frill and three facial horns, which may have been used for defense, mating displays, or social interactions within the species.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_ankylosaurus_description">Ankylosaurus was a genus of heavily armored dinosaurs and among the last surviving non-avian dinosaurs, living during the Late Cretaceous. Large individuals could reach up to 6.25 meters in length, 1.7 meters in height, and weigh around 6 tonnes. Ankylosaurus is most famous for its massive club-like tail, which may have been used for defense against predators like Tyrannosaurus.\nRecent fossil discoveries suggest that some ankylosaurs may have had countershading — a form of camouflage where the body is darker on top and lighter underneath — providing protection from predators. This indicates a high level of predation pressure during the final stages of the Cretaceous.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_mosasaurus_description">Mosasaurus was an extinct genus of large, carnivorous marine lizards that lived during the Late Cretaceous. It could grow up to 17 meters in length, making it one of the top predators of its time. Fossil evidence suggests that it lived near the ocean surface, where it hunted a wide range of prey, including fish, turtles, ammonites, smaller mosasaurs, seabirds, pterosaurs, and plesiosaurs. Its long, streamlined body and powerful tail made it an efficient swimmer, and it likely used ambush tactics to capture its prey.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_ammonite_description">Ammonites were an extinct group of marine mollusks, closely related to modern squids and octopuses. They are well-known for their spiral shells and are considered excellent index fossils because they evolved rapidly and were widespread. Ammonites first appeared in the Devonian Period and thrived for hundreds of millions of years. They are mentioned here because they were among the most iconic marine creatures to go extinct during the Cretaceous–Paleogene extinction event.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_therizinosaurus_description">Therizinosaurus cheloniformis was a large and unusual theropod dinosaur that lived during the Late Cretaceous. It could reach up to 10 meters in length and weigh around 5 tonnes. Therizinosaurus is best known for its enormous claws — the longest of any known animal — which could grow up to 70 centimeters in length. Although it belonged to a group of theropods, which are typically carnivorous, Therizinosaurus was likely herbivorous, with long necks, small heads, and a beaked mouth adapted for browsing vegetation.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_tsintaosaurus_description">Tsintaosaurus was a herbivorous hadrosaurid dinosaur, easily recognized by its characteristic “duck-billed” snout and a battery of strong, closely packed teeth adapted for chewing tough vegetation. It measured about 10 meters in length and stood approximately 3.6 meters tall. Tsintaosaurus lived during the Late Cretaceous and may have had a hollow, unicorn-like crest on its head, although the structure and function of this crest remain subjects of scientific debate.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_deinocherus_description">Deinocheirus was a highly unusual dinosaur that lived during the Late Cretaceous. It could grow up to 11 meters in length and weigh around 6.4 tonnes, making it one of the largest members of the ornithomimosaur group. It had a pair of massive arms with long claws, which were likely used for foraging, possibly to dig or gather plants. Fossil evidence suggests that Deinocheirus was omnivorous, feeding on a mix of plants, small animals, and possibly fish. It is also thought to have been a slow-moving animal with a bulky build and a sail-like structure along its back.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_quetzalcoatlus_description">Quetzalcoatlus was a giant pterosaur and one of the largest known flying animals of all time. Its name is derived from the Mesoamerican feathered serpent god, Quetzalcoatl. With an estimated wingspan of 10–11 meters, it likely stood around 3 meters tall when on the ground. Quetzalcoatlus lived during the Late Cretaceous and may have soared long distances using thermal air currents. Despite its size, it is believed to have been capable of flight and may have hunted small animals or scavenged for food on land.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_giganotosaurus_description">Giganotosaurus was a giant theropod dinosaur that lived during the Late Cretaceous in what is now Argentina. It was comparable in size — and possibly even slightly longer — than Tyrannosaurus rex, though it was more lightly built. Like Tyrannosaurus, it is believed to have had a metabolism somewhere between that of modern reptiles and mammals, allowing it to maintain a relatively stable body temperature. Giganotosaurus was likely a top predator in its ecosystem, preying on large herbivorous dinosaurs such as sauropods.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_linhenykus_description">Linhenykus is the only known non-avian dinosaur to have had a single functional finger. It was a small-bodied theropod that lived during the Late Cretaceous in what is now Mongolia. Although its body shape resembles that of a modern ostrich, it was not closely related to birds like ostriches. Linhenykus belonged to a group called alvarezsaurids, which were specialized for digging and may have used their single large claw to break into insect nests, such as those of termites.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_sarcosuchus_description">Sarcosuchus was an extinct genus of crocodyliform and a distant relative of modern crocodilians. It was one of the largest crocodile-like reptiles to have ever lived and existed during the Early Cretaceous in what is now Africa and South America. Sarcosuchus could grow up to 11–12 meters in length and weigh as much as 8 tonnes — nearly twice the size of today\'s saltwater crocodile. It lived in freshwater environments and likely hunted both aquatic prey such as fish and terrestrial animals, similar to the behavior of modern Nile crocodiles.</string>
    <string name="cretaceous_microraptor_description">Microraptor was a genus of small, four-winged paravian dinosaurs that lived during the Early Cretaceous. Its exceptionally well-preserved fossils provide crucial evidence for the evolutionary link between birds and dinosaurs. Microraptor was one of the most abundant non-avialan dinosaurs in its ecosystem. Adult specimens are estimated to have reached up to 77 centimeters in length and weighed around 1 kilogram. It was an opportunistic predator that likely fed on small mammals, bird-like dinosaurs, lizards, and even fish, suggesting it may have been capable of gliding or controlled flight to ambush prey.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="paleogene_titanoboa">Titanoboa</string>
    <string name="paleogene_gastornis">Gastornis</string>
    <string name="paleogene_basilosaurus">Basilosaurus</string>
    <string name="paleogene_paraceratherium">Paraceratherium</string>
    <string name="paleogene_daeodon">Daeodon</string>
    <string name="paleogene_pyrotherium">Pyrotherium</string>
    <string name="paleogene_archaeotherium">Archaeotherium</string>
    <string name="paleogene_arsinoitherium">Arsinoitherium</string>

    <string name="paleogene_titanoboa_description">Titanoboa is the largest known snake to have ever lived, reaching lengths of up to 13 meters (about 43 feet) and weighing as much as 1.2 tonnes. It lived during the Paleocene epoch in the hot, humid tropical regions of what is now South America. Titanoboa likely hunted large fish in prehistoric rivers and swamps, using its massive size and strength to ambush and overpower its prey.</string>
    <string name="paleogene_gastornis_description">Gastornis were very large, flightless birds that lived during the Late Paleocene and Eocene epochs. They could grow up to 2 meters (about 6.5 feet) tall. While they were once thought to be fierce predators of small mammals, newer evidence suggests they were likely herbivores. The lack of hooked claws in fossilized footprints, along with studies of their massive, deep beaks, indicates that Gastornis probably fed on tough vegetation, hard seeds, and possibly fruits. These birds roamed forested environments and were among the largest land animals of their time.</string>
    <string name="paleogene_basilosaurus_description">Basilosaurus is a genus of early whales that lived during the Late Eocene epoch, around 40 to 34 million years ago. Unlike modern whales, which primarily feed on small prey like krill or fish, Basilosaurus was an apex predator that likely hunted large marine animals, including other whales and sharks.\nIt had an elongated, serpent-like body and still possessed small, vestigial hind limbs—a visible reminder of its land-dwelling ancestors. Below you can see some of the currently known transitional forms in whale evolution, showing how whales gradually adapted from land to sea.</string>
    <string name="paleogene_paraceratherium_description">Paraceratherium is an extinct genus of giant, hornless rhinoceros and is considered one of the largest land mammals to have ever lived. It stood about 4.8 meters (16 feet) tall at the shoulder, measured approximately 7.4 meters (24 feet) in length, and is estimated to have weighed between 15 and 20 tonnes.\nDespite its massive size, Paraceratherium was a herbivore, likely feeding on soft leaves and branches from tall trees. It lived during the Late Oligocene epoch across parts of Asia, where it roamed open woodlands and floodplains.</string>
    <string name="paleogene_daeodon_description">Daeodon is an extinct genus of large, pig-like artiodactyls that lived in North America during the Late Oligocene and Early Miocene epochs. Artiodactyls are even-toed ungulates, a group that includes modern animals like deer, pigs, and bison. Daeodon stood about 1.8 meters (6 feet) tall at the shoulder and had massive skulls measuring up to 90 centimeters (about 3 feet) in length.\nDespite their resemblance to pigs, Daeodon belonged to a distinct family called entelodonts, often nicknamed "hell pigs" due to their fearsome appearance. They had powerful jaws, large teeth, and were likely omnivorous—capable of eating both meat and plant matter. Their size and build suggest they may have been opportunistic predators or scavengers.</string>
    <string name="paleogene_pyrotherium_description">Pyrotherium is an extinct genus of large, herbivorous mammals that lived in what is now Argentina during the Early Oligocene epoch. Although not directly related to modern ungulates like pigs, cattle, or deer, they belonged to a unique and now-extinct South American lineage with some similarities in body structure. Pyrotherium stood about 1.5 meters (5 feet) tall and could weigh up to 3,500 kilograms (about 7,700 pounds).\nThese animals had strong, column-like limbs and short, tusk-like incisors, suggesting they fed on tough vegetation. Their fossil remains indicate a specialized herbivorous lifestyle, likely adapted to floodplains and forested environments.</string>
    <string name="paleogene_archaeotherium_description">Archaeotherium is an extinct genus of entelodonts—an ancient group of pig-like, omnivorous mammals—that lived in what is now North America during the Late Eocene to Early Miocene. Although they were distantly related to modern pigs, Archaeotherium belonged to a separate evolutionary branch. It stood about 1.2 meters (4 feet) tall at the shoulder and weighed around 270 kilograms (about 600 pounds).\nArchaeotherium had a large, heavy skull with prominent bony flanges on its cheeks, possibly used in display or combat. It was likely an omnivore, feeding on a mix of plants, carrion, and possibly live prey. Its strong jaws and powerful bite made it one of the more formidable mammals of its time.</string>
    <string name="paleogene_arsinoitherium_description">Arsinoitherium is an extinct genus of large, herbivorous mammals that lived in northern Africa during the Late Eocene and Early Oligocene epochs. Although they resembled modern rhinoceroses, they were more closely related to elephants, manatees, and hyraxes. Adult individuals stood about 1.75 meters (5.7 feet) tall at the shoulder.\nArsinoitherium inhabited tropical rainforests and coastal areas near mangrove swamps. It had a massive body, sturdy limbs, and a distinctive pair of large, forward-curving horns on its snout. These horns may have been used for display or combat. Despite their size and appearance, Arsinoitherium were peaceful plant-eaters, likely feeding on soft vegetation and aquatic plants.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="neogene_argentavis">Argentavis</string>
    <string name="neogene_ardipithecus">Ardipithecus</string>
    <string name="neogene_megalodon">Megalodon</string>
    <string name="neogene_levyatan">Livyatan</string>
    <string name="neogene_titanis">Titanis</string>
    <string name="neogene_deinotherium">Deinotherium</string>
    <string name="neogene_platybelodon">Platybelodon</string>
    <string name="neogene_stegotetrabelodon">Stegotetrabelodon</string>

    <string name="neogene_argentavis_description">Argentavis is one of the largest flying birds ever known, with an estimated wingspan of 5–6 meters, a height of 1.5–2 meters, and a weight of around 70 kilograms. It likely relied on soaring flight, using thermal air currents to glide across vast distances with minimal effort. Argentavis probably preferred scavenging for carrion, similar to modern vultures, but may have also hunted small animals. Its enormous size and wings made it a dominant presence in the skies of prehistoric South America during the Late Miocene.</string>
    <string name="neogene_ardipithecus_description">Ardipithecus is considered one of the earliest known ancestors of humans following the split from the main ape lineage, although its exact place in the evolutionary tree remains debated. It lived around 4.4 million years ago in what is now modern-day Ethiopia and shared some similarities with chimpanzees, such as a small brain size—ranging between 300 and 350 cm³, which is slightly smaller than that of modern chimpanzees and about 20% the size of a modern human brain.\nDespite these similarities, Ardipithecus also had features that distinguish it from chimpanzees, suggesting that the last common ancestor of humans and apes may not have looked like today’s chimpanzees. Notably, while chimpanzee feet are highly adapted for tree-climbing, Ardipithecus had a more versatile foot structure that allowed it to walk upright on the ground, marking an important step toward habitual bipedalism in human evolution.</string>
    <string name="neogene_megalodon_description">Carcharodon megalodon, commonly known as megalodon, was an enormous extinct species of shark that lived until near the end of the Neogene period. It was one of the largest and most powerful predators in vertebrate history, with estimates suggesting it could grow up to 18 meters in length. Fossil evidence shows that megalodon preyed on large marine animals, including whales, dolphins, and large fish, using its massive jaws and serrated teeth to deliver devastating bites.\nMegalodon likely went extinct due to a combination of factors, including a global drop in ocean temperatures, falling sea levels, and a decline in its primary food sources. As marine ecosystems shifted and competition with other predators—like early orcas—increased, megalodon\'s dominance in the oceans came to an end.</string>
    <string name="neogene_levyatan_description">Livyatan was a gigantic extinct species of toothed whale, comparable in size to the modern sperm whale, reaching lengths of nearly 18 meters. Unlike today’s sperm whales, Livyatan had massive, functional teeth in both its upper and lower jaws—up to 36 cm long—used to hunt large prey, including other marine mammals. Alongside the giant shark megalodon, it was one of the top apex predators of the Miocene oceans.\nLivyatan likely went extinct due to oceanic cooling at the end of the Miocene, which led to a decline in warm-water prey species. Fossils of this whale have been discovered in marine formations that also contain a diverse array of marine life, including sharks, dolphins, and seals, offering a glimpse into the rich ecosystems of Neogene seas.</string>
    <string name="neogene_titanis_description">Titanis walleri was a large, flightless, carnivorous bird that lived in North America during the Late Neogene, around 5 to 2 million years ago. Standing about 2.5 meters tall and weighing roughly 150 kilograms, it was a formidable predator. Titanis belonged to a group of birds known as terror birds (Phorusrhacidae), which were dominant land predators in South America during much of the early and middle Cenozoic era.\nUnlike most of its relatives, Titanis migrated northward into North America during the Great American Biotic Interchange, after the formation of the Isthmus of Panama. It had strong legs for fast running and a powerful beak capable of delivering deadly blows, likely hunting small mammals and other prey.</string>
    <string name="neogene_deinotherium_description">Deinotherium was a massive prehistoric relative of modern elephants that lived throughout the Miocene and Pliocene epochs. Unlike today’s elephants, Deinotherium had a shorter trunk and distinctive downward-curving tusks attached to its lower jaw. These tusks may have been used for stripping bark from trees or digging up roots.\nStanding up to 4 meters tall at the shoulder and weighing as much as 12 tonnes, Deinotherium was one of the largest land mammals of its time. Fossils have been found across Africa, Europe, and Asia, suggesting it was widely distributed in warm, forested environments.</string>
    <string name="neogene_platybelodon_description">Platybelodon was a large herbivorous mammal closely related to modern elephants, known for its unusual shovel-shaped lower jaw and flattened tusks. It lived during the Miocene epoch and inhabited regions of Asia and the Caucasus.\nIts unique jaw structure may have been used to scoop up water plants or strip bark from trees, functioning like a natural tool. Fossil evidence suggests that Platybelodon thrived in wet, forested environments near rivers and swamps.</string>
    <string name="neogene_stegotetrabelodon_description">Stegotetrabelodon was an extinct, primitive relative of modern elephants, notable for having four tusks instead of two—two upper tusks and two smaller ones in the lower jaw. It lived during the Late Miocene and early Pliocene, primarily in Africa.\nAlthough Stegotetrabelodon resembled modern elephants in body shape and size, its multiple tusks and more primitive skull features reflect an earlier stage in elephant evolution. Fossils suggest it inhabited open woodland and savanna environments. Below is an artist\'s interpretation of what Stegotetrabelodon may have looked like in life.</string>

    <!-- Next -->

    <string name="quaternary_mammutus">Mammuthus</string>
    <string name="quaternary_coelodonta">Coelodonta</string>
    <string name="quaternary_megatherium">Megatherium</string>
    <string name="quaternary_smilodon">Smilodon</string>
    <string name="quaternary_coelacanth">Coelacanth</string>
    <string name="quaternary_xiphosura">Horse-shoe crab</string>
    <string name="quaternary_ginkgo">Ginkgo</string>
    <string name="quaternary_welwitschia">Welwitschia</string>
    <string name="quaternary_tuatara">Tuatara</string>
    <string name="quaternary_human">Human</string>
    <string name="quaternary_dodo">Dodo</string>
    <string name="quaternary_megalania">Megalania</string>

    <string name="quaternary_mammutus_description">Mammoths were large mammals closely related to today\'s elephants, characterized by their thick insulating fur adapted for cold climates. Most mammoth species were roughly as large as modern Asian elephants, inhabiting vast areas of the northern hemisphere, including regions of Eurasia and North America. They primarily fed on grasses, shrubs, and small trees. Mammoths disappeared from Africa approximately 3–4 million years ago, and from Europe and mainland North America around 10,000 years ago. Remarkably, small populations persisted much longer, with the last known group surviving on Wrangel Island in the Arctic until about 3,750 years ago.\nThe extinction of mammoths was primarily driven by rapid climate warming around 12,000 years ago, which caused glaciers to retreat, sea levels to rise, and grassy tundra habitats—critical to mammoth survival—to diminish and be replaced by dense forests. Human hunting may also have played a role, especially in North America, where mammoths were actively hunted by early peoples, as evidenced by spearheads found alongside mammoth remains.\nToday, exciting scientific efforts are underway to potentially revive mammoths using advanced genetic techniques. Researchers in Japan and South Korea are independently working on extracting viable DNA from frozen mammoth remains to clone or genetically engineer mammoth-like creatures. Additionally, in northeastern Russia, the ambitious "Pleistocene Park" project led by scientist Sergey Zimov seeks to restore ancient ecosystems, preparing vast grasslands to potentially reintroduce cloned mammoths. This effort could even help slow Arctic permafrost melting by recreating conditions similar to those of the Ice Age. For further exploration, the VICE documentary titled "The Crazy Solution For Keeping The Melting Arctic Frozen" provides fascinating insights into this innovative ecological restoration initiative.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_coelodonta_description">Coelodonta, commonly known as the woolly rhinoceros, is an extinct genus of large, hairy rhinoceroses that roamed across Eurasia during the Pleistocene epoch. Equipped with thick fur, compact bodies, and large horns, these impressive animals were well-adapted to the harsh, cold environments of the Ice Age, grazing primarily on grasses and tundra vegetation. Like many other members of the Pleistocene megafauna, the woolly rhinoceros became extinct approximately 10,000 years ago, with the last known populations surviving in Western Siberia.\nWhile the exact reasons for their extinction remain debated, it is widely believed to be a combination of climatic shifts at the end of the Ice Age—resulting in significant habitat loss—and increased human activity, including hunting. Ancient cave paintings, such as those found in Chauvet Cave in France, vividly depict woolly rhinoceroses, demonstrating early humans\' familiarity with and perhaps admiration for these majestic creatures. Remarkably well-preserved remains, including fully intact carcasses with fur, skin, and even stomach contents, have been discovered in Siberian permafrost, providing extraordinary insights into their biology and lifestyle.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_megatherium_description">Megatherium was a genus of enormous ground sloths that roamed South America during the Pleistocene epoch. Comparable in size to modern elephants, Megatherium could weigh around 4 tonnes and reach lengths up to 6 meters. It inhabited diverse environments ranging from temperate grasslands to arid and semi-arid regions. With its powerful limbs, large claws, and robust tail for balance, it was perfectly adapted to feed on leaves and grasses, including plants like yuccas, agaves, and other tough vegetation.\nMegatherium became extinct approximately 10,000 years ago, likely due to habitat fragmentation and environmental changes associated with the end of the last Ice Age. However, human activity, such as hunting by early South American peoples, may have also contributed to their demise. Intriguingly, Megatherium fossils were among the first American fossils studied scientifically, described by Georges Cuvier in 1796. This impressive animal\'s skeletal remains astonished early naturalists and greatly influenced ideas about extinction and prehistoric life.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_smilodon_description">Smilodon, famously known as the saber-toothed cat, was one of the most iconic predators of the Quaternary Period. Roaming across the Americas until about 10,000 years ago, Smilodon was powerfully built, weighing up to 400 kilograms and standing around 120 cm at the shoulder. Its most distinctive features were the elongated canine teeth, some reaching lengths of nearly 30 centimeters, perfect for delivering devastating bites to large prey.\nSmilodon primarily hunted massive herbivores such as bison, camels, horses, and even juvenile mammoths, employing powerful limbs and muscular strength to wrestle prey to the ground. The extinction of Smilodon coincided closely with the disappearance of many large herbivores at the end of the last Ice Age, around 10,000 years ago. This was largely due to significant environmental shifts causing prey animals to become smaller, faster, and more elusive—conditions that favored quicker, lighter predators. Additionally, increased human competition and hunting pressure might have further accelerated their decline.\nInterestingly, thousands of exceptionally preserved Smilodon fossils have been recovered from the La Brea Tar Pits in Los Angeles, providing scientists with rare insights into the life and ecology of this fascinating predator.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_coelacanth_description">Latimeria, commonly known as the coelacanth, is an ancient lineage of lobe-finned fish often described as a "living fossil" because it closely resembles species known only from fossils over 360 million years old. Remarkably, coelacanths can live for 80 to 100 years and inhabit deep oceanic waters, often residing at depths of up to 700 meters. Their diet primarily consists of squid, small sharks, and other fishes.\nOne intriguing adaptation contributing to their survival is their ability to significantly slow down their metabolism, allowing them to conserve energy and survive long periods with minimal food. For many years, coelacanths were thought to have become extinct about 66 million years ago, until a living specimen was unexpectedly discovered off the coast of South Africa in 1938, astonishing the scientific community.\nToday, two known populations of coelacanths exist: one near Sodwana Bay in South Africa, and another around the Comoros Islands in the Indian Ocean. Due to their elusive nature and deep-sea habitat, coelacanths remain rare and mysterious, continuing to captivate scientists with clues about the evolutionary transition from aquatic to terrestrial vertebrates.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_xiphosura_description">Xiphosura, the group that includes horseshoe crabs, has remained largely unchanged for hundreds of millions of years, earning them the nickname "living fossils." These ancient arthropods are more closely related to spiders and scorpions than to true crabs and share evolutionary roots with the extinct trilobites, another dominant arthropod group of the Paleozoic Era. Horseshoe crabs have a hard, dome-shaped shell, long tail spine (telson), and multiple pairs of legs and gills adapted for both crawling and underwater breathing.\nOne of their most remarkable features is their bright blue blood, which contains a substance called Limulus Amebocyte Lysate (LAL). This compound is crucial in modern medicine, as it is used to test vaccines, IV drugs, and surgical implants for contamination by bacterial endotoxins. Thanks to this unique biological trait, horseshoe crabs have become essential for the safety of pharmaceutical products worldwide.\nDespite their importance, horseshoe crab populations face increasing threats from habitat loss, overharvesting for bait and biomedical use, and climate change. Conservation efforts are underway to protect these ancient creatures and ensure their survival into the future.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_ginkgo_description">Ginkgo is the only surviving species of the ancient plant division Ginkgophyta, earning it the nickname "living fossil." Fossil records show that Ginkgo trees have existed for over 270 million years, dating back to the Permian period. Once widespread across the globe, Ginkgo biloba is now native only to parts of China, where it was preserved in temple gardens and sacred groves for centuries.\nToday, Ginkgo is widely cultivated around the world for its distinctive fan-shaped leaves and exceptional resilience to pollution, pests, and disease. It holds cultural and medicinal significance, especially in traditional Chinese medicine, where its seeds and leaf extracts are used to support memory and circulation. Ginkgo nuts are also considered a delicacy in East Asian cuisine. Remarkably, some Ginkgo trees even survived the atomic bombing of Hiroshima, continuing to grow today as symbols of endurance and hope.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_welwitschia_description">Welwitschia is one of the three genera within the ancient plant division Gnetophyta and is often referred to as a "living fossil." Endemic to the Namib Desert in southwestern Africa, this remarkable plant is uniquely adapted to one of the harshest environments on Earth. Each individual Welwitschia plant produces only a single pair of strap-like leaves that grow continuously throughout its life, often becoming frayed and split over time.\nMany existing Welwitschia plants are estimated to be over 1,000 years old, with some believed to be more than 2,000 years old, making them among the longest-living plants in the world. Despite their strange appearance, Welwitschia plants are gymnosperms and are considered close relatives of modern flowering plants. Their ability to survive extreme aridity is supported by deep taproots and the absorption of moisture through specialized leaf surfaces.\nWelwitschia has fascinated scientists and botanists for centuries and is considered a national symbol in Namibia. Its slow growth, extreme longevity, and bizarre structure continue to intrigue researchers studying plant evolution and desert survival strategies.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_tuatara_description">Tuatara are unique reptiles endemic to New Zealand and are the only surviving members of the ancient reptile order Rhynchocephalia, which thrived around 200 million years ago during the age of the dinosaurs. Resembling lizards but genetically distinct, tuatara can grow up to 80 cm in length and weigh up to 1.3 kg. They are terrestrial and nocturnal, and unlike most reptiles, they thrive in cooler climates, remaining active at much lower temperatures. During the winter months, they enter a state of hibernation to conserve energy.\nTuatara are now classified as endangered, primarily due to habitat destruction and the introduction of invasive species such as rats, which prey on their eggs and juveniles. Conservation programs in New Zealand have been successful in protecting and reintroducing tuatara to predator-free offshore islands. Fascinatingly, tuatara possess a "third eye" (the parietal eye) on the top of their heads, visible in hatchlings, which may help regulate their circadian rhythms and hormone production. They also have one of the slowest growth and reproductive rates of any reptile, with some individuals living over 100 years. As living links to prehistoric reptiles, tuatara are often referred to as "living fossils" and are treasured symbols of New Zealand’s unique natural heritage.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_human_description">Human, or Homo sapiens, is the most successful large vertebrate species to ever roam the Earth. The estimated human population by 2017 was around 7.5 billion, and humans occupy most natural niches—except the deep oceans, salt lakes, deep caves, and Antarctica (although some specimens have been reported to live there, at least seasonally). It is currently listed as a species of “least concern” on the IUCN Red List of endangered species.\nTraditionally, there are two competing paleoanthropological theories about the origin of H. sapiens: the recent African origin and the multiregional origin. The more widely accepted single-origin theory states that modern humans appeared in East Africa and later migrated northward as glaciers retreated. They overwhelmed the northern-dwelling H. neanderthalensis, which were already suffering from reduced genetic diversity, and eventually migrated across the globe—killing and destroying most natural habitats and animal species in their path. Eventually, humans became apex, opportunistic predators. However, different human populations specialized in different types of food. For example: the Japanese are regarded as the most ferocious marine predators, killing thousands of whales, dolphins, sharks, and other sea animals each year; the Chinese are known for their passion for killing rhinoceroses, elephants, and other horned animals—they even recently wiped out the Northern White Rhinoceros in Africa, great job! European populations depleted their natural resources long ago, so they usually rely on other populations to bring them food and are best known for their manipulative skills, and so on.\nThe human creating this application is about 1.84 meters tall, weighs approximately 74 kilograms, and is alive thanks to photosynthesis.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_dodo_description">The dodo was a flightless bird endemic to the island of Mauritius, located east of Madagascar in the Indian Ocean. Standing about 1 meter tall and weighing up to 17 kg, the dodo was a close relative of modern pigeons and doves. Although often portrayed historically as fat and clumsy, the dodo was actually well-adapted to its predator-free island environment. It used gizzard stones to aid in the digestion of its diet, which mainly consisted of fallen fruits.\nThe first recorded mention of the dodo was by Dutch sailors in 1598. Over the following decades, it was hunted by humans and preyed upon by invasive species such as rats, pigs, and monkeys that were introduced to the island. Simultaneously, its forest habitat was rapidly destroyed. The last widely accepted sighting of a dodo occurred in 1662. Its extinction in less than a century after its discovery by Europeans became one of the earliest and most iconic examples of human-driven extinction.\nThe dodo\’s fate served as a powerful wake-up call to the scientific world, symbolizing the fragility of isolated ecosystems and the far-reaching impacts of human colonization and environmental disruption. Today, the dodo remains a global emblem of extinction and a lasting reminder of the importance of wildlife conservation.</string>
    <string name="quaternary_megalania_description">Megalania was a giant extinct lizard and a formidable member of the Pleistocene megafauna that once roamed southern Australia. Believed to have gone extinct around 50,000 years ago, it may have coexisted with the first Aboriginal settlers, who could have played a role in its disappearance. The largest individuals are estimated to have reached lengths of up to 7 meters and weighed between 600 and 620 kilograms, making Megalania the largest terrestrial lizard known to have ever lived.\nA powerful predator, Megalania fed primarily on medium to large-sized animals, including giant marsupials. It possessed strong limbs, a muscular tail, and a massive skull equipped with serrated, blade-like teeth capable of inflicting deep wounds. Some paleontologists suggest it may have had venom glands like its modern relative, the Komodo dragon, which would have made its bite even more lethal.\nMegalania\'s dominance in its ecosystem ended as Australia\'s climate shifted and human activities—including hunting and habitat modification—intensified. Its extinction marks one of many dramatic faunal changes following human arrival on the continent. Today, Megalania remains one of the most fascinating examples of prehistoric reptilian giants and a powerful symbol of Australia\'s lost megafauna.</string>

</resources>